<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1186</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01186</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>sierra-local: A lightweight standalone application for
drug resistance prediction</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0693-8940</contrib-id>
<string-name>Jasper C. Ho</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Garway T. Ng</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Mathias Renaud</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3779-154X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Art F. Y. Poon</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, Western
University, London, ON, Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Western
University, London, ON, Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Applied Mathematics, Western University,
London, ON, Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-11-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>33</issue>
<fpage>1186</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>bioinformatics</kwd>
<kwd>HIV/AIDS</kwd>
<kwd>drug resistance</kwd>
<kwd>sequence analysis</kwd>
<kwd>clinical virology</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Genotypic resistance interpretation systems for the prediction and
  interpretation of HIV-1 antiretroviral resistance are an important
  part of the clinical management of HIV-1 infection. Current
  interpretation systems are generally hosted on remote webservers that
  enable clinical laboratories to generate resistance predictions easily
  and quickly from patient HIV-1 sequences encoding the primary targets
  of modern antiretroviral therapy. However they also potentially
  compromise a health provider’s ethical, professional, and legal
  obligations to data security, patient information confidentiality, and
  data provenance. Furthermore, reliance on web-based algorithms makes
  the clinical management of HIV-1 dependent on a network connection.
  Here, we describe the development and validation of
  <italic>sierra-local</italic>, an open-source implementation of the
  Stanford HIVdb genotypic resistance interpretation system for local
  execution, which aims to resolve the ethical, legal, and
  infrastructure issues associated with remote computing. This package
  reproduces the HIV-1 resistance scoring by the web-based Stanford
  HIVdb algorithm with a high degree of concordance (99.997%) and a
  higher level of performance than current methods of accessing HIVdb
  programmatically.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="background-and-rationale">
  <title>Background and Rationale</title>
  <p>Genotype-based prediction of human immunodeficiency virus type 1
  (HIV-1) drug resistance is an important component for the routine
  clinical management of HIV-1 infection
  (<xref alt="Günthard et al., 2014" rid="ref-Gunthard2014" ref-type="bibr">Günthard
  et al., 2014</xref>;
  <xref alt="Tural et al., 2002" rid="ref-tural2002clinical" ref-type="bibr">Tural
  et al., 2002</xref>). Detecting the presence of viruses carrying
  mutations that confer drug resistance enables physicians to select an
  optimal drug combination for that patient’s treatment regimen.
  Furthermore, genotyping by bulk sequencing is a cost-effective
  alternative to the direct measurement of drug resistance from
  culturing virus isolates in a laboratory
  (<xref alt="Mayer et al., 2001" rid="ref-Mayer2001" ref-type="bibr">Mayer
  et al., 2001</xref>). Provided access to affordable bulk sequencing at
  an accredited laboratory for clinical microbiology, the interpretation
  of HIV-1 sequence variation is the primary obstacle to utilizing
  resistance genotyping for HIV-1 care.</p>
  <p>Fortunately, there are several HIV-1 drug resistance interpretation
  algorithms that can be accessed at no cost through web applications or
  services hosted by remote network servers, such as the Standard
  University HIV Drug Resistance Database (HIVdb)
  (<xref alt="Liu &amp; Shafer, 2006" rid="ref-shafer2006" ref-type="bibr">Liu
  &amp; Shafer, 2006</xref>), Agence Nationale de Recherche sur le SIDA
  (ANRS) AC11
  (<xref alt="Meynard et al., 2002" rid="ref-Meynard2002" ref-type="bibr">Meynard
  et al., 2002</xref>), and Rega Institute
  (<xref alt="Van Laethem et al., 2002" rid="ref-VanLaethem2002" ref-type="bibr">Van
  Laethem et al., 2002</xref>) algorithms. The Stanford HIVdb
  interpretation system can be accessed either through a web browser at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hivdb.stanford.edu/hivdb">http://hivdb.stanford.edu/hivdb</ext-link>
  or programmatically through its Sierra Web Service
  (<xref alt="Tang et al., 2012" rid="ref-tang2012hivdb" ref-type="bibr">Tang
  et al., 2012</xref>), which requires the transmission of an HIV-1
  sequence from a local computer over the network to the remote server.
  This is a convenient arrangement for clinical laboratories because
  there is no need to install any specialized software, web browsers are
  ubiquitous and most users are familiar with submitting web forms.
  Alternatively, a laboratory may host an instance of the HIVdb Sierra
  Web Service itself, which was recently made possible with the release
  of the Sierra source code. This approach, however, requires the
  configuration of a web server, the Apache Tomcat web container, and a
  large number of Java libraries.</p>
  <p>There are a number of disadvantages to accessing interpretation
  systems over a network connection. First, HIV-1 sequences are
  sensitive patient information, not only because infection with HIV-1
  remains a highly stigmatized condition, but also because sequence data
  have been used as evidence in the criminal prosecution of individuals
  for engaging in sexual intercourse without disclosing their infection
  status, leading to virus transmission
  (<xref alt="Bernard et al., 2007" rid="ref-bernard2007hiv" ref-type="bibr">Bernard
  et al., 2007</xref>). Once sequence data have been transmitted to a
  remote server, one cedes all control over data security. Preventing
  the onward distribution of the data and deleting the data once the
  analysis is complete, for instance, is entirely the responsibility of
  the system administrators of the host server. Furthermore, unless the
  host server employs a secure transfer protocol, the unencrypted data
  are transmitted in the clear between a number of intermediary web
  servers, exposing these data to a ‘man-in-the-middle’ attack
  (<xref alt="Patil &amp; Seshadri, 2014" rid="ref-patil2014big" ref-type="bibr">Patil
  &amp; Seshadri, 2014</xref>).</p>
  <p>Second, the algorithm hosted on the server is effectively a black
  box — one has no insight into how resistance predictions are
  generated. Even if a version of the algorithm has been released into
  the public domain, one cannot be certain that the exact same algorithm
  was applied to their transmitted data. Importantly, different versions
  of a given algorithm can output significantly different resistance
  predictions, with the general trend being an increase in both
  resistance scores and predicted resistance levels
  (<xref alt="Hart et al., 2018" rid="ref-Hart2018" ref-type="bibr">Hart
  et al., 2018</xref>). In addition to contributing to inconsistencies
  in algorithm outputs, this makes it difficult to track data
  provenance, <italic>i.e.</italic>, the historical record of data
  processing, that has become recognized as a critical gap in the
  workflows of clinical laboratories. For instance, the College of
  American Pathologists recently issued new accreditation requirements
  stipulating that clinical laboratories must track the specific version
  of software programs used to process patient data
  (<xref alt="Aziz et al., 2015" rid="ref-aziz2014college" ref-type="bibr">Aziz
  et al., 2015</xref>). Thus, a reliance on web-based systems creates
  significant issues for the reproducibility and quality assurance of
  clinical workflows. The Stanford HIVdb web service (Sierra
  (<xref alt="Tang et al., 2012" rid="ref-tang2012hivdb" ref-type="bibr">Tang
  et al., 2012</xref>)), for instance, automatically utilizes the most
  recent version of the HIVdb algorithm. While this constraint ensures
  that users employ the most up-to-date algorithm, it also introduces
  hidden changes to clinical pipelines, which may have been locally
  validated on older versions of the algorithm.</p>
  <p>Third, dependence on a web resource may cause problems when the
  laboratory cannot access the host server, either due to local or
  regional network outages, or because the host server is malfunctioning
  or offline. In our experience, the web servers hosting the more
  popular HIV drug resistance interpretation algorithms such as the
  Stanford HIVdb database are reliable and well-maintained. However, it
  is not unusual for other web-based algorithms to be relocated or go
  offline when the developers move to other institutions or lack the
  resources to maintain the service.</p>
  <p>One of the important features of the Stanford HIVdb algorithm is
  that it is regularly updated and released into the public domain in a
  standardized XML-based interchange format — the Algorithm
  Specification Interface version 2 (ASI2) format
  (<xref alt="Betts &amp; Shafer, 2003" rid="ref-betts2003asi" ref-type="bibr">Betts
  &amp; Shafer, 2003</xref>) — that was formulated and published by the
  same developers in conjunction with the Frontier Science Foundation.
  Here, we describe the implementation and validation of
  <italic>sierra-local</italic>, an open-source Python package for local
  execution of the HIVdb algorithm in the ASI2 format. This package
  utilizes, but does not require, a network connection to synchronize
  its local ASI2 file and reference data with the latest releases on the
  Stanford HIVdb web server. Our objective was to release a lightweight
  alternative to transmitting HIV-1 sequences to the HIVdb web server
  that minimizes the number of software dependencies, and that produces
  the exact same interpretations as the Sierra web service for all
  available HIV-1 sequences in the Stanford database.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="validation">
  <title>Validation</title>
  <p>We obtained the entirety of the genotype-treatment correlation
  datasets available through the Stanford HIV Drug Resistance Database
  (HIVdb
  (<xref alt="Shafer, 2006" rid="ref-shafer2006rationale" ref-type="bibr">Shafer,
  2006</xref>)) on May 7 2018. After screening for invalid data, the
  resulting dataset contained 103,711 HIV-1 protease, 110,222 reverse
  transcriptase and 11,769 integrase entries. We scored these data with
  both <italic>sierra-local</italic> and SierraPy (version 0.2.1,
  https://github.com/hivdb/sierra-client) using the HIVdb version 8.5
  algorithm on both platforms. Because the algorithm was updated to
  version 8.6.1 during the validation experiments, we used the newer
  version for the HIV-1 integrase data sets since the update mostly
  affected the interpretation of mutations within this region. Out of
  the total 226,702 sequence records, the predicted resistance scores
  were completely identical in 226,696 (99.997%).</p>
  <p>In addition, we retrieved 7 population-based HIV-1
  <italic>pol</italic> datasets from Genbank using the NCBI PopSet
  interface
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/popset">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/popset</ext-link>).
  These datasets were selected from the most recent uploads of
  substantial numbers of HIV-1 sequences covering the regions encoding
  both PR and RT, and representing a diversity of HIV-1 subtypes and
  sampling locations around the world
  (<xref alt="Arimide et al., 2018" rid="ref-arimide2018hiv" ref-type="bibr">Arimide
  et al., 2018</xref>;
  <xref alt="Rasmussen et al., 2018" rid="ref-rasmussen2017external" ref-type="bibr">Rasmussen
  et al., 2018</xref>;
  <xref alt="Wilhelmson et al., 2018" rid="ref-wilhelmson2018prevalence" ref-type="bibr">Wilhelmson
  et al., 2018</xref>). All resistance scores for all 1,006 sequences
  were completely concordant between the pipelines. Further details are
  provided in Ho et al.
  (<xref alt="2018" rid="ref-ho2018sierra" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="performance">
  <title>Performance</title>
  <p>Performance was evaluated on a workstation running Ubuntu 18.04 LTS
  with an Intel Xeon E5-1650 v4 hexa-core CPU at 3.60 GHz and 16 GB of
  DDR4-2400 RAM with a gigabit network connection.
  <italic>sierra-local</italic> achieved mean [range] processing speeds
  of 47.08 sequences/second (seq/s) [45.07, 48.49] for PR, 16.20 seq/s
  [14.01, 19.97] for RT, and 14.99 seq/s [14.79, 15.56] for IN. A
  substantial fraction of processing time was consumed by subtyping.
  SierraPy, with the same dataset as previously described, yielded mean
  processing speeds of 16.01 seq/s [12.88, 17.60] for PR, 6.12 seq/s
  [4.83, 7.54] for RT, and 5.19 seq/s [5.05, 5.47] for IN. Although the
  size of sequence batches used in this performance comparison likely is
  a factor in the results by virtue of file writing and reading being
  done once per batch, the large batch size used minimizes the effect of
  these I/O processes on the overall runtime. Overall,
  <italic>sierra-local</italic> is able to process and return results
  for submitted query HIV-1 <italic>pol</italic> sequences roughly 3
  times faster than SierraPy, depending on the nature of the sequences
  and the type of local computing resources available.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="concluding-remarks">
  <title>Concluding remarks</title>
  <p>The distribution of the HIVdb resistance genotyping algorithm in a
  standardized format (ASI
  (<xref alt="Betts &amp; Shafer, 2003" rid="ref-betts2003asi" ref-type="bibr">Betts
  &amp; Shafer, 2003</xref>)) is an important resource for HIV-1
  research and clinical management, and an exemplary case of open
  science. <italic>sierra-local</italic> provides a convenient framework
  to generate HIV drug resistance predictions from ASI releases in a
  secure environment and confers full control over data provenance. The
  ability to apply ASI-encoded algorithms locally (offline) also makes
  this part of the laboratory workflow robust to network availabilty may
  be particularly important for laboratories situated in
  resource-limited settings. We hope this lightweight, open-source
  implementation of the HIVdb ASI will further democratize HIV drug
  resistance genotyping across providers of HIV care.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We thank Philip Tzou for bringing NucAmino to our attention, and
  for his contributions to open science in the release of the Stanford
  HIVdb resistance program source code. This work was supported in part
  by the Government of Canada through Genome Canada and the Ontario
  Genomics Institute (OGI-131) and by a grant from the Canadian
  Institutes of Health Research (PJT-156178). The funders had no role in
  study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to
  submit the work for publication.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-ho2018sierra">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Jasper C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>Garway T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Renaud</surname><given-names>Mathias</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>Art FY</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sierra-local: A lightweight standalone application for secure HIV-1 drug resistance prediction</article-title>
        <source>bioRxiv</source>
        <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/393207</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shafer2006rationale">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>Robert W</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Rationale and uses of a public HIV drug-resistance database</article-title>
        <source>J Infect Dis</source>
        <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
        <volume>194</volume>
        <issue>Supplement_1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/505356</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-rasmussen2017external">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>David A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>Eduan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vandormael</surname><given-names>Alain</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tanser</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pillay</surname><given-names>Deenan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>Tanja</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>Tulio de</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Tracking external introductions of HIV using phylodynamics reveals a major source of infections in rural KwaZulu-natal, south africa</article-title>
        <source>Virus Evolution</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vey037</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-wilhelmson2018prevalence">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wilhelmson</surname><given-names>Sten</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Månsson</surname><given-names>Fredrik</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lindman</surname><given-names>Jacob Lopatko</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Biai</surname><given-names>Ansu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Esbjörnsson</surname><given-names>Joakim</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Norrgren</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>Marianne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Medstrand</surname><given-names>Patrik</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Prevalence of HIV-1 pretreatment drug resistance among treatment naı̈ve pregnant women in Bissau, Guinea Bissau</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0206406</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-arimide2018hiv">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Arimide</surname><given-names>Dawit Assefa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>Almaz</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kebede</surname><given-names>Yenew</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Adugna</surname><given-names>Fekadu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tilahun</surname><given-names>Tesfaye</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kassa</surname><given-names>Desta</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Assefa</surname><given-names>Yibeltal</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Balcha</surname><given-names>Taye Tolera</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Björkman</surname><given-names>Per</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Medstrand</surname><given-names>Patrik</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>HIV-genetic diversity and drug resistance transmission clusters in Gondar, Northern Ethiopia, 2003-2013</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0205446</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-tural2002clinical">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Tural</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>Lidia</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Holtzer</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schapiro</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Viciana</surname><given-names>Pompeyo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>González</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Domingo</surname><given-names>Pere</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rey-Joly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Clotet</surname><given-names>Bonaventura</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clinical utility of HIV-1 genotyping and expert advice: The Havana trial</article-title>
        <source>AIDS</source>
        <publisher-name>LWW</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-tang2012hivdb">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Michele W</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Tommy F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>Robert W</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The HIVdb system for HIV-1 genotypic resistance interpretation</article-title>
        <source>Intervirology</source>
        <publisher-name>Karger Publishers</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>55</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <uri>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22286876</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000331998</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22286876</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-bernard2007hiv">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>Edwin J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Azad</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weait</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Geretti</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>HIV forensics: pitfalls and acceptable standards in the use of phylogenetic analysis as evidence in criminal investigations of HIV transmission</article-title>
        <source>HIV Med</source>
        <publisher-name>Wiley/Blackwell (10.1111)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <uri>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1111/j.1468-1293.2007.00486.x</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1293.2007.00486.x</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17661846</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-aziz2014college">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>Nazneen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Qin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bry</surname><given-names>Lynn</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>Denise K.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>Birgit</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>Jane S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grody</surname><given-names>Wayne W.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>Madhuri R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hoeltge</surname><given-names>Gerald A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>Debra G. B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Merker</surname><given-names>Jason D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>Rakesh</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Palicki</surname><given-names>Linda A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Robetorye</surname><given-names>Ryan S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schrijver</surname><given-names>Iris</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weck</surname><given-names>Karen E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Voelkerding</surname><given-names>Karl V.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>College of American Pathologists’ laboratory standards for next-generation sequencing clinical tests</article-title>
        <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
        <publisher-name>the College of American Pathologists</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>139</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <uri>http://www.archivesofpathology.org/doi/10.5858/arpa.2014-0250-CP</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5858/arpa.2014-0250-CP</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25152313</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-betts2003asi">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>Bradley J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>Robert W</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Algorithm specification interface for human immunodefiency virus type 1 genotypic interpretation</article-title>
        <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
        <publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <isbn>0095-1137 (Print)$\backslash$n0095-1137 (Linking)</isbn>
        <uri>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12791935 http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC156534</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.41.6.2792-2794.2003</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12791935</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shafer2006">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Web resources for HIV type 1 genotypic-resistance test interpretation</article-title>
        <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
        <volume>42</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <uri>https://academic.oup.com/cid/article-lookup/doi/10.1086/503914</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/503914</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16652319</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Gunthard2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Günthard</surname><given-names>Huldrych F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Aberg</surname><given-names>Judith A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Eron</surname><given-names>Joseph J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hoy</surname><given-names>Jennifer F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Telenti</surname><given-names>Amalio</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>Constance A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>David M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cahn</surname><given-names>Pedro</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gallant</surname><given-names>Joel E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Glesby</surname><given-names>Marshall J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Saag</surname><given-names>Michael S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>David L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>Donna M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Volberding</surname><given-names>Paul A.</given-names></name>
          <string-name>International Antiviral Society-USA Panel</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Antiretroviral Treatment of Adult HIV Infection: 2014 Recommendations of the International Antiviral Society-USA Panel</article-title>
        <source>JAMA</source>
        <publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <volume>312</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <isbn>1538-3598 (Electronic) 0098-7484 (Linking)</isbn>
        <uri>http://jama.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?doi=10.1001/jama.2014.8722 http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25038359</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.8722</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038359</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Mayer2001">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>D’Aquila</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clinical use of genotypic and phenotypic drug resistance testing to monitor antiretroviral chemotherapy</article-title>
        <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <isbn>1058-4838</isbn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/319231</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11229846</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Hart2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>Stephen A. SA</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vardhanabhuti</surname><given-names>Saran</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Strobino</surname><given-names>Sarah A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>LJ Linda J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The impact of changes over time in the Stanford University Genotypic Resistance Interpretation algorithm</article-title>
        <source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>79</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>http://insights.ovid.com/crossref?an=00126334-900000000-96635 http://insights.ovid.com/crossref?an=00126334-201809010-00016</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAI.0000000000001776</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-VanLaethem2002">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Van Laethem</surname><given-names>Kristel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>De Luca</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Antinori</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cingolani</surname><given-names>Antonello</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Perno</surname><given-names>Carlo Federico</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>Anne Mieke</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A genotypic drug resistance interpretation algorithm that significantly predicts therapy response in HIV-1-infected patients</article-title>
        <source>Antivir Ther</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12212924</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Meynard2002">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Meynard</surname><given-names>Jean-Luc</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vray</surname><given-names>Muriel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Morand-Joubert</surname><given-names>Laurence</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Race</surname><given-names>Esther</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Descamps</surname><given-names>Diane</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peytavin</surname><given-names>Gilles</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Matheron</surname><given-names>Sophie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lamotte</surname><given-names>Claire</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Guiramand</surname><given-names>Sonia</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Costagliola</surname><given-names>Dominique</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Phenotypic or genotypic resistance testing for choosing antiretroviral therapy after treatment failure: A randomized trial</article-title>
        <source>AIDS</source>
        <publisher-name>LWW</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-patil2014big">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>Harsh Kupwade</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>Ravi</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Big data security and privacy issues in healthcare</article-title>
        <source>Big Data (BigData Congress), 2014 IEEE International Congress on</source>
        <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/BigData.Congress.2014.112</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
