<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2507</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02507</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>TTLocVis: A Twitter Topic Location Visualization
Package</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2346-2841</contrib-id>
<string-name>Gillian Kant</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0616-1027</contrib-id>
<string-name>Christoph Weisser</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-4702-3333</contrib-id>
<string-name>Benjamin Säfken</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Centre for Statistics, Georg-August-Universität Göttingen,
Germany</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Campus-Institut Data Science, Göttingen,
Germany</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-05-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>54</issue>
<fpage>2507</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Twitter</kwd>
<kwd>Topic Modelling</kwd>
<kwd>LDA</kwd>
<kwd>Latent Dirichlet Allocation</kwd>
<kwd>Visualization</kwd>
<kwd>Spatial Modelling</kwd>
<kwd>Geocoded Text</kwd>
<kwd>Hashtag-Pooling Algorithm</kwd>
<kwd>Natural Language Processing</kwd>
<kwd>Machine Learning</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The package TTLocVis provides a broad range of methods to generate,
  clean, analyze and visualize the contents of Twitter data. TTLocVis
  enables the user to work with geo-spatial Twitter data and to generate
  topic distributions from Latent Dirichlet Allocation (LDA) Topic
  Models
  (<xref alt="Blei et al., 2003" rid="ref-blei" ref-type="bibr">Blei et
  al., 2003</xref>) for geo-coded Tweets. As such, TTLocVis is an
  innovative tool to work with geo-coded text on a high geo-spatial
  resolution to analyze the public discourse on various topics in space
  and time. The package can be used for a broad range of applications
  for scientific research to gain insights into topics discussed on
  Twitter. For instance, the package could be used to analyze the public
  discourse on the COVID-19 pandemic on Twitter in different countries
  and regions in the world over time. In particular, data from the
  recently provided COVID-19 stream by Twitter can be analyzed to
  research the discussion about COVID-19 on
  Twitter.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref> In the following, an
  overview of TTLocVis will be provided. Finally, it will also be
  discussed how TTLocVis extends existing related software solutions.
  The installation of TTLocVis can easily be done via pip. Further
  details on the installation and the package can be found in the
  packages repository or on the documentation website of
  TTLocVis.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref></p>
  <sec id="statement-of-need">
    <title>Statement of Need</title>
    <p>In general, Topic Models are generative probabilistic models,
    that provide an insight into hidden information in large text
    corpora by estimating the underlying topics of the texts in an
    unsupervised manner. In Topic Models, each topic is a distribution
    over words that can be labeled by humans. For the purpose of
    labelling histograms and word clouds (for example, see graph)
    provide helpful visualizations for the decision-making process of
    the user
    (<xref alt="Blei et al., 2003" rid="ref-blei" ref-type="bibr">Blei
    et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
    <p>Firstly, the package allows the user to collect Tweets using a
    Twitter developer account for any area in the world. Subsequently,
    the inherently noisy Twitter data can be cleaned, transformed and
    exported. In particular, TTLocVis enables the user to apply LDA
    Topic Models on extremely sparse Twitter data by preparing the
    Tweets for LDA analysis by the pooling Tweets by hashtags. The
    hashtags pooling algorithm
    (<xref alt="Mehrotra et al., 2013" rid="ref-Mehrotra" ref-type="bibr">Mehrotra
    et al., 2013</xref>) is implemented in a parallelized form in order
    to speed up the heavy computational task. The goal of hashtag
    pooling is to supply the Topic Models with longer documents than
    just single Tweets to reduce the problems of Topic Models to process
    short and sparse texts. The pooling idea can be summarized into the
    following steps: Pool all Tweets by existing hashtags and check the
    similarity of an unlabeled Tweet with all labeled Tweets
    (hashtag-pools). Subsequently, the unlabeled Tweets join the
    hashtag-pool with the highest cosine similarity value, if the value
    exceeds a certain threshold. This process is repeated for all
    unlabeled Tweets. The resulting topic distributions that are
    computed with an LDA model that is trained on the pooled Tweets are
    substantially improved. When trained with sufficient data, clear
    topics can be generated, and the shortcoming of LDAs with short and
    sparse text are minimized.</p>
    <p>TTLocVis provides options for automatized Topic Model parameter
    optimization. Furthermore, a distribution over topics is generated
    for each document. The distribution of topics over documents can be
    visualized with various plotting methods (for example, see figure
    Word Cloud). The average prevalence of topics in the documents at
    each day can be plotted as a time series (for example see figure
    Time Series), in order to visualize, how topics develop over
    time.</p>
    <p>Above this, the spatial distribution of Tweets can be plotted on
    a world map, which automatically chooses an appropriate part of the
    world, in order to visualize the chosen sample of Tweets. As part of
    the mapping process, each Tweet is classified by its most prevalent
    topic and color coded (for example see figure Word Map 1 and figure
    World Map 2 for the spatial distribution of the same selected topics
    at different points in time).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="comparison-with-existing-tools">
    <title>Comparison with existing tools</title>
    <p>To the knowledge of the authors, no Python Package with a
    comparable functionality of TTLocVis is currently available. A web
    tool that is most related to TTLocVis is TweetViz
    (<xref alt="Stojanovski et al., 2014" rid="ref-stojanovski2014" ref-type="bibr">Stojanovski
    et al., 2014</xref>). TweetViz provides word clouds and topic
    distributions for Twitter data. However, TTLocVis improves on
    TweetViz by optimizing the LDA input with tweet pooling and options
    for geo-spatial and temporal analysis. Further, a major limitation
    of TweetViz is that the number of topics for the LDA estimation is
    always fixed at 20. TTLocVis gives the option to define a range of
    potential topic numbers and also includes an algorithm to select the
    optimal topic number according to coherence scoring.</p>
    <p>Alternatively, Twitter data may be analyzed with a web
    application
    (<xref alt="Malik et al., 2013" rid="ref-malik2013" ref-type="bibr">Malik
    et al., 2013</xref>) with an LDA Topic Model. The authors use
    so-called bins resembling time intervals for the Topic Model
    estimation. For each of these bins, an LDA Topic Model is estimated
    in order to account for the topical change over time. They then use
    cosine similarity to align the topics from several bins to a
    resulting topic. However, in this framework, Topic Models are
    estimated on very small samples on which LDA Models usually do not
    perform well. In contrast to this approach, the LDA Model is trained
    on pooled tweets in TTLocVis in order to improve the estimation
    results.</p>
    <p>A further web application
    (<xref alt="Onorati et al., 2019" rid="ref-onorati2019" ref-type="bibr">Onorati
    et al., 2019</xref>) offers functionality to generate word clouds,
    treemaps and map visualization. In contrast to TTLocVis, topics are
    not estimated by LDA, but rather by semantic relations. The focus of
    this application is on the contents of individual tweets with regard
    to disaster-related classification.</p>
    <p>A recent analysis of COVID-19 related Tweets can be found in the
    integration of the packages Birdspotter and Evently
    (<xref alt="Kong et al., 2020" rid="ref-kong2020" ref-type="bibr">Kong
    et al., 2020</xref>), in order to analyze retweet cascades.
    Birdspotter is a package to analyze the social influence and botness
    of Twitter users, while Evently can be used to model the temporal
    spread of information.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="figures">
  <title>Figures</title>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Time
    Series.<styled-content id="figU003ATimeU0020Series"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="figures/time_series.pdf" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Word
    Cloud.<styled-content id="figU003AWordU0020Cloud"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="figures/word_cloud.pdf" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>World Map
    1.<styled-content id="figU003Aworld-map-1"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/world_map1.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>World Map
    2.<styled-content id="figU003Aworld-map-2"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/world_map2.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Mehrotra">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>Rishabh</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sanner</surname><given-names>Scott</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Buntine</surname><given-names>Wray</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Lexing</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Improving LDA topic models for microblogs via tweet pooling and automatic labeling</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of the 36th international ACM SIGIR conference on research and development in information retrieval</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2484028.2484166</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-blei">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Blei</surname><given-names>David M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>Andrew Y.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>Michael I.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Latent dirichlet allocation</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Machine Learning Research</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jmlr.2003.3.4-5.993</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-malik2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>Sana</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Alison</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Papadatos</surname><given-names>Panagis</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jianyu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>Cody</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shneiderman</surname><given-names>Ben</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TopicFlow: Visualizing topic alignment of twitter data over time</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of the 2013 IEEE/ACM international conference on advances in social networks analysis and mining</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2492517.2492639</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-stojanovski2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Stojanovski</surname><given-names>Dario</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dimitrovski</surname><given-names>Ivica</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Madjarov</surname><given-names>Gjorgji</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Tweetviz: Twitter data visualization</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of the data mining and data warehouses</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-onorati2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Onorati</surname><given-names>Teresa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dı́az</surname><given-names>Paloma</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Carrion</surname><given-names>Belen</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>From social networks to emergency operation centers: A semantic visualization approach</article-title>
        <source>Future Generation Computer Systems</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.future.2018.01.052</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-kong2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Quyu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ram</surname><given-names>Rohit</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rizoiu</surname><given-names>Marian-Andrei</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evently: A toolkit for analyzing online users via reshare cascade modeling</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06167</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
<fn-group>
  <fn id="fn1">
    <label>1</label><p>https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/labs/covid19-stream/overview</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn2">
    <label>2</label><p>https://ttlocvis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/#installation</p>
  </fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
