<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">384</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00384</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>hmis: A python tool to visualize and analyze HMIS
data</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0920-3042</contrib-id>
<string-name>Sara Mahar</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-6353-6043</contrib-id>
<string-name>Matthew Bellis</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Siena College</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>18</issue>
<fpage>384</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>python</kwd>
<kwd>hmis</kwd>
<kwd>homelessness</kwd>
<kwd>homeless</kwd>
<kwd>continuum of care</kwd>
<kwd>open source</kwd>
<kwd>data visualization</kwd>
<kwd>data science</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Many organizations that work to combat homelessness receive funds
  from the US Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). These
  organizations might be overnight shelters or transitional housing or
  somewhere in between the Continuum of Care (CoC) provided by these
  groups. Since 2004, HUD has mandated that groups that receive these
  funds collect data on the homeless individuals that make use of these
  services. As such, there is a wealth of data that has been collected
  all over the country from a variety of organizations. Organizations
  have some freedom in how they collect and store these data, often
  making use of 3rd-party software solutions, but the data format is the
  same everywhere.</p>
  <p>This variety of data storage tools means that is is difficult for a
  data scientist at any of these organizations to dig into this data
  using standard, open-source computing tools like python or R. These
  groups can download the data in a standardized “HMIS data dump”, which
  results in 12 separate .csv files, but this still does not make any
  initial analysis any easier, a priori. These files have information
  about individuals’s name (hashed as a personal ID number), date of
  birth, prior living, disabilities, jail time, etc.</p>
  <p>This module contains a suite of python functions to allow for
  analysis and visualization of the data collected by the various
  partners across the CoC. Visualization includes time-series plots, and
  mapping of the locations of the programs individuals have entered.
  Analysis can be done with these visualizations and with the ability to
  withdraw individuals who share a common character. For example, the
  analyst can withdraw all of the individuals who have visited more than
  25 programs and then visualize them.</p>
  <p>We have developed these tools to work with the standard HMIS data
  dump in the RHY (Runaway and Homeless Youth) data format, that
  produces 12 .csv files in which personal identifying information is
  de-identified through a hashing algorithm. Because of this
  standardization, any other tools that leverage this software package
  can be used by similar networks across the country.</p>
  <p>The definitions of the information in the HMIS data can be found on
  HUD’s website
  (<xref alt="Housing &amp; Development, 2017" rid="ref-hmisdd2017" ref-type="bibr">Housing
  &amp; Development, 2017</xref> ;
  <xref alt="Housing &amp; Development, 2016" rid="ref-hmisdsdm2016" ref-type="bibr">Housing
  &amp; Development, 2016</xref>).</p>
  <p>This software project started thanks to the help and assistance
  from members of CARES NY (http://caresny.org/), a group committed to
  ending homelessness and who applies for grants from HUD and
  administers them with partners across the CoC. We would like to
  particularly acknowledge CARES members, Maureen Burns, Terry O’Brien,
  and Allyson Thiessen, who explained to us the need for tools like this
  and the data formats themselves. We also acknowledge members of the
  Siena College community, Ruth Kassel and Paul Thurston, for the
  initial connects with CARES, and their strong and continued support of
  this project.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-hmisdd2017">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Housing</surname><given-names>US Department of</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Development</surname><given-names>Urban</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>HMIS data standards data dictionary</article-title>
        <publisher-name>US Department of Housing; Urban Development; https://www.hudexchange.info/resource/3824/hmis-data-dictionary/</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-hmisdsdm2016">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Housing</surname><given-names>US Department of</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Development</surname><given-names>Urban</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>HMIS data standards data manual</article-title>
        <publisher-name>US Department of Housing; Urban Development; https://www.hudexchange.info/resources/documents/HMIS-Data-Standards-Manual.pdf</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
