<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1397</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01397</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>hankel: A Python library for performing simple and
accurate Hankel transformations</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3059-3823</contrib-id>
<string-name>Steven G. Murray</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-7686-4089</contrib-id>
<string-name>Francis J. Poulin</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>International Centre for Radio Astronomy Research (ICRAR),
Curtin University, Bentley, WA 6102, Australia</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>ARC Centre of Excellence for All-Sky Astrophysics in 3
Dimensions (ASTRO 3D)</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>School of Earth and Space Exploration, Arizona State
University, Tempe, AZ, 85281, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-4">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Applied Mathematics, University of
Waterloo</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-04-02">
<day>2</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>37</issue>
<fpage>1397</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>astronomy</kwd>
<kwd>numerical analysis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The Hankel transform is a one-dimensional functional transform
  involving a Bessel-function kernel. Moreover, it is the radial
  solution to an angularly symmetric Fourier transform of any dimension,
  rendering it very useful in several fields of application. The NASA
  Astronomical Data Service yields over 700 refereed articles including
  the term “hankel transform”, in fields as diverse as astronomy,
  geophysics, fluid mechanics, electrodynamics, thermodynamics and
  acoustics.</p>
  <p>As an example, in cosmology, the density field of the Universe is
  expected to be isotropic. One of the primary means of describing this
  field is via its Fourier power spectrum, or equivalently its spatial
  autocorrelation function. Due to the isotropy of the field, these can
  be related by an angularly symmetric Fourier transform, which is more
  simply expressed as a Hankel transform
  (<xref alt="Szapudi et al., 2005" rid="ref-Szapudi2005" ref-type="bibr">Szapudi
  et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
  <p>Another example that arises in both geophysical and astrophysical
  contexts is in regards to vortices. The radially-symmetric vortical
  solution to Laplace’s equation in two, three or even higher dimensions
  can be performed quickly and accurately via the Hankel transform
  (<xref alt="Carton, 2001" rid="ref-carton2001hydrodynamical" ref-type="bibr">Carton,
  2001</xref>).</p>
  <p>Conceptually, computation of such problems using the Hankel
  transform, in contrast to the Fourier transform, has the advantage of
  reducing the problem’s dimensionality to unity, regardless of the
  original dimensionality. Analytically, this <italic>may</italic> be a
  useful tool in solving the transform. Numerically, it naively promises
  to enhance efficiency.</p>
  <p>Despite these advantages, the Hankel transform introduces some
  numerical challenges. Most importantly, the Hankel transform is a
  <italic>highly oscillatory</italic> integral, especially for large
  values of the transformation variable, <italic>k</italic> (henceforth
  we will use <italic>r</italic> to denote the magnitude of the
  real-space co-ordinate). Highly oscillatory integrals are a topic of
  much interest in applied mathematics, and there does not exist a
  general optimal solution to numerically evaluate them in general
  (<xref alt="Huybrechs &amp; Olver, 2009" rid="ref-huybrechs_olver_2009" ref-type="bibr">Huybrechs
  &amp; Olver, 2009</xref>). Nevertheless, Ogata
  (<xref alt="2005" rid="ref-Ogata2005" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>)
  determined that a double-exponential variable transformation based on
  the zeros of the Bessel function
  (<xref alt="Ooura &amp; Mori, 1999" rid="ref-Ooura1999" ref-type="bibr">Ooura
  &amp; Mori, 1999</xref>) has the property that the numerical integral
  converges with many fewer divisions compared to naively computing the
  transform integral. This procedure is able to efficiently and
  accurately evaluate the Hankel integral (and hence the Hankel
  transform) in many cases.</p>
  <p>The purpose of <monospace>hankel</monospace> is to provide a
  dead-simple intuitive pure-Python interface for performing Hankel
  integrals and transforms, written with both Python 2 and 3
  compatibility. It enables the accurate determination of the transform
  of a callable function at any arbitrary value of the transform
  variable, <italic>k</italic>, and utilises the proven method of Ogata
  (<xref alt="2005" rid="ref-Ogata2005" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) to
  do this efficiently. In addition, it recognizes that the most common
  application of the Hankel transform is in the context of the radial
  Fourier transform, and it provides an additional interface dedicated
  to making the connection between these transforms more
  transparent.</p>
  <p>The chief performance-critical components of
  <monospace>hankel</monospace> are the evaluation of the zeros of the
  Bessel function, and the sum of terms required for integration. The
  former is made efficient by a tiered approach – using the efficient
  <monospace>scipy</monospace> for integer-order Bessel functions,
  directly returning regular arrays for order-1/2, and using the very
  accurate <monospace>mpmath</monospace> for all other orders. The
  latter is made efficient by utilising <monospace>numpy</monospace>,
  bringing it close to C-level performance.</p>
  <p>The <monospace>hankel</monospace> package is thoroughly tested to
  ensure accuracy of transforms, by comparing to known analytic
  solutions. These tests, supported by continuous integration, are also
  useful for the user who wishes to explore the numerical limitations of
  the method. Aside from functions which are theoretically divergent,
  the method can struggle to transform several classes of functions,
  including those with very sharp features, especially at small
  <italic>r</italic>. The method itself has two free parameters,
  <italic>h</italic> and <italic>N</italic>, which respectively
  determine the resolution and upper limit of the integration grid.
  These can be modified to accurately transform any function that
  theoretically converges. How to choose these values, and the estimated
  error of the transform under a given choice, are discussed in the
  <monospace>hankel</monospace>’s extensive online documentation (and
  the reader is referred to Ogata
  (<xref alt="2005" rid="ref-Ogata2005" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) for
  more details). Based on the arguments in the documentation,
  <monospace>hankel</monospace> provides an automatic, guided-adaptive
  algorithm for determination of <italic>h</italic> and
  <italic>N</italic>.</p>
  <p>A particularly important limitation of
  <monospace>hankel</monospace>, as currently implemented, is that it
  does <italic>not</italic> implement the <italic>discrete Hankel
  transform</italic>. That is, it provides no direct means of
  transforming an array of regular-spaced function values into “radial
  Fourier space” at regular-spaced <italic>k</italic> values. It is
  focused solely on transforming <italic>callable</italic> functions, so
  that it can evaluate that function at the non-regular locations
  required by the double-exponential transform of Ogata
  (<xref alt="2005" rid="ref-Ogata2005" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>).
  Extensions to discrete Hankel transforms (and even
  <italic>fast</italic> Hankel transforms) are envisioned for v2.0 of
  <monospace>hankel</monospace>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>The authors acknowledge helpful contributions from Sebastian
  Mueller during the construction of this code. Parts of this research
  were supported by the Australian Research Council Centre of Excellence
  for All Sky Astrophysics in 3 Dimensions (ASTRO 3D), through project
  number CE170100013. FJP would like to thank NSERC for research funding
  during the time of this research.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Ogata2005">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>Hidenori</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A Numerical Integration Formula Based on the Bessel Functions</article-title>
        <source>Publ RIMS Kyoto Univ</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2977/prims/1145474602</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Szapudi2005">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Szapudi</surname><given-names>István</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Prunet</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Budavári</surname><given-names>Tamás</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast Edge Corrected Measurement of the Two-Point Correlation Function and the Power Spectrum</article-title>
        <source>Arxiv E-Prints</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2005-05">2005</year><month>05</month>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/496971</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-huybrechs_olver_2009">
      <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Huybrechs</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Olver</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Highly oscillatory quadrature</article-title>
        <source>Highly oscillatory problems</source>
        <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/CBO9781139107136.003</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Ooura1999">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Ooura</surname><given-names>Takuya</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>Masatake</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A robust double exponential formula for Fourier-type integrals</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Computational and Applied Mathematics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year>
        <volume>112</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0377-0427(99)00223-X</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-carton2001hydrodynamical">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Carton</surname><given-names>Xavier</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hydrodynamical modeling of oceanic vortices</article-title>
        <source>Surveys in Geophysics</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
