<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3159</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03159</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>fctSnPM: Factorial ANOVA and post-hoc tests for
Statistical nonParametric Mapping in MATLAB</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-6807-0505</contrib-id>
<string-name>Robin Trama</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Christophe A Hautier</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-5960-8916</contrib-id>
<string-name>Yoann Blache</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Univ. Lyon, UCBL-Lyon 1, Laboratoire Interuniversitaire de
Biologie de la Motricité, EA 7424, F 69622, Villeurbanne,
France</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-11-06">
<day>6</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>63</issue>
<fpage>3159</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>MATLAB</kwd>
<kwd>statistical analysis</kwd>
<kwd>Statistical Parametric Mapping</kwd>
<kwd>Statistical nonParametric Mapping</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM) is a statistical method
  originally used in neuroimaging developed in the early 90’s in
  biomedical imaging, allowing to determine which brain zones were
  solicited during a functional MRI
  (<xref alt="Friston et al., 1995" rid="ref-FristonU003A1995" ref-type="bibr">Friston
  et al., 1995</xref>). Originally developed for a three dimensional
  analysis, the application of this method to the analysis of vectors or
  matrices was made possible thanks to Pataky
  (<xref alt="2010" rid="ref-PatakyU003A2010" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>)
  whom allows to perform statistical inference on curves (vectors - 1D)
  or maps (matrices - 2D).</p>
  <p>As in “classical” statistics on scalar values (0D), there is a
  parametric and a non-parametric approach to the SPM method. While the
  parametric method is based on random gaussian fields, the
  non-parametric method is based on label permutation tests
  (<xref alt="Nichols &amp; Holmes, 2002" rid="ref-NicholsU003A2002" ref-type="bibr">Nichols
  &amp; Holmes, 2002</xref>), and thus, on re-sampling and randomness to
  make statistical inference. The main advantage of the non-parametric
  approach is that a gaussian distribution of the data is not required,
  making possible it to work with both curves and maps.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>Most of physiological data measured during human movement are
  continuous and expressed in function of time. However, researchers
  predominantly analyze extracted scalar values from the continuous
  measurement, as the mean, the maximum, the amplitude, or the
  integrated value over the time. Analyzing continuous values (i.e.,
  time series) can provide more information than extracted indicators,
  as the later discards one dimension of the data among the magnitude
  and localization in time. In addition, oscillatory signals such as
  muscle vibrations and electromyograms contain information in the
  temporal and frequency domains. However, scalar analysis reduces the
  information at only one dimension by discarding two dimensions among
  the magnitude and the localization in the time and/or frequency
  domain.</p>
  <p>To analyze all the dimensions of a signal without losing
  information, the analysis of curves or maps was proposed, coded, and
  put online by Pataky. However, the use of the proposed functions does
  not allow the analysis of 2D data automatically. Moreover, a rather
  frequent error is to consider only the significance of the last
  statistical test performed and not the intersection between the
  post-hoc tests and the ANOVA. Indeed, a difference between two samples
  can be significant if, and only if the ANOVA is significant in the
  same areas. The spm1d package, redistributed with fctSnPM at
  <monospace>./fctSnPM/src/spm1d_Pataky</monospace> is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/0todd0000/spm1dmatlab">published
  elsewhere</ext-link>, and thus is not part of this JOSS review.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="fctsnpm">
  <title>fctSnPM</title>
  <p>The function we propose meets two objectives. 1/ to allow
  statistical inferences on curves and maps with a standardized format
  and 2/ to simplify analyses by comparing means while considering
  intersections with tests performed upstream (ANOVA and post-hoc of
  main effects).</p>
  <p>The statistical tests are performed taking into account the
  independent and repeated measure effects provided in the obligatory
  function inputs. ANOVA, up to three-way ANOVA with three repeated
  measures, is performed if required, and followed by post-hoc tests as
  paired or independent Student t-tests. By default, the ANOVA is
  performed with an alpha risk of 5%, while post-hoc tests alpha risk is
  adjusted with Bonferronni correction. A number of 10/alpha
  permutations (200 for a 5% risk) is defined for each test. Statistical
  parameters are customizable via optional inputs, like
  <monospace>multiPerm</monospace> which can be used to increase the
  number of permutations and achieve numerical stability and reliable
  analysis
  (<xref alt="Nichols &amp; Holmes, 2002" rid="ref-NicholsU003A2002" ref-type="bibr">Nichols
  &amp; Holmes, 2002</xref>). A Matlab (.mat) file containing the number
  of permutations, the significant clusters, the statistical thresholds,
  and the raw data used in the analysis is also generated for each test
  family.</p>
  <p>To interpret the results, figures directly usable for presentations
  and/or articles are available. In one dimension, the main figure
  contains the mean and standard deviations for each group of the
  analyzed condition, and the results of the post-hoc tests corrected
  with the result of the ANOVA. In two dimensions, the mean maps and the
  standard deviations are on two separate figures, and the result of the
  statistical analysis is displayed on the map of differences between
  two modalities. Therewith, other figures that display absolute and
  relative differences, effect sizes, and the raw value of the
  statistical test and its threshold are available.</p>
  <p>To personalize the figures, Matlab (.fig) files are implemented to
  perform a posteriori modifications, and optional inputs are available
  to a priori customize the figures. These parameters are gathered in
  three categories: 1/ general plot parameters working identically for
  one and two dimensions, acting on axis labels and limits, image
  resolution and size 2/ one dimension parameters that act on the
  characteristics of the curves like color and transparency, or the
  position of the statistical analysis relatively to curves 3/ two
  dimensions parameters acting on the colormap and its limits, as well
  as the color of the statistical test displayed on map of
  differences.</p>
  <p>This function was already used in Trama et al.
  (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-TramaU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)
  to compare soft-tissue and muscle vibrations of the <italic>vastus
  lateralis</italic>. It is currently used to assess modifications of
  soft-tissue vibrations caused by mountain ultra-marathons, the effect
  of the pedaling phase on <italic>quadriceps</italic> soft-tissue
  vibrations, and differences in isokinetic torque after ACL operation
  and rehabilitation.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-FristonU003A1995">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>KJ.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>AP.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Worsley</surname><given-names>KJ.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Poline</surname><given-names>JB.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Frith</surname><given-names>CD.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Frackowiak</surname><given-names>RSJ.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Statistical parametric maps in functional imaging: a general linear approach</article-title>
        <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.460020402</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-PatakyU003A2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Pataky</surname><given-names>TC.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Generalized n-dimensional biomechanical field analysis using statistical parametric mapping</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Biomechanics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>43</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiomech.2010.03.008</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-NicholsU003A2002">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>TE.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>AP.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nonparametric permutation tests for functional neuroimaging: a primer with examples</article-title>
        <source>Human Brain Mapping</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.1058</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-TramaU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Trama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hautier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Souron</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lapole</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fouré</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Blache</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Is accelerometry an effective method to assess muscle vibrations in comparison to ultrafast ultrasonography</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <volume>68</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TBME.2020.3035838</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
