<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2484</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02484</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Science Capsule - Capturing the Data Life
Cycle</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-6819-6949</contrib-id>
<string-name>Devarshi Ghoshal</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-0527-1534</contrib-id>
<string-name>Ludovico Bianchi</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Abdelilah Essiari</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Michael Beach</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0711-9744</contrib-id>
<string-name>Drew Paine</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1761-4132</contrib-id>
<string-name>Lavanya Ramakrishnan</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Lawrence Berkeley National Lab</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Washington</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-06-12">
<day>12</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>62</issue>
<fpage>2484</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>reproducibility</kwd>
<kwd>scientific workflows</kwd>
<kwd>data management</kwd>
<kwd>high performance computing</kwd>
<kwd>big data analytics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The data generated from scientific workflows often become unusable
  due to the lack or incompleteness of information required for
  processing and analyzing the data. Reproducibility of scientific data
  and workflows facilitates efficient processing and analyses. A key to
  enabling reproducibility is to capture the end-to-end workflow life
  cycle, and any contextual metadata and provenance. Existing tools (Guo
  &amp; Seltzer
  (<xref alt="2012" rid="ref-guo2012burrito" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>),
  Chirigati et al.
  (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-chirigati2016reprozip" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>),
  Brinckman et al.
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-brinckman2019computing" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>),
  Šimko et al.
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-vsimko2019reana" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>))
  require researchers to either modify or instrument their analyses,
  which is a barrier to use.</p>
  <p>Science Capsule is free open source software that allows
  researchers to automatically capture their end-to-end workflows
  including the scripts, data, and execution environment. Science
  Capsule monitors the workflow environment to capture the provenance at
  runtime. It provides a timeline view and a web interface to represent
  the workflow and data life cycle, and the associated provenance
  information. Science Capsule also leverages container technologies to
  provide a lightweight, executable package of the scripts and required
  dependencies, ensuring portability and reproducibility.</p>
  <p>The Science Capsule software has the following key features:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Captures provenance through file system and process
      monitoring</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Uses container technologies to create re-executable packages
      containing scripts and metadata</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Runs on a user’s desktop and is also compatible with container
      technologies such as Shifter (Gerhardt et al.
      (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-gerhardt2017shifter" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>))
      running on HPC environments</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Provides a timeline view of an execution through a web
      interface</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Provides an interface to add artifacts including lab notebooks
      and notes</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Supports multiple OS platforms including Windows, Mac and
      Linux</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of Need</title>
  <p>Science Capsule addresses the need for reproducible science. Users
  can download the Science Capsule software and easily set it up to
  capture their workflow and provenance at runtime. Unlike many existing
  tools, Science Capsule does not require users to modify or instrument
  their code. The timeline view provides a visualization for the
  scientist to understand their workflows and data life cycle. Science
  Capsule lets scientists monitor, share, reproduce or use their
  workflows across different software and hardware platforms.</p>
  <p>Science Capsule is currently being used by researchers at the
  Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory. Generally, scientists with any
  data processing or analyses workflow will benefit from the Science
  Capsule software package. For example, a scientist using experimental
  facilities such as light sources or electron microscopes will be able
  to capture their data analyses environment during experiment time and
  reuse it for post-analyses of the data or share the workflows with
  other researchers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="science-capsule-software">
  <title>Science Capsule Software</title>
  <p>Science Capsule is implemented using Python, and uses Node JS and
  Javascript for the web interface. It also uses a MongoDB database for
  storing and managing events captured by the different monitoring
  tools. Science Capsule has been evaluated using synthetic and
  real-world workflows (e.g., Montage) on Windows, MacOS and Linux.</p>
  <p>Science Capsule supports two modes for capturing the information
  about workflows and the associated provenance: a) container mode,
  where Science Capsule captures metadata for all the processes and
  artifacts that are encapsulated within a Docker container, and b)
  bare-metal mode, where Science Capsule captures the execution time
  provenance for user-specified artifacts. The two modes in Science
  Capsule provide different levels of reproducibility. In the container
  mode, all process and data events of a workflow, which run inside the
  container, are captured. This allows for complete reproducibility of
  the workflow. When using the bare-metal mode, Science Capsule monitors
  the file system events of the user-specified directories to understand
  the data life cycle of a workflow. This is typically useful for the
  workflows that cannot be managed in a container.</p>
  <sec id="automatic-monitoring-and-capture">
    <title>Automatic Monitoring and Capture</title>
    <p>Science Capsule monitors the environment where the workflows are
    managed by the researchers by using different system-level file and
    process monitoring tools. The use of these tools depend on the
    underlying platform and the granularity at which researchers intend
    to capture the information. Currently, Science Capsule captures
    events from inotify (Fisher
    (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-fisher2017linux" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)),
    Linux’s strace utility and the Python watchdog library. These tools
    are configured and set up during the installation of Science
    Capsule. These raw events captured by the various monitoring tools
    are processed to extract the high-level data life cycle and task
    execution information. Finally, both raw and processed events are
    stored in a mongodb database for sharing and visualizing the
    execution and provenance of scientific workflows.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="interactive-web-interface">
    <title>Interactive Web Interface</title>
    <p>The processed events in Science Capsule are used to represent
    various activities of a scientific workflow in a chronological
    order, a.k.a. the timeline. Science Capsule provides an interactive
    web interface where researchers can view the timeline in near
    real-time and/or annotate with notes/images that might capture a
    researcher’s thought process and experiment design. The interactive
    web interface provides a way for the researchers to enrich the
    execution and provenance information collected through the
    monitoring framework for enabling better reusability and sharing of
    knowledge. Figure 1 shows an example timeline for a workflow as
    captured by Science Capsule.</p>
    <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figs/example_webui.png" />
    Figure 1: Science Capsule web user interface.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="science-capsule-containers">
    <title>Science Capsule Containers</title>
    <p>A Science Capsule container allows users to monitor their
    workflows running inside the container. The containers themselves
    are managed by docker commands. However, the Science Capsule
    software inside the container transparently monitors and captures
    the metadata necessary to understand and reproduce the workflow. The
    docker commands are also used to save and export the container with
    all the workflow data and metadata. One limitation of this approach
    is that only the current state of the workflow can be saved and
    exported for sharing. We are working on tracking and managing
    different stages and versions of a workflow execution, which will
    allow users to create and share different states, timelines and
    execution traces of a workflow.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="related-work">
  <title>Related Work</title>
  <p>Over the past decade, several frameworks have been developed to
  enable computational reproducibility. Burrito (Guo &amp; Seltzer
  (<xref alt="2012" rid="ref-guo2012burrito" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>))
  captures a researcher’s computational activities and provides user
  interfaces to annotate the captured provenance. Other tools provide
  specific wrappers and dedicated interfaces to create reproducible
  packages for software-based experiments and computational narratives
  (Chirigati et al.
  (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-chirigati2016reprozip" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>),
  Brinckman et al.
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-brinckman2019computing" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>),
  Ton That et al.
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-that2017sciunits" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)).
  Reprozip (Chirigati et al.
  (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-chirigati2016reprozip" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>))
  is a Linux-only tool designed to help scientists package up their
  software-based experiment after it is completed. This tool traces
  systems calls using ptrace to generate provenance information, and
  identify software packages that can then be reconstituted in a virtual
  environment or Docker image. Sciunit is another Linux command-line
  tool (Ton That et al.
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-that2017sciunits" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>))
  that lets users reproduce their computational experiments, and
  captures any command a user runs through the UNIX shell. REANA (Šimko
  et al.
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-vsimko2019reana" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>))
  provides a platform for defining and managing reusable workflows
  through cloud computing. Unlike Science Capsule, these tools often
  require modifications to researchers’ existing work practices, can
  only run on specific platforms (Linux), and do not allow users to
  capture ad-hoc resources (e.g., lab notebooks etc).</p>
  <p>Metadata and provenance are critical in building knowledge for
  enabling reproducibility of scientific workflows. Past research has
  shown the use of data provenance for sharing and reproducing
  scientific workflows (Goble et al.
  (<xref alt="2010" rid="ref-goble2010myexperiment" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>),
  Fomel et al.
  (<xref alt="2013" rid="ref-fomel2013madagascar" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>)).
  However, existing workflow management systems (Oinn et al.
  (<xref alt="2004" rid="ref-oinn2004taverna" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>),
  Deelman et al.
  (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-deelman2015pegasus" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>),
  Altintas et al.
  (<xref alt="2006" rid="ref-altintas2006provenance" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>),
  Barga &amp; Digiampietri
  (<xref alt="2006" rid="ref-barga2006automatic" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>))
  are explicitly instrumented for capturing data provenance from
  scientific workflows. Science Capsule is agnostic to workflow tools
  and uses system-level monitoring to extract information from
  experimental processes and artifacts. It augments and complements
  existing real world practices and tools without requiring a wholesale
  adaptation of scientist’s work to fit the design of Science Capsule,
  while providing usable and understandable interfaces for engaging with
  detailed provenance information.</p>
  <p>Additionally, scientists and researchers may not be using existing
  workflow tools for managing their scientific pipelines, which makes
  the case for other alternatives for collecting relevant metadata to
  enable reproducibility. Traditionally, filesystem metadata have been
  used for performance monitoring and anomaly detection (Miller et al.
  (<xref alt="2010" rid="ref-miller2010monitoring" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>),
  Muniswamy-Reddy et al.
  (<xref alt="2006" rid="ref-muniswamy2006provenance" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>),
  Huang &amp; Wong
  (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-huang2011anomaly" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)).
  Metadata and data context services like Ground (Hellerstein et al.
  (<xref alt="n.d." rid="ref-hellersteinground" ref-type="bibr">n.d.</xref>))
  and Bluesky data broker (Arkilic et al.
  (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-arkilic2015databroker" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>))
  provide integrated interfaces to access data and metadata from various
  sources. We envision Science Capsule to use metadata collected from
  these systems to enrich the provenance in addition to what is
  automatically captured through system-level monitoring tools in
  Science Capsule .</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This work is supported by the U.S. Department of Energy, Office of
  Science and Office of Advanced Scientific Computing Research (ASCR)
  under Contract No. DE-AC02-05CH11231.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-fisher2017linux">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Linux filesystem events with inotify</article-title>
        <source>Linux Journal</source>
        <publisher-name>Belltown Media</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>2017</volume>
        <issue>280</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-chirigati2016reprozip">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Chirigati</surname><given-names>Fernando</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rampin</surname><given-names>Rémi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shasha</surname><given-names>Dennis</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Freire</surname><given-names>Juliana</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ReproZip: Computational reproducibility with ease</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of the 2016 international conference on management of data</source>
        <publisher-name>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <isbn>9781450335317</isbn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1145/2882903.2899401</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2882903.2899401</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-guo2012burrito">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Philip J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Seltzer</surname><given-names>Margo I</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Burrito: Wrapping your lab notebook in computational infrastructure</article-title>
        <publisher-name>USENIX Association</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-brinckman2019computing">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Brinckman</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chard</surname><given-names>Kyle</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gaffney</surname><given-names>Niall</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hategan</surname><given-names>Mihael</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Matthew B</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kowalik</surname><given-names>Kacper</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kulasekaran</surname><given-names>Sivakumar</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ludäscher</surname><given-names>Bertram</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mecum</surname><given-names>Bryce D</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nabrzyski</surname><given-names>Jarek</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Computing environments for reproducibility: Capturing the whole tale</article-title>
        <source>Future Generation Computer Systems</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>94</volume>
        <uri>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167739X17310695</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.future.2017.12.029</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-vsimko2019reana">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Šimko</surname><given-names>Tibor</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>Lukas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hirvonsalo</surname><given-names>Harri</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kousidis</surname><given-names>Dinos</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rodrı́guez</surname><given-names>Diego</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>REANA: A system for reusable research data analyses</article-title>
        <source>EPJ web of conferences</source>
        <publisher-name>EDP Sciences</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>214</volume>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1051/epjconf/201921406034</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/epjconf/201921406034</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-oinn2004taverna">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Oinn</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Addis</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Marvin</surname><given-names>Darren</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Senger</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>Matthew R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wipat</surname><given-names>Anil</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Taverna: A tool for the composition and enactment of bioinformatics workflows</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>17</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bth361</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bth361</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-deelman2015pegasus">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Deelman</surname><given-names>Ewa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vahi</surname><given-names>Karan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Juve</surname><given-names>Gideon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rynge</surname><given-names>Mats</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Callaghan</surname><given-names>Scott</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Maechling</surname><given-names>Philip J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mayani</surname><given-names>Rajiv</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Weiwei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>Rafael Ferreira</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Livny</surname><given-names>Miron</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pegasus, a workflow management system for science automation</article-title>
        <source>Future Generation Computer Systems</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>46</volume>
        <uri>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167739X14002015</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.future.2014.10.008</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-altintas2006provenance">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Altintas</surname><given-names>Ilkay</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Barney</surname><given-names>Oscar</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jaeger-Frank</surname><given-names>Efrat</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Provenance collection support in the kepler scientific workflow system</article-title>
        <source>International provenance and annotation workshop</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/11890850_14</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-barga2006automatic">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Barga</surname><given-names>Roger S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Digiampietri</surname><given-names>Luciano A</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Automatic generation of workflow provenance</article-title>
        <source>International provenance and annotation workshop</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/11890850_1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-gerhardt2017shifter">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gerhardt</surname><given-names>Lisa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bhimji</surname><given-names>Wahid</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fasel</surname><given-names>Markus</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>Jeff</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>Mustafa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>Doug</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tsulaia</surname><given-names>Vakho</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Canon</surname><given-names>Shane</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Shifter: Containers for hpc</article-title>
        <source>J. Phys. Conf. ser.</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>898</volume>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1088/1742-6596/898/8/082021</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1742-6596/898/8/082021</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-goble2010myexperiment">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Goble</surname><given-names>Carole A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bhagat</surname><given-names>Jiten</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Aleksejevs</surname><given-names>Sergejs</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cruickshank</surname><given-names>Don</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Michaelides</surname><given-names>Danius</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Borkum</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bechhofer</surname><given-names>Sean</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>myExperiment: A repository and social network for the sharing of bioinformatics workflows</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford Univ Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>38</volume>
        <issue>suppl 2</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkq429</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq429</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-miller2010monitoring">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Ross</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Jason</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dillow</surname><given-names>David A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gunasekaran</surname><given-names>Raghul</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shipman</surname><given-names>Galen M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>Don</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Monitoring tools for large scale systems</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of cray user group conference (CUG 2010)</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-muniswamy2006provenance">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Muniswamy-Reddy</surname><given-names>Kiran-Kumar</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>David A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>Uri</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Seltzer</surname><given-names>Margo I</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Provenance-aware storage systems.</article-title>
        <source>Usenix annual technical conference, general track</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-huang2011anomaly">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Liang</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Kenny</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Anomaly detection by monitoring filesystem activities</article-title>
        <source>2011 IEEE 19th international conference on program comprehension</source>
        <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ICPC.2011.23</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-hellersteinground">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hellerstein</surname><given-names>Joseph M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sreekanti</surname><given-names>Vikram</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>Joseph E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>Akon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nag</surname><given-names>Sreyashi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>Krishna</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>Sudhanshu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>Arka</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>Shirshanka</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ground: A data context service</article-title>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-arkilic2015databroker">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Arkilic</surname><given-names>Arman</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chabot</surname><given-names>Daron</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dalesio</surname><given-names>Leo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>Wayne</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Databroker: An interface for NSLS-II data management system</article-title>
        <source>15th int. Conf. On accelerator and large experimental physics control systems (ICALEPCS’15), melbourne, australia, 17-23 october 2015</source>
        <publisher-name>JACOW, Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-that2017sciunits">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Ton That</surname><given-names>Dai Hai</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fils</surname><given-names>Gabriel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Zhihao</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>Tanu</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Sciunits: Reusable research objects</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume></volume>
        <issue></issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/eScience.2017.51</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-fomel2013madagascar">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Fomel</surname><given-names>Sergey</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sava</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vlad</surname><given-names>Ioan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bashkardin</surname><given-names>Vladimir</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Madagascar: Open-source software project for multidimensional data analysis and reproducible computational experiments</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Research Software</source>
        <publisher-name>Ubiquity Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/jors.ag</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
