<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1494</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01494</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>mTower: Trusted Execution Environment for MCU-based
devices</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4651-1696</contrib-id>
<string-name>Taras A. Drozdovskyi</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3167-983X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Oleksandr S. Moliavko</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Samsung R&amp;D Institute Ukraine, Kiev,
Ukraine</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-05-06">
<day>6</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>40</issue>
<fpage>1494</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>ARM</kwd>
<kwd>TrustZone</kwd>
<kwd>Trusted Execution Environment</kwd>
<kwd>embedded systems</kwd>
<kwd>microcontrollers</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="background">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Embedded computing systems have already become ubiquitous in daily
  life. In many cases these systems deal with confidential data and
  control access to valuable resources. Significant efforts are put into
  securing these systems against malicious access. However, the software
  and data are often protected by outdated mechanisms that contain
  well-known vulnerabilities, thus do not pose any real obstacles for
  technically savvy adversary. Consequences of deliberate attack against
  embedded systems can be severe, e.g.:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>poor data protection in network-connected medical device can
      pose life risk
      (<xref alt="Basu, 2013" rid="ref-Forbes" ref-type="bibr">Basu,
      2013</xref>)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>hardcoded cryptographic keys and application vulnerable to
      reverse engineering in automotive platform
      (<xref alt="Valasek &amp; Miller, 2014" rid="ref-IOactive" ref-type="bibr">Valasek
      &amp; Miller, 2014</xref>)</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Yet developing safe and efficient data protection mechanism from
  scratch is time-consuming and costly endeavor. Without an independent
  assessment there is always a risk of some undiscovered vulnerability
  persist. However, current generations of ARM-based microcontrollers
  offer a solid hardware foundation for building security mechanisms:
  ARM TrustZone technology. Initially developed for ARM family of CPUs,
  TrustZone technology was later adapted for microcontroller (MCU)
  implementations of ARM architecture. Software libraries that implement
  security-related operations based on ARM TrustZone are readily
  available for Linux family of OSes including the one used in
  Android-based smartphones. However, these libraries are too cumbersome
  and resource-consuming to be directly adopted to embedded systems and
  MCU-based devices where clock speeds are orders of magnitude lower and
  RAM available for use is severely limited. There are several attempts
  to develop a TrustZone-based security solution for MCU-based systems:
  Kinibi-M
  (<xref alt="Trustonic, 2017" rid="ref-Kinibi-M" ref-type="bibr">Trustonic,
  2017</xref>), ProvenCore-M
  (<xref alt="Prove &amp; Run, 2018" rid="ref-ProvenCore-M" ref-type="bibr">Prove
  &amp; Run, 2018</xref>), CoreLockr-TZ
  (<xref alt="Sequitur Labs Inc., 2018" rid="ref-CoreLockr-TZ" ref-type="bibr">Sequitur
  Labs Inc., 2018</xref>). However, these solutions are either
  proprietary and not available as a source code for independent review,
  or have technical limitations that make them not fully standard
  compliant. mTower is an experimental industrial standard-compliant
  implementation of GlobalPlatform Trusted Execution Environment (GP
  TEE) APIs based on ARM TrustZone. From the very beginning mTower was
  designed to have minimal RAM footprint and to avoid the use of
  time-consuming operations. As of May 2019 mTower contains a partial
  implementation of GP TEE API, with remaining part of API to be
  implemented soon. Source code and compatibility table are available at
  https://github.com/Samsung/mTower.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="implementation-overview">
  <title>Implementation overview</title>
  <p>Secure applications that utilize TrustZone protection live in two
  interacting environments: Normal World (NW) and Secure World (SW).
  Normal World part is typically a standard Linux executable that uses
  TEE library containing API functions to interact with Secure World
  part. The corresponding Secure World part is essentially a set of
  event handlers that are executed in hardware-protected area of RAM
  under control of a specially designed operating system. Secure World
  part processes calls received from Normal World and deals with
  sensitive data that must be protected from unauthorized access such as
  cryptographic keys, passwords, user identification data, etc. Common
  operations performed by Secure World part of the application include
  data encryption/decryption, user authentication, key generation,
  digital signing and signature verification.</p>
  <p>Secure application architecture should comply with TEE System
  Architecture v1.0 document
  (<xref alt="GlobalPlatform, 2018c" rid="ref-TEESystemArch" ref-type="bibr">GlobalPlatform,
  2018c</xref>). mTower follows the layout described in this
  specification. Also it provides the implementation of APIs described
  in GP TEE specification documents. The two most important GP
  specifications are:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>TEE Client API Specification v1.0
      (<xref alt="GlobalPlatform, 2010" rid="ref-ClientAPISpec" ref-type="bibr">GlobalPlatform,
      2010</xref>) describes the communication between NW applications
      and Trusted Applications residing in the SW</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>TEE Internal Core API Specification v1.0
      (<xref alt="GlobalPlatform, 2018b" rid="ref-CoreAPISpec" ref-type="bibr">GlobalPlatform,
      2018b</xref>) describes the internal operations of Trusted
      Applications</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Most up-to-date versions of these specifications are available at
  Global Platform web site
  (<xref alt="GlobalPlatform, 2018a" rid="ref-GPSpecLibrary" ref-type="bibr">GlobalPlatform,
  2018a</xref>) after registration.</p>
  <p>mTower’s modular architecture allows for build-time configuration
  of the required features to optimize memory footprint and performance.
  Originally resource management for mTower is based on FreeRTOS
  real-time operating system. It can be replaced by other operating
  systems if needed. As of May 2019, mTower runs on Nuvoton M2351 board
  based on ARM Cortex-M23 MCU. There are plans to include support for
  other platforms based on ARM Cortex-M23/33/33p family MCUs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="potential-future-development">
  <title>Potential future development</title>
  <p>After completing the implementation of relevant APIs, we plan to
  provide support for dynamic loading, remote updating of secure
  applications including the essential security mechanisms of OS. Also
  we plan the extension of Resource Manager that provides secure access
  to H/W. Another planned component is the set of instrumentation hooks
  in mTower code that will simplify specification compliance evaluation,
  performance measurements, assessment and debugging of secure
  applications.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="expected-audience-for-mtower-project">
  <title>Expected audience for mTower project</title>
  <p>mTower project is expected to be used for proof-of-concepts and
  evaluation models for ARM TrustZone-based secure applications in
  MCU-based systems. It can be of interest for:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Internet-of-Things and Smart Home appliance developers</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>embedded system developers in general</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>computer security specialists</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="research-applications">
  <title>Research applications</title>
  <p>mTower is being developed as a part of search for efficient
  hardware/software security solution for low-cost IoT devices. It is
  expected to demonstrate the feasibility of porting GP TEE-compliant
  Trusted Applications from full-feature CPU-based to MCU-based systems.
  Another mTower targeted application is using it as a platform for
  developing and evaluating secure applications for EDGE devices. Also
  only a limited information is available about resource consumption
  penalty incurred by adding security mechanisms into IoT applications.
  The prevailing opinion seems to be that security through obscurity is
  sufficient for embedded systems, and any attempt to introduce
  sophisticated security features incurs an unacceptable overhead. Thus
  another objective of mTower development is to provide a reference
  platform that allows the researchers to actually measure this overhead
  by comparing system performance with mTower security mechanisms and
  without them. We hope that mTower will contribute to TrustZone-based
  security adoption for low-cost IoT.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Forbes">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hacking insulin pumps and other medical devices from Black Hat</article-title>
        <source>Forbes</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013-08">2013</year><month>08</month>
        <uri>https://www.forbes.com/sites/ericbasu/2013/08/03/hacking-insulin-pumps-and-other-medical-devices-reality-not-fiction</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-IOactive">
      <element-citation publication-type="report">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Valasek</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Charlie</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Adventures in automotive networks and control units</article-title>
        <publisher-name>IOActive, Inc.</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <uri>http://www.ioactive.com/pdfs/IOActive_Adventures_in_Automotive_Networks_and_Control_Units.pdf</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Kinibi-M">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Trustonic</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Not just droning on! The rise of Kinibi-M</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-10">2017</year><month>10</month>
        <uri>https://www.trustonic.com/news/blog/not-just-droning-rise-kinibi-m/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ProvenCore-M">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Prove &amp; Run</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ProvenCore-M</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>http://www.provenrun.com/products/provencore-m/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-CoreLockr-TZ">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Sequitur Labs Inc.</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>CoreLockr-TZ</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>https://www.sequiturlabs.com/corelockrtz/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-TEESystemArch">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>GlobalPlatform</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TEE System Architecture v1.2</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>https://globalplatform.org/specs-library/tee-system-architecture-v1-2/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ClientAPISpec">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>GlobalPlatform</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TEE Client API Specification v1.0</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <uri>https://globalplatform.org/specs-library/tee-client-api-specification/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-CoreAPISpec">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>GlobalPlatform</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TEE Internal Core API Specification v1.2.1</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>https://globalplatform.org/specs-library/tee-internal-core-api-specification-v1-2/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-GPSpecLibrary">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>GlobalPlatform</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GlobalPlatform Specification Library</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>https://globalplatform.org/specs-library/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
