<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3247</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03247</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Eir: A Python Package for Epidemic
Simulation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-5513-432X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Mathew Jacob</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>RxCovea, New York University, New York, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-04-08">
<day>8</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>62</issue>
<fpage>3247</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>epidemiology</kwd>
<kwd>super spreaders</kwd>
<kwd>spatial models</kwd>
<kwd>stochastic</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p><monospace>Eir</monospace> is a Python package that simulates
  epidemics with various assumptions and compartmental models. By mainly
  using spatial models, <monospace>Eir</monospace> allows for better
  modeling of the spread of an epidemic in smaller communities and
  localities. There are four different spatial models used: the Strong
  Infectious Model
  (<xref alt="Fujie &amp; Odagaki, 2007" rid="ref-FujieU0026Odagaki" ref-type="bibr">Fujie
  &amp; Odagaki, 2007</xref>), Hub Model
  (<xref alt="Fujie &amp; Odagaki, 2007" rid="ref-FujieU0026Odagaki" ref-type="bibr">Fujie
  &amp; Odagaki, 2007</xref>), the Random Movement Model, and the
  Periodic Mobility Model. While the Strong Infectious Model and Hub
  Model are static models, where no movement pattern is simulated, the
  Random Movement and Periodic Mobility Model simulates the movement
  pattern of people using different assumptions. The Random Movement
  Model assumes that an individual is equally likely to move in any
  direction for a random distance, generated from a user-defined normal
  distribution. The Periodic Mobility Model assumes that individuals
  move in a circle to capture the routine nature of people’s movements.
  Therefore, after randomly generating locations, the model calculates a
  center of a circle and individuals move along that circle. With all of
  these spatial models, researchers can use the
  <monospace>Simul_Details</monospace> objects to interact with the
  simulation data and get a deeper understanding of the simulation’s
  dynamics, such as transmission chains, state histories, etc. The data
  from these simulations can be plotted using Matplotlib or be returned
  in the form of a pandas DataFrame. It is important to note that these
  models are stochastic and are discrete-time Markov chains.</p>
  <p><monospace>Eir</monospace> leverages many different compartmental
  models in addtition to different spatial models in order to give
  researchers flexibility and robustness when simulating the spread of
  an epidemic. The models include but are not limited to:
  Susceptible-Infected-Recovered (SIR),
  Susceptible-Infected-Recovered-Dead (SIRD),
  Susceptible-Exposed-Infected-Recovered (SEIR),
  Susceptible-Exposed-Infected-Recovered-Vaccinated (SEIRV),
  Susceptible-Infected-Recovered-Susceptible-Vaccinated (SIRSV), and ICU
  models. The ICU models, in particular, are based on the work of
  Mühlpfordt et al
  (<xref alt="Mühlpfordt, 2020" rid="ref-ICU" ref-type="bibr">Mühlpfordt,
  2020</xref>). Additionally, for any model that includes vaccinations,
  there is a timeDelay variable that allows the user to delay vaccine
  distribution by a particular amount of days.</p>
  <p>While not the primary focus of the Python package,
  <monospace>Eir</monospace> also allows for researchers to use
  determinstic models to simulate basic compartmental models, including
  SIR, SEIR, SIRV, and more.</p>
  <p><monospace>Eir</monospace> is currently being used for a
  publication involving simulating hospitalizations and studying
  vaccinations strategies. It is intended to be used by epidemiologists
  and researchers who are interested in understanding the dynamics of
  epidemics when operating under different modelling assumptions, such
  as periodic movement or random movement, which can be evaluated by
  using different models in Eir.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of Need</title>
  <p>When modelling the spread of diseases, epidemiologists often use
  compartmental models, which classify people into states, the most
  common one being the SIR Model
  (<xref alt="Kermack &amp; McKendrick, 1927" rid="ref-SIR" ref-type="bibr">Kermack
  &amp; McKendrick, 1927</xref>). There are certain rules that govern
  these compartmental models, such as that an individual can only exist
  in one compartment at any given time. With these models,
  epidemiologists are able to understand the dynamics of how an epidemic
  spreads. However, a lot of these models often use ODEs to approximate
  parameters for large populations and make assumptions to simplify
  calculations, which don’t capture the complexities of smaller
  communities, where national averages may not be accurate. Then,
  researchers often use discrete-time Markov chains
  (<xref alt="Allen, 2017" rid="ref-Allen" ref-type="bibr">Allen,
  2017</xref>), which generate stochastic events at certain time steps,
  such as every day or every hour. Additionally, in these smaller
  localities, spatial models are often deployed to get more accurate
  transmission probabilities. The sheer number of spatial models in Eir,
  as well as Eir’s inclusion of models with movement, will make the
  process of modelling local disease transmission far easier. These
  spatial models are known as the Hub model
  (<xref alt="Fujie &amp; Odagaki, 2007" rid="ref-FujieU0026Odagaki" ref-type="bibr">Fujie
  &amp; Odagaki, 2007</xref>), Strong Infectious Model
  (<xref alt="Fujie &amp; Odagaki, 2007" rid="ref-FujieU0026Odagaki" ref-type="bibr">Fujie
  &amp; Odagaki, 2007</xref>), Random Movement Model, and Periodic
  Mobility Model. The Random Movement Model assumes that an individual
  is equally likely to move in every direction. The Periodic Mobility
  Model assumes that each person moves along a circle with a normally
  distributed radius. These models offer different structure to the
  spatial models, which can be used by epidemiologists.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="dependencies">
  <title>Dependencies</title>
  <p>NumPy, Matplotlib, multipledispatch, pandas</p>
</sec>
<sec id="related-packages">
  <title>Related Packages</title>
  <p>There are different software package that enable users to simulate
  epidemics in different ways. A couple of such packages are:</p>
  <sec id="epidemics-on-networks">
    <title>Epidemics on Networks</title>
    <p>Epidemics on Networks
    (<xref alt="Miller &amp; Ting, 2019" rid="ref-Miller2019" ref-type="bibr">Miller
    &amp; Ting, 2019</xref>), abbreviated EoN, is a Python package that
    allows users to simulate SIS and SIR epidemics on networks. It
    handles many different simulation types, as well. More can be found
    by reading the documentation at
    https://epidemicsonnetworks.readthedocs.io/en/latest/. Eir allows
    for a wider variety of models than EoN, which only includes SIS and
    SIR. Additionally, another difference is that Eir allows for the
    movement of individuals within the simulation, while the structure
    in EoN does not.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="epimodel">
    <title>EpiModel</title>
    <p>EpiModel
    (<xref alt="Jenness et al., 2018" rid="ref-EpiModel" ref-type="bibr">Jenness
    et al., 2018</xref>) is an R package that allows the user to
    simulate models such as SIS and SIR. The details of this model can
    be found at https://www.epimodel.org/. EpiModel offers network based
    transmission, which is a feature that is not included in Eir.
    However, similar to EoN, there is no clear way to incorporate the
    movement of individuals within the simulation. Additionally, Eir
    offers a more detailed look at the simulation through the
    Simul_Details object, which can include information about individual
    state history, transmission chains, and more.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>The author would like to acknowledge the contributions of Xueyao
  Guo to the models. Additionally, the author would like to acknowledge
  and thank Dr. Ernest Battifarano, Dr. Jantine Broek, and Professor
  Shirshendu Chatterjee for their mentorship and guidance through the
  author’s research. Finally, the author would like to thank Professor
  Bud Mishra and the RxCovea group for guiding the author through his
  research.</p>
  <p>This project received no funding.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-SIR">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kermack</surname><given-names>W. O.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McKendrick</surname><given-names>A. G. A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A Contribution to the Mathematical Theory of Epidemics</article-title>
        <source>Proc. Roy. Soc. Edinburgh</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1927-01">1927</year><month>01</month>
        <volume>115</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspa.1927.0118</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-FujieU0026Odagaki">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Fujie</surname><given-names>Ryo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Odagaki</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Effects of superspreaders in spread of epidemic</article-title>
        <source>Physica A-statistical Mechanics and Its Applications - PHYSICA A</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007-02">2007</year><month>02</month>
        <volume>374</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2006.08.050</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Allen">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>Linda</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A primer on stochastic epidemic models: Formulation, numerical simulation, and analysis</article-title>
        <source>Infectious Disease Modelling</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-03">2017</year><month>03</month>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idm.2017.03.001</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ICU">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mühlpfordt</surname><given-names>Tillmann</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SEIR Model with Stochastic Uncertainties – A Polynomial Chaos Approach</article-title>
        <source>GitHub repository</source>
        <publisher-name>GitHub</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <uri>https://github.com/timueh/PandemicModeling</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Miller2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Joel C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>Tony</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>EoN (Epidemics on Networks): a fast, flexible Python package for simulation, analytic approximation, and analysis of epidemics on networks</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <publisher-name>The Open Journal</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>44</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01731</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01731</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-EpiModel">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Jenness</surname><given-names>Samuel M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Goodreau</surname><given-names>Steven M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>Martina</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>EpiModel: An R Package for Mathematical Modeling of Infectious Disease over Networks</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Statistical Software, Articles</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>84</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <issn>1548-7660</issn>
        <uri>https://www.jstatsoft.org/v084/i08</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v084.i08</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
