<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2805</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02805</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Predihood: an open-source tool for predicting
neighbourhoods' information</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3469-4149</contrib-id>
<string-name>Nelly Barret</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-6803-917X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Fabien Duchateau</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2039-3481</contrib-id>
<string-name>Franck Favetta</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>LIRIS UMR5205, Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1, Lyon,
France</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-09-16">
<day>16</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>61</issue>
<fpage>2805</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>MongoDB</kwd>
<kwd>data management</kwd>
<kwd>neighbourhood</kwd>
<kwd>prediction</kwd>
<kwd>machine learning</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>Neighbourhoods are a widespread concept in studies from diverse
  domains such as health, social sciences, or biology. For instance,
  Japanese researchers investigated the relationships between social
  factors and health by taking into account behavioral risks and housing
  and neighbourhood environments
  (<xref alt="Takada et al., 2014" rid="ref-takada2014japanese" ref-type="bibr">Takada
  et al., 2014</xref>). In a British study, authors describe how living
  areas impact physical activities, from which they determine a
  walkability index at the neighbourhood level for improving future
  urban planning
  (<xref alt="Frank et al., 2010" rid="ref-frank2010development" ref-type="bibr">Frank
  et al., 2010</xref>). Another survey describes the luxury effect,
  i.e., the impact of wealthy neighbourhoods on the surrounding
  biodiversity
  (<xref alt="Leong et al., 2018" rid="ref-leong2018biodiversity" ref-type="bibr">Leong
  et al., 2018</xref>). Several works focus on qualifying neighbourhoods
  using social networks. For instance, the Livehoods project defines and
  computes neighbourhoods dynamics
  (<xref alt="Cranshaw et al., 2012" rid="ref-cranshaw2012livehoods" ref-type="bibr">Cranshaw
  et al., 2012</xref>), while the Hoodsquare project detects similar
  areas based on Foursquare check-ins
  (<xref alt="Zhang et al., 2013" rid="ref-zhang2013hoodsquare" ref-type="bibr">Zhang
  et al., 2013</xref>). Crowd-based systems are interesting but may
  sometimes be biased, and they require technical skills to extract
  relevant data. DataFrance is an interface that integrates data from
  several sources, such as indicators provided by the National Institute
  of Statistics (INSEE), geographical information from the National
  Geographic Institute (IGN), and surveys from newspapers for prices
  (L’Express). DataFrance enables the visualization of hundreds of
  indicators but makes it difficult to judge the main characteristics of
  a neighbourhood and is limited to France. Despite all of these
  existing applications, there is no simple tool to visualize and
  predict insights about neighbourhoods.</p>
  <p>The Predihood tool fills this gap by defining neighbourhoods, their
  characteristics, and variables to be predicted. It also includes a
  cartographic interface for searching and displaying information about
  neighbourhoods. Domain experts can provide a few examples of annotated
  neighbourhoods, and Predihood provides a configuration interface for
  using popular machine-learning algorithms in order to predict
  variables for the remaining neighbourhoods. One of the most recent
  applications of Predihood was measuring the impact and influence of a
  neighbourhood’s environment on the decision-making process when people
  move to another city
  (<xref alt="Barret et al., 2020" rid="ref-data2020" ref-type="bibr">Barret
  et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
  <p>Predihood mainly targets non-programmers users (e.g., researchers
  in social sciences or history) due to its simplicity for running and
  configuring predictive algorithms. It can be extended to other
  application domains: measuring the pollution degree in neighbourhoods,
  determining whether a certain neighbourhood is suitable as a stopover
  for migratory birds, predicting neighbourhood evolution based on
  historical data, etc. This paper describes the main features of
  Predihood and how to extend them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="methodology">
  <title>Methodology</title>
  <p>Predihood provides the following functionalities:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>adding new neighbourhoods and indicators to describe them;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>predicting variables of a neighbourhood by configuring and
      using predefined algorithms;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>adding new predictive algorithms.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>To facilitate understanding, we describe and illustrate these
  functionalities based on a simple example that aims to evaluate which
  neighbourhood is preferable for migratory birds to make a temporary
  stop. We only include three indicators per neighbourhood: the percent
  of greens, the percent of buildings and the degree of human pressure.
  A single variable <monospace>migration zone</monospace> qualifies a
  neighbourhood from <italic>favorable</italic> to
  <italic>unfavorable</italic>.</p>
  <sec id="adding-new-datasets">
    <title>Adding new datasets</title>
    <p>As Predihood is a general-purpose application, it enables
    contributors to add their own datasets. The key concept of a dataset
    is the neighbourhood, which is represented as a
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://geojson.org/">GeoJSON
    object</ext-link> including:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>a geometry (multi-polygons), which describes the shape of the
        neighbourhood. This crucial data is not only useful for
        cartographic visualization but also enable automatic
        calculations such as area;</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>properties, which are divided into two categories.
        Descriptive information (e.g., name, city postcode) mainly aims
        to improve display while a set of quantitative indicators is
        used to predict the values of the variable.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p>Besides, some neighbourhoods have to be manually annotated, a
    task typically performed by domain experts. To add a new dataset, it
    is necessary to store them as GeoJSON and make them accessible by
    Predihood, for instance, in a document-oriented database.</p>
    <p>To build a dataset for the <italic>bird migration</italic>
    example, it is necessary to collect and integrate data sources about
    neighbourhoods located in the studied geographic area. Values for
    the three indicators should be provided, and a value to the
    <monospace>migration zone</monospace> variable should be assigned to
    a few neighbourhoods.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="predicting">
    <title>Predicting</title>
    <p>Machine learning algorithms require data preparation by grouping
    relevant properties and variables. We illustrate this step on the
    <italic>bird migration</italic> dataset, as shown in Figure
    <xref alt="1" rid="figU003Adataset">1</xref>. Predihood produces a
    table composed of the identifier and the name of the neighbourhood
    (grey columns), its indicators (yellow columns) that could be
    normalized by factors such as density of population (green columns),
    and optionally the assessment of researchers for the
    <monospace>migration zone</monospace> variable (blue column). The
    objective of Predihood is to automatically fill question marks for
    neighbourhoods that are not yet assessed.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>A subset of the <italic>bird-migration</italic>
      dataset.<styled-content id="figU003Adataset"></styled-content></p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="doc/predihood-indicators-bird.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
    <p>To perform prediction, a selection process first selects subsets
    of relevant indicators, since too many indicators may degrade
    performance. The tool automatically reduces the number of
    indicators, e.g., by removing indicators with a unique value or
    those highly correlated using Spearman coefficient. Then, Predihood
    generates 7 lists of indicators, containing from 10 to 100
    indicators. The current version of Predihood includes 8 predictive
    algorithms from
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scikit-learn.org/">scikit-learn</ext-link>
    (e.g., Random Forest, KNeighbours)
    (<xref alt="Pedregosa et al., 2011" rid="ref-scikit-learn" ref-type="bibr">Pedregosa
    et al., 2011</xref>), depending on the algorithm, small or large
    lists of indicators may be more effective.</p>
    <p>Predihood provides a cartographic web interface based on
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://leafletjs.com/">Leaflet</ext-link>
    and
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">Open
    Street Map</ext-link>, as shown in Figure
    <xref alt="2" rid="figU003Acartographic-interface">2</xref>. For
    this example we use the search query “<italic>lyon</italic>” (left
    panel) and all neighbourhoods containing this query in their name or
    their city names are shown in blue on the map. We select the
    neighbourhood
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parc_de_la_Tête_d%27or"><italic>Le
    parc</italic></ext-link> and run the Random Forest classifier:
    migration is considered <italic>very favorable</italic> in this area
    (for the seven lists of indicators). Indeed, this park seems
    relevant for bird migration as it has nice green areas for birds and
    it is a healthy environment for them.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>Screenshot of the cartographic interface of
      Predihood.<styled-content id="figU003Acartographic-interface"></styled-content></p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="doc/predihood-predictions-bird.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
  </sec>
  <sec id="adding-new-algorithms">
    <title>Adding new algorithms</title>
    <p>Because prediction is a complex task, testing specific algorithms
    tuned with different parameters and comparing their results may help
    increase the overall quality. In order to facilitate this task,
    Predihood proposes a generic and easy-to-use programming structure
    for machine learning algorithms, based on Scikit-learn algorithms.
    Thus, experts can implement hand-made algorithms and run experiments
    in Predihood. Adding a new algorithm only requires 4 steps:</p>
    <list list-type="order">
      <list-item>
        <p>Create a new class that represents your algorithm,
        e.g. <monospace>MyOwnClassifier</monospace>, which inherits from
        <monospace>Classifier</monospace>;</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Implement the core of your algorithm by coding the
        <monospace>fit()</monospace> and
        <monospace>predict()</monospace> functions. The
        <monospace>fit</monospace> function aims at fitting your
        classifier on assessed neighbourhoods while the
        <monospace>predict</monospace> function aims at predicting
        variable(s) for a given neighbourhood;</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Add the <monospace>get_params()</monospace> function, which
        returns a dictionary of parameters along with their value, in
        order to be compatible with the Scikit-learn framework;</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Comment your classifier with the
        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://numpydoc.readthedocs.io/en/latest/format.html#docstring-standard">Numpy
        style</ext-link>
        (<xref alt="Harris et al., 2020" rid="ref-harris2020array" ref-type="bibr">Harris
        et al., 2020</xref>) so that Predihood automatically extracts
        its parameters and enables their tuning in the dedicated
        interface.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p>Below is a simple example to illustrate the aforementioned steps.
    Note that new algorithms are directly loaded into Predihood.</p>
    <code language="python"># file ./algorithms/MyOwnClassifier.py
from predihood.classes.Classifier import Classifier


class MyOwnClassifier(Classifier):
  &quot;&quot;&quot;Description of the classifier.
  Parameters
  ------------
  a : float, default=0.01
    Description of a.
  b : int, default=10
    Description of b.
  &quot;&quot;&quot;

  def __init__(self, a=0.01, b=10):
    self.a = a
    self.b = b

  def fit(self, X, y):
    # do stuff here

  def predict(self, df):
    # do stuff here

  def get_params(self, deep=True):
    # suppose this estimator has parameters &quot;a&quot; and &quot;b&quot;
    return {&quot;a&quot;: self.a, &quot;b&quot;: self.b}</code>
    <p>To facilitate experiments, Predihood provides an interface for
    easily tuning and testing algorithms on a dataset, as shown in
    Figure <xref alt="3" rid="figU003Atuning-interface">3</xref>. The
    left panel stands for the selection of an algorithm and the tuning
    of its parameters and hyper parameters, such as training and test
    sizes. Note that two options enable to remove outliers and
    under-represented neighbourhoods (for a given variable) without
    directly modifying the dataset. On the right, the table illustrates
    the accuracies obtained for each list of indicators (generated
    during the selection process) and each variable. Results can be
    exported in XLS with the blue download icon. Here, we notice that
    the new algorithm <italic>MyOwnClassifier</italic> has been chosen,
    and its parameters (<italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic>) can
    be configured. We have performed 2 runs, the former with the Random
    Forest classifier and the latter with MyOwnClassifier. Best
    predictive results are achieved with all indicators (green
    cells).</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>Screenshot of algorithmic interface of
      Predihood.<styled-content id="figU003Atuning-interface"></styled-content></p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="doc/predihood-accuracies-bird.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="current-applications-of-predihood">
  <title>Current applications of Predihood</title>
  <p>Our Predihood tool was presented during the DATA conference
  (<xref alt="Barret et al., 2020" rid="ref-data2020" ref-type="bibr">Barret
  et al., 2020</xref>) posing the evaluation of whether people choose a
  similar neighbourhood environment when moving elsewhere as the main
  research challenge. The tool is bundled with data from France using
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gitlab.liris.cnrs.fr/fduchate/mongiris">mongiris</ext-link>
  project (in which unit divisions named
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.insee.fr/en/metadonnees/definition/c1523/">IRIS</ext-link>
  stand for neighbourhoods), this dataset contains about 50,000
  neighbourhoods with 640 indicators (about population, shops,
  buildings, etc.). Six environment variables have been defined
  (<italic>building type</italic>, <italic>building usage</italic>,
  <italic>landscape</italic>, <italic>social class</italic>,
  <italic>morphological position</italic> and <italic>geographical
  position</italic>), and 270 neighbourhoods were annotated by social
  science researchers (one to two hours per neighbourhood to investigate
  building and streets pictures, parked cars, facilities and green areas
  from services such as Google Street View). Prediction results achieved
  by Predihood using 6 algorithms from Scikit-learn range from 30% to
  65% accuracy depending on the environment variable, and designing new
  algorithms could help improving these results.</p>
  <p>The open-source project is available here:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gitlab.com/fduchate/predihood">https://gitlab.com/fduchate/predihood</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This work has been partially funded by LABEX IMU (ANR-10-LABX-0088)
  from Université de Lyon, in the context of the program
  “Investissements d’Avenir” (ANR-11-IDEX-0007) from the French Research
  Agency (ANR). In addition to Scikit-learn and Numpy, Predihood relies
  on other dependencies, namely Pandas
  (<xref alt="team, 2020" rid="ref-jeff_reback_2020_4161697" ref-type="bibr">team,
  2020</xref>), seaborn
  (<xref alt="Waskom, 2021" rid="ref-Waskom2021" ref-type="bibr">Waskom,
  2021</xref>) and matplotlib
  (<xref alt="Hunter, 2007" rid="ref-HunterU003A2007" ref-type="bibr">Hunter,
  2007</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-cranshaw2012livehoods">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Cranshaw</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Raz</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Jason I</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sadeh</surname><given-names>Norman</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The livehoods project: Utilizing social media to understand the dynamics of a city</article-title>
        <source>International AAAI conference on weblogs and social media</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <uri>https://ssrn.com/abstract=2168428</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-scikit-learn">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Pedregosa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Varoquaux</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gramfort</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thirion</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grisel</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Blondel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Prettenhofer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dubourg</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vanderplas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Passos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cournapeau</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brucher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Perrot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Duchesnay</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Scikit-learn: Machine learning in Python</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Machine Learning Research</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-harris2020array">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>Charles R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Millman</surname><given-names>K. Jarrod</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Walt</surname><given-names>Stéfan J. van der</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gommers</surname><given-names>Ralf</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Virtanen</surname><given-names>Pauli</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cournapeau</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wieser</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>Sebastian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Nathaniel J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Picus</surname><given-names>Matti</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hoyer</surname><given-names>Stephan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kerkwijk</surname><given-names>Marten H. van</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Haldane</surname><given-names>Allan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Río</surname><given-names>Jaime Fernández del</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>Pearu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gérard-Marchant</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>Tyler</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weckesser</surname><given-names>Warren</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>Hameer</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gohlke</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oliphant</surname><given-names>Travis E.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Array programming with NumPy</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Science; Business Media LLC</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-09">2020</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>585</volume>
        <issue>7825</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-jeff_reback_2020_4161697">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>team</surname><given-names>The pandas development</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Pandas-dev/pandas: Pandas 1.1.4</source>
        <publisher-name>Zenodo</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-10">2020</year><month>10</month>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4161697</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.4161697</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-HunterU003A2007">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Matplotlib: A 2D graphics environment</article-title>
        <source>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</source>
        <publisher-name>IEEE COMPUTER SOC</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MCSE.2007.55</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Waskom2021">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Waskom</surname><given-names>Michael L.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Seaborn: Statistical data visualization</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <publisher-name>The Open Journal</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>60</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.03021</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03021</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-zhang2013hoodsquare">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Amy X</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Noulas</surname><given-names>Anastasios</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Scellato</surname><given-names>Salvatore</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mascolo</surname><given-names>Cecilia</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hoodsquare: Modeling and recommending neighborhoods in location-based social networks</article-title>
        <source>2013 international conference on social computing</source>
        <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/socialcom.2013.17</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-data2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Barret</surname><given-names>Nelly</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Duchateau</surname><given-names>Fabien</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Favetta</surname><given-names>Franck</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bonneval</surname><given-names>Loïc</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Predicting the environment of a neighborhood: A use case for france</article-title>
        <source>International conference on data management technologies and applications (DATA)</source>
        <publisher-name>SciTePress</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <isbn>978-989-758-440-4</isbn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5220/0009885702940301</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-takada2014japanese">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>Misato</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>Naoki</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Hideki</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Japanese study on stratification, health, income, and neighborhood: Study protocol and profiles of participants</article-title>
        <source>Journal of epidemiology</source>
        <publisher-name>Japan Epidemiological Association</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.2188/jea.JE20130084</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2188/jea.JE20130084</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-frank2010development">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>Lawrence D</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sallis</surname><given-names>James F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Saelens</surname><given-names>Brian E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>Lauren</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>Kelli</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>Terry L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>Paul M</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The development of a walkability index: Application to the neighborhood quality of life study</article-title>
        <source>British journal of sports medicine</source>
        <publisher-name>British Association of Sport; Excercise Medicine</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>44</volume>
        <issue>13</issue>
        <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bjsm.2009.058701</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsm.2009.058701</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-leong2018biodiversity">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>Misha</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>Robert R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Trautwein</surname><given-names>Michelle D</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Biodiversity and socioeconomics in the city: A review of the luxury effect</article-title>
        <source>Biology Letters</source>
        <publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2018.0082</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsbl.2018.0082</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
