<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3756</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03756</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>A flexible search system for high-accuracy identification
of biological entities and molecules</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0169-0480</contrib-id>
<string-name>Max Franz</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8912-5699</contrib-id>
<string-name>Jeffrey V. Wong</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-7556-093X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Metin Can Siper</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-4650-6181</contrib-id>
<string-name>Christian Dallago</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-5"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9621-5046</contrib-id>
<string-name>John Giorgi</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3663-7113</contrib-id>
<string-name>Emek Demir</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-6059-6270</contrib-id>
<string-name>Chris Sander</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-6"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-7"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0185-8861</contrib-id>
<string-name>Gary D. Bader</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-8"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-9"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-10"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-11"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1"><sup>*</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>The Donnelly Centre, University of Toronto, Toronto,
Ontario, M5S 3E1, Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Computational Biology Program, Oregon Health and Science
University, Portland, OR 97239, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Cell Biology, Harvard Medical School, Boston,
MA, 02215, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-4">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Systems Biology, Harvard Medical School,
Boston, MA, 02215, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-5">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Informatics, Technische Universität München,
85748 Garching, Germany</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-6">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Data Sciences, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute,
Boston, MA, 02215, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-7">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, Boston, MA, 02142,
USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-8">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Computer Science, University of Toronto,
Ontario, M5S 2E4, Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-9">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Toronto,
Ontario, M5S 1A8, Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-10">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>The Lunenfeld-Tanenbaum Research Institute, Mount Sinai
Hospital, Toronto, Ontario, M5G 1X5, Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-11">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Princess Margaret Cancer Centre, University Health Network,
Toronto, Ontario, M5G 2C1, Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">* E-mail: <email></email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-09-09">
<day>9</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>67</issue>
<fpage>3756</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>biological entities</kwd>
<kwd>small molecules</kwd>
<kwd>grounding</kwd>
<kwd>identifiers</kwd>
<kwd>identification</kwd>
<kwd>search</kwd>
<kwd>Docker</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Identifying subcellular biological entities (genes, gene products,
  and small molecules) is essential in using and creating bioinformatics
  analysis tools, text mining, and accessible biological research apps.
  When research information is uniquely and unambiguously identified, it
  enables data to be accurately retrieved, cross-referenced, and
  integrated. In practice, biological entities are identified when they
  are associated with a matching record from a knowledge base that
  specialises in collecting and organising information of that type
  (e.g. genes in NCBI Gene). Our search service increases the efficiency
  and ease of use for identifying biological entities compared to prior
  approaches
  (<xref alt="Berriz &amp; Roth, 2008" rid="ref-berriz2008synergizer" ref-type="bibr">Berriz
  &amp; Roth, 2008</xref>;
  <xref alt="Côté et al., 2007" rid="ref-cote2007protein" ref-type="bibr">Côté
  et al., 2007</xref>;
  <xref alt="Juty et al., 2012" rid="ref-juty2012identifiers" ref-type="bibr">Juty
  et al., 2012</xref>;
  <xref alt="Reimand et al., 2007" rid="ref-reimand2007g" ref-type="bibr">Reimand
  et al., 2007</xref>). A comparison of similar tools is available in
  the software
  documentation(<xref alt="Franz et al., 2021a" rid="ref-githubRepoReadme" ref-type="bibr">Franz
  et al., 2021a</xref>). This identification service may be used to
  power research apps and tools, such as Biofactoid, GeneMANIA, and
  STRING, where colloquial entity names may be provided as input by
  users
  (<xref alt="Mering et al., 2003" rid="ref-mering2003string" ref-type="bibr">Mering
  et al., 2003</xref>;
  <xref alt="Mostafavi et al., 2008" rid="ref-mostafavi2008genemania" ref-type="bibr">Mostafavi
  et al., 2008</xref>;
  <xref alt="Wong et al., 2021" rid="ref-wong2021capturing" ref-type="bibr">Wong
  et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>Most biologists are unaware of the concept of grounding data to
  database identifiers (i.e., a value, usually a piece of text, that
  uniquely identifies the entity)
  (<xref alt="Abeysooriya et al., 2021" rid="ref-abeysooriya2021gene" ref-type="bibr">Abeysooriya
  et al., 2021</xref>). When an author labels a biological entity as
  ‘IL6’, for instance, they may not consider that this label could be
  ambiguous. Is this IL6 for <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> or for
  <italic>Mus musculus</italic>? If for <italic>Mus musculus</italic>,
  there is more than one gene that is called by that name. By mapping
  the user’s entity to a database identifier, in this case, 3569 in NCBI
  Gene, the data becomes disambiguated.</p>
  <p>Because many biologists are unaware of the utility of database
  identifiers, they often have the perception that the common or
  canonical name of an entity is sufficient for use with analysis tools.
  These users can be confused by traditional database grounding
  interfaces, where it is the user’s responsibility to select a
  particular identifier from a long list manually. This sort of
  grounding interface is incongruent with users’ mental model: What
  purpose could this list of entities have when the entity has already
  been identified by name?</p>
  <p>Our search service can be used to power interfaces that allow the
  user to identify an entity by name, as per their mental model. This
  makes grounding accessible to a wider set of researchers, with high
  ease of use. The service returns its results quickly, i.e., in less
  than 100 milliseconds on a 2.4 GHz dual-core processor with 8 GB of
  RAM, so that the result may be shown to a user interactively and
  without impeding the user’s actions. As output, the service returns a
  ranked list of possible groundings in descending order of relevance.
  The first entry in this list is the predicted identifier with the
  highest confidence given to the user’s input. The remainder of the
  list exists only to allow the user to recover from an incorrect first
  identifier. The service is customisable to accommodate various use
  cases, e.g., interactive grounding interfaces that can dynamically
  build up heuristics during a user’s session with the system.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="performance-evaluation">
  <title>Performance evaluation</title>
  <p>In the rare case where the service does not return the correct
  result as the first result, the app which uses the service may present
  one or more of the following entries in the list. For instance, the
  app may allow the user to indicate a correction manually — e.g., “I
  meant this IL6, not that one”. To facilitate this, each identifier in
  the results list has included a corresponding set of descriptions and
  metadata.</p>
  <p>To verify the accuracy of the service’s results, a test suite was
  created. The tests include entity names used in PubMed Central,
  Pathway Commons, and Biofactoid projects. Primarily, the test cases
  were prioritised based on popularity to measure how well
  commonly-researched entities are correctly assigned by the service. In
  all, there are currently over 750 test cases. Of those test cases, 91%
  returned the expected result as the first entry in the returned list
  in our tests. In nearly 98% of cases, the expected result was within
  the top ten entries in the returned list.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="mechanism">
  <title>Mechanism</title>
  <p>The database is built using a dynamic indexing approach with
  Elasticsearch. The system includes facilities to download the latest
  set of identifiers and associated metadata from NCBI Gene (including
  DNA, genes, and proteins in <italic>H. sapiens</italic>, <italic>M.
  musculus</italic>, <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, <italic>D.
  melanogaster</italic>, <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>C.
  elegans</italic>, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>R.
  norvegicus</italic>, <italic>D. rerio</italic>,
  <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic>, and extensible to other organisms), ChEBI
  (including small molecules, e.g., drugs), and UniProt (including
  proteins for cross-referencing NCBI Gene identifiers) to build the
  database. This indexing process is exposed as a top-level command,
  integrated with the search server itself, so that data sources can
  automatically be kept fresh regularly. The indices of the grounding
  service can be exported to an external repository (e.g. Zenodo) and
  directly imported in order to provide a means of referencing a
  particular version of an index and to reduce the need to manually
  build an index for researchers that reuse the grounding service in
  their own projects.</p>
  <p>The grounding service operates by making queries on the database,
  with the query string normalised – i.e., the string has punctuation
  removed, the case is normalised (e.g., “TNF-a” is considered the same
  as “tnf alpha”). A fuzzy query and a precise query are made to the
  database to ensure that both exact matches and near matches are
  included in the initial results. These initial results are processed
  with a multithreaded ranking approach. The Sørensen–Dice coefficient
  is used to rank the initial results based on each entity’s official
  name and synonyms, considering each entity’s best-case score.</p>
  <p>The Sørensen–Dice coefficient, <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[s_i]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
  for the <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[i]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>th
  synonym, is given as follows, where: * <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[b_t]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  is the total number of bigrams in both the
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[i]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>th
  synonym and the query string, * <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[b_i]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  is the total number of bigrams in the <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[i]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>th
  synonym, and * <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[b_q]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  is the total number of bigrams in the query string:</p>
  <p><disp-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[s_i = (\frac{2b_t}{b_i + b_q})]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="block" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
  <p>For tie-breaking, a series of further measures are used to order
  the results. These measures include an organism ranking preference,
  molecular charge (with a preference for charged, aqueous molecules),
  and the Sørensen–Dice coefficient of the official name. Finally, the
  data source (namespace) filter may be applied, if specified, in order
  to include results only of a particular type (e.g., small molecules
  from ChEBI).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="usage">
  <title>Usage</title>
  <p>With a complete index, the grounding service’s server can be
  started. The server exposes a REST-like API to enable client
  applications to query the index
  (<xref alt="Franz et al., 2021b" rid="ref-groundingswagger" ref-type="bibr">Franz
  et al., 2021b</xref>). The main endpoint in the API is search. A
  search contains a number of input parameters, the user’s typed entity
  name chief among them. Other parameters are optional. They may be
  implicitly specified by the user, or they may be specified by the
  client application. The target namespace is an optional parameter that
  filters the search result by a particular data source (e.g., NCBI
  Gene). When unspecified, no namespace filtering is applied. A second
  optional parameter is an organism ranking, which can inform the
  service of the relative likelihood of a search’s pertinence to a
  particular organism. An organism ranking based on general popularity,
  measured by PubMed mentions, is used by default
  (<xref alt="Maglott et al., 2010" rid="ref-gene2pubmed" ref-type="bibr">Maglott
  et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="discussion">
  <title>Discussion</title>
  <p>An existing app, Biofactoid, provides an example of how this
  grounding service empowers novice users to ground entities to database
  identifiers automatically. Biofactoid users typically take one to five
  minutes to summarise the molecular interactions with a paper. The
  database identifiers in author’s Biofactoid documents have been
  accurate thus far, as evaluated by extensive manual spot-checking, and
  these novice users require no training in or understanding of database
  identifiers in order to create these documents.</p>
  <p>Apps that previously required a user to explicitly specify an
  organism may instead use heuristics paired with the grounding
  service’s API to provide intelligent results without user
  intervention. On the other hand, organism-specific apps may leverage
  the organism ordering to provide results only for the relevant
  organism: The first instance of a non-specified organism in one of the
  returned entries indicates that there are no further grounding entries
  for the specified organism.</p>
  <p>Further, more natural search systems may emerge as a result of the
  approaches of this grounding service. A biological data search engine
  may allow for natural language queries, powered by the grounding
  service. A user may type a search, such as “interactions of tnf in
  human”, in order to get relevant results. If the user types an
  ambiguous query, such as “tnf”, the search engine may use the ranked
  results to provide intelligent follow-up questions: “Did you mean tnf
  (mouse)?” These results and follow-up questions may go so far as to be
  user-personalised. A user that predominantly searches for mouse genes
  may have the search engine provide custom-tailored results, based on a
  search history used to inform the grounding service.</p>
  <p>Modern research apps and tools motivate the need for robust, fast,
  reusable grounding tools that allow for easily identifying biological
  entities from their common names. Our grounding service can be used in
  apps to provide users with an easy-to-use experience in line with
  their mental model of biological entities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This project was funded by the US National Institutes of Health
  (NIH) [U41 HG006623, U41 HG003751, R01 HG009979 and P41 GM103504].</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-wong2021capturing">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Jeffrey V</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>Max</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Siper</surname><given-names>Metin Can</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>Dylan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Durupinar</surname><given-names>Funda</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dallago</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>Augustin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>John M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rodchenkov</surname><given-names>Igor</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Babur</surname><given-names>Özgün</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Capturing scientific knowledge in computable form</article-title>
        <source>bioRxiv</source>
        <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.03.10.382333</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-berriz2008synergizer">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Berriz</surname><given-names>Gabriel F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>Frederick P</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The synergizer service for translating gene, protein and other biological identifiers</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <issue>19</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn424</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-mering2003string">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mering</surname><given-names>Christian von</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Huynen</surname><given-names>Martijn</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jaeggi</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>Steffen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>Peer</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Snel</surname><given-names>Berend</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>STRING: A database of predicted functional associations between proteins</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg034</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-mostafavi2008genemania">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mostafavi</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>Debajyoti</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Warde-Farley</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grouios</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>Quaid</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GeneMANIA: A real-time multiple association network integration algorithm for predicting gene function</article-title>
        <source>Genome biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2008-9-s1-s4</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-reimand2007g">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Reimand</surname><given-names>Jüri</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kull</surname><given-names>Meelis</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>Hedi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>Jaanus</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vilo</surname><given-names>Jaak</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>G: Profiler—a web-based toolset for functional profiling of gene lists from large-scale experiments</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <issue>suppl_2</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm226</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-cote2007protein">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Côté</surname><given-names>Richard G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>Lennart</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kerrien</surname><given-names>Samuel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Reisinger</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Quan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Leinonen</surname><given-names>Rasko</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>Rolf</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hermjakob</surname><given-names>Henning</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The protein identifier cross-referencing (PICR) service: Reconciling protein identifiers across multiple source databases</article-title>
        <source>BMC bioinformatics</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-8-401</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-juty2012identifiers">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Juty</surname><given-names>Nick</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Le Novere</surname><given-names>Nicolas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Laibe</surname><given-names>Camille</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identifiers. Org and MIRIAM registry: Community resources to provide persistent identification</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>40</volume>
        <issue>D1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr1097</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-abeysooriya2021gene">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Abeysooriya</surname><given-names>Mandhri</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Soria</surname><given-names>Megan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kasu</surname><given-names>Mary Sravya</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ziemann</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gene name errors: Lessons not learned</article-title>
        <source>bioRxiv</source>
        <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.03.30.437702</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-groundingswagger">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>Max</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Jeffrey V</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Siper</surname><given-names>Metin Can</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pathway commons grounding search service</article-title>
        <source>GitHub documentation</source>
        <publisher-name>GitHub</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <uri>https://grounding.baderlab.org</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-githubRepoReadme">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>Max</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Jeffrey V</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Siper</surname><given-names>Metin Can</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GitHub: Pathway commons grounding search service</article-title>
        <source>GitHub repository</source>
        <publisher-name>GitHub</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <uri>https://github.com/PathwayCommons/grounding-search</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-gene2pubmed">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Maglott</surname><given-names>Donna</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ostell</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>Kim D</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tatusova</surname><given-names>Tatiana</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Entrez gene: Gene-centered information at NCBI</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>39</volume>
        <issue>suppl_1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki031</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
