<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1337</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01337</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>LGP: A robust Linear Genetic Programming implementation
on the JVM using Kotlin.</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5028-9987</contrib-id>
<string-name>Jed Simson</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Waikato, Waikato, New Zealand</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-02-10">
<day>10</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>42</issue>
<fpage>1337</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>JVM</kwd>
<kwd>Linear Genetic Programming</kwd>
<kwd>Genetic Programming</kwd>
<kwd>Machine Learning</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The desire for a system which can automatically craft computer
  programs has been known in the machine learning community for some
  time. Friedberg
  (<xref alt="1958" rid="ref-friedberg1958" ref-type="bibr">1958</xref>)
  experimented with a system that solved problems by randomly changing
  instructions in a program and favouring those changes which most
  frequently achieved a positive result.</p>
  <p>Linear Genetic Programming (LGP)
  (<xref alt="Brameier &amp; Banzhaf, 2007" rid="ref-brameier2007linear" ref-type="bibr">Brameier
  &amp; Banzhaf, 2007</xref>) is a paradigm of genetic programming that
  employs a representation of linearly sequenced instructions in
  automatically generated programs.</p>
  <p>There are two primary features which differentiate LGP from a
  traditional tree- based approach: first, LGP programs exhibit a unique
  graph-based data flow due to the way the contents of a particular
  register may be used multiple times during a programs execution. This
  leads to program graphs with higher variability thus enabling program
  solutions which are more compact in comparison to tree-based solutions
  to evolve.</p>
  <p>Secondly, special non-effective code coexists with a program’s
  effective code as a result of the imperative structure. Non-effective
  code refers to instructions within an LGP program which do not impact
  the program output. These non-effective instructions guard the
  effective instructions from disruption caused by the genetic operator
  application and allows variations to remain neutral in terms of a
  fitness change.</p>
  <p><monospace>LGP</monospace> is a Kotlin package for performing
  Linear Genetic Programming, with a focus on modern design, ease of
  use, and extensibility. The usage of the Kotlin language enables a
  functional and modern API that can make full usage of the Java Virtual
  Machine and rich Java package ecosystem. The LGP core package is
  designed for the generic case, offering a rich set of extensible
  components that can be adapted to the particular problem and a set of
  different core implementations of various LGP algorithms. A
  sub-package <monospace>LGP-lib</monospace> provides implementations
  for core components, including program generation, program instruction
  operations, and base program definitions. A set of example usages is
  available to aid users in getting started solving problems.</p>
  <p>The creation of <monospace>LGP</monospace> was motivated by the
  apparent lack of open-source Linear Genetic Programming
  implementations in an attempt to promote its usage. The project has
  intentions for use at the University of Waikato for future student
  projects and is currently in the process of being used for a research
  project in the image processing domain at the Max Planck Institute of
  Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics. The goal of
  <monospace>LGP</monospace> is to facilitate the usage of Linear
  Genetic Programming in solving problems in machine learning, as an
  alternative to other techniques.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-friedberg1958">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Friedberg</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A learning machine: Part i</article-title>
        <source>IBM J. Res. Dev.</source>
        <publisher-name>IBM Corp.</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Riverton, NJ, USA</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="1958-01">1958</year><month>01</month>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>0018-8646</issn>
        <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1147/rd.21.0002</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1147/rd.21.0002</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-brameier2007linear">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Brameier</surname><given-names>Markus F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Banzhaf</surname><given-names>Wolfgang</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Linear genetic programming</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Science &amp; Business Media</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
