<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1112</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01112</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>HRDS: A Python package for hierarchical raster
datasets</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1340-4373</contrib-id>
<string-name>Jon Hill</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Environment and Geography, University of
York, UK</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-11-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>37</issue>
<fpage>1112</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>numerical modelling</kwd>
<kwd>gis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Multi-scale modelling of geophysical domains requires data, such as
  bathymetry or topography to set up the initial conditions. These data
  are typically in the form of GIS rasters and can be derived from a
  number of sources. A single data source is commonly used which has a
  fixed spatial resolution. However, in multiscale models, e.g.
  Martin-Short et al.
  (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-Martin-Short2015" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>),
  the spatial scale of the model can vary by four or more orders of
  magnitude, e.g. from kilometre- to sub-metre-scale. In order to use
  the high resolution data set in the area of highest model resolution
  this limited-area highest resolution data must be blended with a wider
  area coarse resolution dataset. A choice therefore has to be made to
  either sacrifice some resolution or create a very large data file. For
  a wide region zooming into metre-scale processes this data file could
  be terabytes in size when re-sampled at the resolution of the highest
  resolution dataset. This problem is particularly acute when using GIS
  tools such as <monospace>qmesh</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Avdis et al., 2018" rid="ref-Avdis2018" ref-type="bibr">Avdis
  et al., 2018</xref>) to generate meshes from contours or other
  derivatives of the raster data.</p>
  <p><monospace>HRDS</monospace> is a solution to this problem as it
  allows a user to extract data from an arbitrary point from a stack of
  rasters, each of which can have different extents and resolutions.
  <monospace>HRDS</monospace> is based on the
  <monospace>GDAL</monospace> library
  (<xref alt="GDAL Development Team, 2018" rid="ref-GDALOGR2018" ref-type="bibr">GDAL
  Development Team, 2018</xref>) so can load all common raster formats.
  As these rasters are unlikely to agree on the topographic/bathymetric
  height where they overlap, a linear distance buffer is created to
  smoothly blend the two datasets together (Fig. 1). The user can
  specify the distance over which this buffer acts. The user gives HRDS
  a base raster which is low resolution but covers the whole extent of
  the domain to be modelled and then a stack of other rasters in
  priority order (typically increasing in resolution) along with a
  corresponding list of buffer distances. <monospace>HRDS</monospace>
  then calculates the linear buffers and stores these as rasters. Linear
  buffers are used as this makes the fewest assumptions about the data.
  Alternatives could include other functions, such as sigmoidal, which
  may be included in future releases, depending on use cases. The user
  can then request data at an arbitrary point which is calculated via
  bilinear interpolation. There are limitations in this approach in that
  rasters cannot be partially overlapped; all but the base raster must
  be entirely contained within another raster. This may be resolved in
  future versions. The software assumes all rasters are using the same
  coordinate system and datum.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Conceptual image demonstrating the blending of two data
    sets (coarse resolution - grey, high resolution: black). The buffer
    generated (red line) goes from zero at the edge of the high
    resolution dataset to 1.0 over the user-prescribed distance. The
    resulting data can then be calculated at the requied points (black
    dots on x-axis) as a function of the buffer and the two datasets
    (light blue thick line).</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="buffer_figure.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>This software solves a particular problem when using multiscale
  numerical models which use high resolution meshes: high resolution
  spatial data is required, but only for spatially limited regions. By
  blending a hierarchy of data sources, <monospace>HRDS</monospace>
  overcomes this problem and enables multiscale numerical problems to
  use spatially appropriate data to be used with minimal effort.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>I acknowledge the University of York and World University Network
  for funding my sabbatical visit which enabled this work to be
  completed. Also thanks to Tristan Salles and Jody Webster for hosting
  me at the University of Sydney.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-GDALOGR2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>GDAL Development Team</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <source>GDAL/OGR Geospatial Data Abstraction Library, Version 2.1.3.3</source>
        <publisher-name>Open Source Geospatial Foundation</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>http://www.gdal.org</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Avdis2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Avdis</surname><given-names>Alexandros</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Candy</surname><given-names>Adam S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Jon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>Stephan C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Piggott</surname><given-names>Matthew D</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Efficient unstructured mesh generation for marine renewable energy applications</article-title>
        <source>Renewable Energy</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-02">2018</year><month>02</month>
        <volume>116</volume>
        <issn>0960-1481</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2017.09.058</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Martin-Short2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Martin-Short</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>S C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Avdis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>P A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Piggott</surname><given-names>M D</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Tidal resource extraction in the Pentland Firth, UK: Potential impacts on flow regime and sediment transport in the Inner Sound of Stroma</article-title>
        <source>Renewable Energy</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015-04">2015</year><month>04</month>
        <volume>76</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <issn>0960-1481</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2014.11.079</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
