<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">701</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00701</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>EndoMineR for the extraction of endoscopic and associated
pathology data from medical reports</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1673-2663</contrib-id>
<string-name>Sebastian S Zeki</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Gastroenterology, St Thomas’ Hospital,
Westminster Bridge Bridge Road, London SE1 7EH</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>24</issue>
<fpage>701</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>example</kwd>
<kwd>tags</kwd>
<kwd>for the paper</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Medical data is increasingly kept in an electronic format worldwide
  (<xref alt="M. et al., 2016" rid="ref-Bretthauer2016Reporting" ref-type="bibr">M.
  et al., 2016</xref>). This serves many purposes including more
  efficient storage, distribution and accessibility of patient-focussed
  data. As important is the ability to analyse healthcare data for to
  optimize resource deployment and usage. The tools for the analysis are
  often statistical and rely on the provision of ‘clean’ datasets before
  this can be done. ‘Cleaning’ a dataset is often the most difficult
  aspect of any data analysis and involves the provision of meaningful
  and well-formatted data so that the interpretation of the analysis is
  not subject to the doubts of the data quality.</p>
  <p>The British Society of Gastroenterology recommends that all
  endoscopic data is kept in an electronic format particularly to
  facilitate audit and maintain standards through the Global Rating
  Scale (GRS)
  (<xref alt="JF., 2011" rid="ref-Stebbing2011quality" ref-type="bibr">JF.,
  2011</xref>). The endoscopic dataset is however only part of the
  patient’s story as many aspects of a patient’s gastroenterological
  care depend on the results of histopathological analysis of tissue
  taken during the examination. Pathology results are often available
  many days after the endoscopic result and usually stored in a separate
  data repository, although this may change with the arrival of an
  encompassing electronic patient record. Regardless of the method of
  storage, it is often difficult to associate the particular
  histopathological result with an endoscopic result. Further, even if
  the two data sets can be merged, a problem occurs in the isolation of
  various parts of each report such that each part can be individually
  analysed. Examples include the isolation of who the endoscopist was or
  the presence of dysplasia within a histopathology report. This is all
  the more difficult if the report is unstructured or partially
  structured free text.</p>
  <p>However if this can be done then many downstream analyses which
  benefit individual patients as well as the department, can be
  automated and include more complex analyses to determine follow-up
  regimes or endoscopic –pathologic lesion recognition performance.</p>
  <p>The EndoMineR package provides a comprehensive way to extract
  information from natural language endoscopy ann pathology reports as
  well as merging the two datasets so that pathology specimens are
  relevant to the endoscopy they came from. Furthermore the package also
  provides functions for the following types of analysis of endoscopic
  and pathological datasets:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <p>Patient surveillance. Examples including determining when
          patients should return for surveillance and who is
          overdue.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <label>2.</label>
          <p>Patient tracking. -Examples include determining the length
          of time since the last endoscopy, as well as aggregate
          functions such as finding how many endoscopies of a certain
          type have been done and predicting future burden.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <label>3.</label>
          <p>Patient flow - determining the kinds of endoscopies an
          individual patient may get over time eg for ablation of
          Barrett’s oesophagus.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <label>4.</label>
          <p>Quality of endoscopy and pathology reporting- Determining
          whether endoscopy quality is being maintained using some of
          the Global Rating scale metrics. Also making sure the
          pathology reports are complete.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <label>5.</label>
          <p>Diagnostic yield. Examples include determination of
          detection of dysplasia and cancer by endoscopist as a measure
          of lesion quality.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>It is the purpose of the package to create a unified process for
  merging of endoscopy reports with their associated pathology reports
  and to allow the extraction and tidying of commonly need data.
  Furthermore the package has methods for the analysis of the data in
  areas that are commonly required for high quality endoscopic services.
  This includes methods to track patients who need endoscopic
  surveillance, methods to determine endoscopic quality and disease
  detection rates. Also included are methods to assess patient flow
  through different types of endoscopy and to predict future usage of
  certain endoscopic techniques.</p>
  <p>The package is in the process of having each analysis function
  validated and functions some validation has been submitted in abstract
  form to gastroenterological societies.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Bretthauer2016Reporting">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>M.</surname><given-names>Bretthauer</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>L.</surname><given-names>Aabakken</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>al.</surname><given-names>Dekker E. et</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Reporting systems in gastrointestinal endoscopy: Requirements and standards facilitating quality improvement: European Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy position statement.</article-title>
        <source>United European Gastroenterology Journal</source>
        <publisher-name>https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.828487</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2050640616629079</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Stebbing2011quality">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>JF.</surname><given-names>Stebbing</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Quality assurance of endoscopy units. Best Practice and Research</article-title>
        <source>Clinical Gastroenterology</source>
        <publisher-name>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dld.2012.06.021</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dld.2012.06.021</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
