<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3460</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03460</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>RayFlare: flexible optical modelling of solar
cells</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9082-9506</contrib-id>
<string-name>Phoebe M. Pearce</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Physics, University of Cambridge, 19 JJ
Thomson Avenue, Cambridge CB3 0HE</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-05-26">
<day>26</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>65</issue>
<fpage>3460</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>physics</kwd>
<kwd>optics</kwd>
<kwd>solar cells</kwd>
<kwd>ray-tracing</kwd>
<kwd>rigorous coupled-wave analysis</kwd>
<kwd>transfer matrix method</kwd>
<kwd>multi-scale modelling</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Optical modelling is a key part of the design of solar cells, as
  the number of absorbed photons in the photovoltaic layer(s)
  fundamentally limits the current which can be generated by the cell.
  Some types of cell design, such as multi-junction cells (where
  multiple semiconductors with different bandgaps are stacked in a
  single structure to each absorb a different part of the solar
  spectrum) or ultra-thin solar cells
  (<xref alt="Hirst, 2019" rid="ref-Hirst2019" ref-type="bibr">Hirst,
  2019</xref>), require even more careful optical design. In the first
  case, it is generally desirable to match the current generated in each
  layer, requiring tuning of e.g. the bandgaps and layer thicknesses,
  while in the second case light-trapping structures such as gratings or
  surface textures are required to maintain high absorption and thus
  current while reducing the semiconductor thickness.</p>
  <p>Light-trapping structures range from the relatively simple
  (e.g. dielectric layers used as anti-reflection coatings on the front
  surface of all commercial solar cells) to highly engineered structures
  for very specific purposes (e.g. diffraction gratings for ultra-thin
  gallium arsenide (GaAs) solar cells for space applications). As such,
  many different simulation methods exist which are appropriate for
  modelling the effect of different light-trapping structures. These
  include:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>Simple Beer-Lambert law calculations</bold>: assumes the
      intensity of light in the material varies as
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[I(z) = I_0 e^{-\alpha z}]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
      where <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[z]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      is the depth in the material and <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\alpha]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      is the absorption coefficient. This neglects any effects due to
      reflection at interfaces, interference, diffraction etc.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>Ideal/theoretical reference cases</bold>: such as a
      perfect mirror or perfect Lambertian scatterer. These are often
      used for comparison purposes to benchmark the performance of
      realistic structures.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>Ray-tracing (RT)</bold>: a geometric optics method
      suitable for calculating reflection and refraction due to
      large-scale (compared to the wavelength) textures, such as the
      pyramidal texturing commonly using for silicon solar cells.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>Transfer-matrix method (TMM)</bold>: a wave-optical
      method suitable for calculating interference effects in thin films
      (transparent or absorbing). This is useful for e.g. calculating
      the effect of an anti-reflection coating on the front surface of a
      cell, or a distributed Bragg reflector (DBR) designed to reflect
      specific wavelengths of light.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>Full Maxwell solvers</bold>: including rigorous
      coupled-wave analysis (RCWA), also referred to as the Fourier
      modal method (FMM), finite element modelling (FEM) or
      finite-difference time-domain (FDTD) methods. Since these are more
      general solutions for solving Maxwell’s equations in
      (periodically) textured layers, these have many uses, but are
      often used in solar cell optics research to calculate the effect
      of gratings or arrays of nanoparticles on absorption in the
      cell.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Schematic of the methods implemented in RayFlare.
    <styled-content id="figU003Arayflare"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="rayflare_diagram_crop.pdf" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>The aim of RayFlare is to provide a single integrated environment
  with a consistent approach to defining structures which incorporates
  all the methods listed above (currently using RCWA as the Maxwell
  solver), as shown in
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="figU003Arayflare">Figure 1</xref>. The
  implementation allows users to simulate a whole structure using a
  single method, or to combine different methods and simulate the
  surfaces of the cell separately, if appropriate. RayFlare is a further
  development of the optical modelling capabilities developed for
  Solcore, an integrated solar cell modelling package
  (<xref alt="Alonso-Álvarez et al., 2018" rid="ref-Alonso-Alvarez2018" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Álvarez
  et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
  <p>Existing packages already implement one or more of these methods;
  for instance, the Python package <monospace>tmm</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Byrnes, 2016" rid="ref-Byrnes2016" ref-type="bibr">Byrnes,
  2016</xref>) performs TMM calculations, while
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[S^4]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  (<xref alt="Liu &amp; Fan, 2012" rid="ref-Liu2012" ref-type="bibr">Liu
  &amp; Fan, 2012</xref>), written in C++ but including a Python
  interface, implements RCWA. Many ray-tracing packages are available
  such as SunSolve
  (<xref alt="PV Lighthouse, 2021" rid="ref-SunSolve" ref-type="bibr">PV
  Lighthouse, 2021</xref>) which is widely used in solar cell research.
  There are also existing methods which combine multiple methods, such
  as CROWM
  (<xref alt="Lipovšek et al., 2011" rid="ref-Lipovsek2011" ref-type="bibr">Lipovšek
  et al., 2011</xref>) (ray-tracing with TMM for textured surfaces with
  thin-film layers), GenPro4
  (<xref alt="Santbergen et al., 2017" rid="ref-Santbergen2017" ref-type="bibr">Santbergen
  et al., 2017</xref>) and OPTOS
  (<xref alt="Eisenlohr et al., 2015" rid="ref-Eisenlohr2015" ref-type="bibr">Eisenlohr
  et al., 2015</xref>;
  <xref alt="Tucher et al., 2015" rid="ref-Tucher2015" ref-type="bibr">Tucher
  et al., 2015</xref>). The latter two use an angular redistribution
  matrix method, which allows the angle-dependent reflection and
  transmission properties of the front and back surface of the cell to
  be calculated separately (further information on this framework is
  given below). GenPro4 is a proprietary software which handles matrix
  calculation for the surfaces using TMM, ray-tracing, or combinations
  thereof, in addition to the subsequent matrix multiplication, while
  OPTOS is an open-source code which implements only the matrix
  multiplication, but not the generation of the matrices describing the
  surfaces. Thus, by including TMM, ray-tracing and RCWA methods as well
  as the angular redistribution matrix method, RayFlare provides a
  powerful modelling environment for a very wide range of structures. In
  addition, the ability to calculate not just total absorption per layer
  in the cell but also depth-dependent absorption profiles through the
  angular redistribution matrix framework is novel.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="rayflare">
  <title>RayFlare</title>
  <p>The RT, TMM or RCWA methods can be used independently to simulate a
  whole structure. In this case, the relevant materials and thicknesses
  of the layers (all methods), surface textures (RT) or grating shapes
  (RCWA) are defined by the user and the reflection, transmission,
  absorption per layer and (if specified) absorption profile in the
  structure are calculated by RayFlare. However, these methods can also
  be used in combination with each other by using the angular
  redistribution matrix formalism
  (<xref alt="Eisenlohr et al., 2015" rid="ref-Eisenlohr2015" ref-type="bibr">Eisenlohr
  et al., 2015</xref>). In this framework, the front and rear surface of
  the structure are decoupled from one another, and suitable methods are
  used for each surface to calculate the redistribution matrices. These
  matrices described how light striking the surface from different
  directions is scattered into other directions (which can be in
  transmission or reflection) or absorbed by any surface layers. The
  front and back surface are coupled by some bulk medium, in which
  simple Beer-Lambert absorption is assumed. This reduces the problem
  down to a matrix multiplication process to calculate total reflection,
  transmission, and absorption in the surface layers and bulk medium.
  Note that for the Beer-Lambert absorption approximation to be valid,
  the bulk medium must be thick enough that interference effects in it
  can be neglected, i.e. significantly thicker than the maximum
  wavelength being considered.</p>
  <p>While this matrix multiplication framework has been previously
  established, as discussed above, the novelty of RayFlare is that it
  will automatically calculate the necessary redistribution matrices for
  the user-defined structure at the required wavelengths as well as
  performing the matrix multiplication, including tracking absorption in
  any surface layers on the front and rear surface. It can also
  calculate absorption profiles in the surface and bulk layers,
  something which has not previously been demonstrated in combination
  with the redistribution matrix approach.</p>
  <p>The methods currently available to generate redistribution matrices
  are:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>Ray-tracing with the Fresnel equations</bold>: suitable
      for interfaces with some large-scale texture and no surface
      layers. The ray-tracer was written specifically for RayFlare.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>TMM</bold>: suitable for planar surfaces with multiple
      layers. The TMM method implemented in RayFlare is a modified and
      vectorized version of the <monospace>tmm</monospace> package
      (<xref alt="Byrnes, 2016" rid="ref-Byrnes2016" ref-type="bibr">Byrnes,
      2016</xref>).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>Integrated ray-tracing and transfer-matrix method</bold>:
      the probability of reflection/transmission (or absorption in
      interface layers) are calculated using TMM rather than through the
      Fresnel equations. This is suitable for large-scale textures with
      one or more thin (compared to the size of the texture features)
      surface layers.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>RCWA</bold>: suitable for gratings or other periodic
      wavelength-scale structures, which can be made of multiple layers
      including planar layers. RayFlare uses a modified version of
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[S^4]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      (<xref alt="Liu &amp; Fan, 2012" rid="ref-Liu2012" ref-type="bibr">Liu
      &amp; Fan, 2012</xref>) which is compatible with Python3 to
      perform RCWA calculations.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><bold>Ideal/theoretical reference cases</bold>: currently, a
      perfect mirror or a perfect Lambertian scatterer are
      implemented.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>As each of these methods are implemented independently, additional
  methods which can be used to calculate redistribution matrices can be
  added.</p>
  <p>The results of RayFlare’s ray-tracer have been compared with those
  of PVLighthouse’s wafer ray tracer tool
  (<xref alt="PV Lighthouse, 2020" rid="ref-Waferraytracer" ref-type="bibr">PV
  Lighthouse, 2020</xref>), while the results of the matrix framework
  using planar surfaces (TMM), a grating (RCWA) or pyramids
  (ray-tracing) have been compared to results generated using OPTOS
  (<xref alt="Tucher et al., 2015" rid="ref-Tucher2015" ref-type="bibr">Tucher
  et al., 2015</xref>), showing excellent agreement in both cases.
  RayFlare, or code which was integrated into RayFlare, has been used to
  simulate the emissivity/absorptivity of silicon heterojunction solar
  cells
  (<xref alt="Alonso-Álvarez et al., 2019" rid="ref-Alonso-Alvarez2019c" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Álvarez
  et al., 2019</xref>), design and simulate ultra-thin GaAs solar cells
  (<xref alt="Pearce et al., 2020" rid="ref-Pearce2020" ref-type="bibr">Pearce
  et al., 2020</xref>), and to simulate a perovskite on silicon tandem
  cell
  (<xref alt="Pearce &amp; Ekins-Daukes, 2019" rid="ref-Pearce2019a" ref-type="bibr">Pearce
  &amp; Ekins-Daukes, 2019</xref>)</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>I would like to thank Diego Alonso Álvarez for helping me
  innumerable times with Python, package management, and general
  software developing skills over the years, and Luis Usier Pimentel for
  coming up with the name `RayFlare’.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Pearce2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>Phoebe</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sayre</surname><given-names>Larkin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hirst</surname><given-names>Louise</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ekins-Daukes</surname><given-names>Nicholas J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Design of photonic light-trapping structures for ultra-thin solar cells</article-title>
        <source>Physics, simulation, and photonic engineering of photovoltaic devices IX</source>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name><surname>Freundlich</surname><given-names>Alexandre</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>Masakazu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>Stéphane</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <publisher-name>SPIE</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-03">2020</year><month>03</month>
        <isbn>9781510633131</isbn>
        <issn>1996756X</issn>
        <uri>https://www.spiedigitallibrary.org/conference-proceedings-of-spie/11275/2550136/Design-of-photonic-light-trapping-structures-for-ultra-thin-solar/10.1117/12.2550136.full</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1117/12.2550136</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Alonso-Alvarez2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Alonso-Álvarez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Führer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ekins-Daukes</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Solcore: a multi-scale, Python-based library for modelling solar cells and semiconductor materials</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Computational Electronics</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-09">2018</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <issn>1569-8025</issn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10825-018-1171-3 http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s10825-018-1171-3</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10825-018-1171-3</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Byrnes2016">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Byrnes</surname><given-names>Steven J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multilayer optical calculations</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1603.02720</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Pearce2019a">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>Phoebe</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ekins-Daukes</surname><given-names>Nicholas</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Open-source integrated optical modelling with RayFlare</article-title>
        <source>2019 IEEE 46th photovoltaic specialists conference (PVSC)</source>
        <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-06">2019</year><month>06</month>
        <isbn>978-1-7281-0494-2</isbn>
        <issn>01608371</issn>
        <uri>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8980868/</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/PVSC40753.2019.8980868</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Liu2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Victor</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Shanhui</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>S4: A free electromagnetic solver for layered periodic structures</article-title>
        <source>Computer Physics Communications</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>183</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <isbn>0010-4655</isbn>
        <issn>00104655</issn>
        <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cpc.2012.04.026</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpc.2012.04.026</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Santbergen2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Santbergen</surname><given-names>Rudi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Meguro</surname><given-names>Tomomi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Suezaki</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Koizumi</surname><given-names>Gensuke</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Kenji</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zeman</surname><given-names>Miro</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GenPro4 Optical Model for Solar Cell Simulation and Its Application to Multijunction Solar Cells</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Journal of Photovoltaics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-05">2017</year><month>05</month>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <issn>2156-3381</issn>
        <uri>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7866819/</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/JPHOTOV.2017.2669640</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Eisenlohr2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Eisenlohr</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tucher</surname><given-names>Nico</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Höhn</surname><given-names>Oliver</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>Hubert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>Marius</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kiefel</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>Jan Christoph</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bläsi</surname><given-names>Benedikt</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Matrix formalism for light propagation and absorption in thick textured optical sheets</article-title>
        <source>Optics Express</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <issn>1094-4087</issn>
        <uri>https://www.osapublishing.org/abstract.cfm?URI=oe-23-11-A502</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1364/OE.23.00A502</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26072875</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Tucher2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Tucher</surname><given-names>Nico</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Eisenlohr</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kiefel</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Höhn</surname><given-names>Oliver</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>Hubert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>Marius</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>Claas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>Jan Christoph</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bläsi</surname><given-names>Benedikt</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>3D optical simulation formalism OPTOS for textured silicon solar cells</article-title>
        <source>Optics Express</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>23</volume>
        <issue>24</issue>
        <issn>1094-4087</issn>
        <uri>https://www.osapublishing.org/abstract.cfm?URI=oe-23-24-A1720</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1364/OE.23.0A1720</pub-id>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26698818</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Alonso-Alvarez2019c">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Alonso-Álvarez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Augusto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Llin</surname><given-names>L. Ferre</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mellor</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ekins-Daukes</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Thermal emissivity of silicon heterojunction solar cells</article-title>
        <source>Solar Energy Materials and Solar Cells</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>201</volume>
        <issue>May</issue>
        <issn>09270248</issn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.solmat.2019.110051</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.solmat.2019.110051</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Waferraytracer">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>PV Lighthouse</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Wafer ray tracer</article-title>
        <publisher-name>PV Lighthouse</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <uri>https://www2.pvlighthouse.com.au/calculators/wafer ray tracer/wafer ray tracer.html</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SunSolve">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>PV Lighthouse</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SunSolve</article-title>
        <publisher-name>PV Lighthouse</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <uri>https://www.pvlighthouse.com.au/sunsolve</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Hirst2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hirst</surname><given-names>Louise</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ever thinner high-efficiency cells</article-title>
        <source>Nature Energy</source>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-09">2019</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <issn>20587546</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41560-019-0444-9</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Lipovsek2011">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Lipovšek</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Krč</surname><given-names>Janez</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Topič</surname><given-names>Marko</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Optical model for thin-film photovoltaic devices with large surface textures at the front side</article-title>
        <source>Informacije MIDEM</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <volume>41</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <issn>03529045</issn>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
