<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2106</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02106</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>mhealthtools: A Modular R Package for Extracting Features
from Mobile and Wearable Sensor Data</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-6967-2185</contrib-id>
<string-name>Phil Snyder</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-0741-8683</contrib-id>
<string-name>Meghasyam Tummalacherla</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1168-8982</contrib-id>
<string-name>Thanneer Perumal</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4719-9120</contrib-id>
<string-name>Larsson Omberg</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Sage Bionetworks</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-01-06">
<day>6</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>47</issue>
<fpage>2106</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>mhealth</kwd>
<kwd>mobile health</kwd>
<kwd>digital health</kwd>
<kwd>ehealth</kwd>
<kwd>accelerometer</kwd>
<kwd>feature extraction</kwd>
<kwd>gait</kwd>
<kwd>heart rate</kwd>
<kwd>tapping</kwd>
<kwd>tremor</kwd>
<kwd>parkinsons</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>As life expectancy continues to rise with the increasing prevalence
  of modern medical practices, the costs associated with caring for an
  increasingly large elderly population have climbed as well. In
  response, there has been an evolving interest in using relatively
  inexpensive remote monitoring methods outside of the clinic to aid in
  the early detection and real-time assessment of Alzheimer’s disease
  (<xref alt="Kourtis et al., 2019" rid="ref-kourtis_2019" ref-type="bibr">Kourtis
  et al., 2019</xref>), Parkinson’s disease
  (<xref alt="Monje et al., 2019" rid="ref-monje_2019" ref-type="bibr">Monje
  et al., 2019</xref>), mood disorders
  (<xref alt="Jacobson et al., 2019" rid="ref-jacobson_2019" ref-type="bibr">Jacobson
  et al., 2019</xref>), and a wide array of other diseases
  (<xref alt="Majumder &amp; Deen, 2019" rid="ref-majumder_deen_2019" ref-type="bibr">Majumder
  &amp; Deen, 2019</xref>). Consumer-grade sensors embedded in
  smartphones and wearables have the potential to provide clinicians
  with remote <italic>digital biomarkers</italic> that can aid in the
  early detection and monitoring of disease via frequent, objective, and
  unobtrusive assessments
  (<xref alt="Coravos et al., 2019" rid="ref-coravos_2019" ref-type="bibr">Coravos
  et al., 2019</xref>). The extraction of relevant digital biomarkers
  from raw sensor data requires a combination of signal processing, data
  science and biological expertise in addition to extensive validation
  data
  (<xref alt="Goldsack et al., 2019" rid="ref-goldsack_chasse_wood_2019" ref-type="bibr">Goldsack
  et al., 2019</xref>;
  <xref alt="Monje et al., 2019" rid="ref-monje_2019" ref-type="bibr">Monje
  et al., 2019</xref>). Software libraries to preprocess and extract
  features from such data are becoming increasingly numerous and varied
  (<xref alt="Czech &amp; Patel, 2019" rid="ref-czech_2019" ref-type="bibr">Czech
  &amp; Patel, 2019</xref>;
  <xref alt="Saez-Pons et al., 2019" rid="ref-saez-pons_2019" ref-type="bibr">Saez-Pons
  et al., 2019</xref>;
  <xref alt="van Gent et al., 2019" rid="ref-paul_van_gent_2019" ref-type="bibr">van
  Gent et al., 2019</xref>). But without an established set of
  preprocessing techniques and features for capturing disease signal, it
  becomes necessary to make use of a broad spectrum of methods and tools
  when exploring potential biomarkers
  (<xref alt="Kumar et al., 2013" rid="ref-kumar_nilsen_2013" ref-type="bibr">Kumar
  et al., 2013</xref>). To this end we have developed mhealthtools: an R
  package that aids in the construction of data pipelines for remote
  sensor data analysis.</p>
  <p>mhealthtools is an open-source, modular R package for preprocessing
  and extracting features from remote sensor data collected using mobile
  and wearable devices. The package is written in a functional style so
  that various components of the preprocessing and feature extraction
  pipeline can be inserted, omitted, moved around, extended, and shared
  between multiple libraries with minimal overhead. Depending on the
  data source, the package includes a default set of preprocessing and
  feature extraction behavior for convenient exploratory analysis. The
  inertial measurement unit (IMU) (e.g., accelerometer and gyroscope)
  features extracted using this package have been used by Perumal et al.
  (<xref alt="2018" rid="ref-perumal_2018" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)
  and the tapping features by Neto et al.
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-neto_2019" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>),
  both using data from the mPower study
  (<xref alt="Bot et al., 2016" rid="ref-bot_2016" ref-type="bibr">Bot
  et al., 2016</xref>). The heart rate features have been used as part
  of a validation study
  (<xref alt="Omberg, n.d." rid="ref-omberg_2020" ref-type="bibr">Omberg,
  n.d.</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="design">
  <title>Design</title>
  <p>Data collection from sensors embedded in wearables and mobile
  devices can occur through active tasks, where participants perform a
  specified task according to a protocol, or passive tasks, where sensor
  measurements are collected discreetly in the background during daily
  living conditions. Features computed from these measurements are
  typically used as the basis of statistical models designed to explore
  potential patient outcomes or measures of disease. mhealthtools
  provides functionality to construct processing pipelines of raw data
  sourced from sensor measurements recorded during these tasks. This
  includes data transformations, filtering and feature extraction. In
  addition to these generalizable pipeline-building functions,
  mhealthtools provides a set of curated, high level functions that
  compute features using already constructed pipelines designed for
  specific active tasks.</p>
  <p>In the case of accelerometer and gyroscope sensors, mhealthtools
  provides functions (<monospace>accelerometer_features</monospace> and
  <monospace>gyroscope_features</monospace>) for extracting general
  features — agnostic of whether data is being collected as part of an
  active or passive task. Higher level functions,
  <monospace>get_heartrate</monospace>,
  <monospace>get_tapping_features</monospace>,
  <monospace>get_walk_features</monospace> and
  <monospace>get_tremor_features</monospace> are designed to compute
  features for specific active tasks that use the camera, touch screen
  sensors, and the underlying
  <monospace>accelerometer_features</monospace> and
  <monospace>gyroscope_features</monospace>, respectively. Unlike
  accelerometer and gyroscope, touch screen and camera sensors do not
  have their own task agnostic feature extraction functions. This
  hierarchical organization of modules is illustrated in the figure
  below.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>The heirarchical organization of mhealthtools. Note that
    touch screen and camera sensors do not have their own task agnostic
    feature extraction functions.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figure_one.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>All modules, whether they operate at the activity or sensor level,
  provide some level of parameterization to modify the default feature
  extraction pipeline. This concept is best illustrated by an
  activity-level module which makes use of both the accelerometer and
  gyroscope feature extraction functions. For example,
  <monospace>get_tremor_features</monospace> is sufficiently
  straightforward to compute features when provided with only the input
  data as a dataframe in a standardized format — while being flexible
  enough to accept an assemblage of parameters that control signal
  detrending, frequency filtering, windowing, which feature sets to
  compute and more. Additionally, it’s possible to modify the order in
  which certain preprocessing steps are applied or to include external
  functions within the pipeline.</p>
  <p>This flexibility in parameterization is an intentional design
  choice of the mhealthtools package, made possible by adhering to a
  consistent functional paradigm. The user is able to easily mix and
  match components of pipelines which may be designed for extracting
  features from different activities without needing to worry about
  potentially inconsistent output formats from those components.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>An expanded view of the hierarchical and modular
    organization of mhealthtools.
    <monospace>get_tremor_features</monospace> calls both
    <monospace>accelerometer_features</monospace> and
    <monospace>gyroscope_features</monospace>, which in turn call a
    sequence of functions that preprocesses (transforms) then extracts
    features from the inputted raw sensor data. Each of the components
    above can be internally modified, extended, or omitted altogether,
    depending on the desired output.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figure_two.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>In the case of the IMU sensors, the paradigm is as follows:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Input — raw sensor data, in a standardized format.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Transform — raw sensor data (by, e.g., tidying
      (<xref alt="Wickham, 2014" rid="ref-hadley_2014" ref-type="bibr">Wickham,
      2014</xref>), computing rates of change, windowing).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Extract — features by computing statistics upon individual
      columns, typically grouped on an index such as axis or
      axis/window.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Return — features for each group.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>The <italic>transform</italic> and <italic>extract</italic> steps
  may be modified relatively easily, allowing functions from external
  libraries to be included as part of the pipeline without needing to
  modify the source code of the package. In addition, to handle the
  processing of large datasets, mhealthtools provides a robust
  error-handling mechanism in the case of corrupted input data or other
  data processing issues — guaranteeing a consistent output.</p>
  <p>For more information, including how to use custom preprocessing
  functions as part of the <italic>transform</italic> step and how to
  include your own features or machine learning models within the
  feature extraction pipeline, see the package vignette
  <italic>Extending mhealthtools</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="features">
  <title>Features</title>
  <p>Default feature sets are provided for both time and frequency
  domains. For a full list of features and their definitions, see the
  <italic>Feature Definitions</italic> vignette.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="comparison-with-related-packages">
  <title>Comparison with Related Packages</title>
  <p>There exist a number of other packages that were built to work with
  data collected from sensors in a digital health research setting.
  HeartPy
  (<xref alt="van Gent et al., 2019" rid="ref-paul_van_gent_2019" ref-type="bibr">van
  Gent et al., 2019</xref>) is a Python package focused on extracting
  features from PPG data collected through PPG or camera sensors. GaitPy
  (<xref alt="Czech &amp; Patel, 2019" rid="ref-czech_2019" ref-type="bibr">Czech
  &amp; Patel, 2019</xref>) is a Python package designed to extract gait
  features collected by an accelerometer sensor on the lower back. It
  includes functionality to identify gait bouts (for measurements
  collected during free-living conditions), implementations of a number
  of published algorithms for deriving gait features, and a convenience
  function to visualize gait events. PDkit
  (<xref alt="Saez-Pons et al., 2019" rid="ref-saez-pons_2019" ref-type="bibr">Saez-Pons
  et al., 2019</xref>) is the package with the most overlap in
  functionality with mhealthtools. Focused on Parkinson’s disease, PDkit
  aims to provide a broad suite of tools, ranging from convenience
  functions for loading data from popular Parkinson’s digital health
  datasets, feature extraction on measurements collected during commonly
  performed tasks in Parkinson’s studies, and even functions which
  attempt to map sensor measurements to Unified Parkinson’s Disease
  Rating Scale (UPDRS) Part III scores, a clinically validated metric
  for measuring Parkinson’s disease progression.</p>
  <p>In comparison to these packages, mhealthtools is focused solely on
  the feature extraction process and tries to offer a transparent and
  generalizable framework that makes minimal assumptions about how the
  sensor data was collected and how it should be processed. This is
  reflected in a function design that caters to both ease of use and
  extensibility. mhealthtools adopts robust, functional programming
  practices, such as predictable error handling, function interfaces,
  and output formats, making the package a good fit for ETL workloads
  and streaming data. The default features for IMU sensors were chosen
  to work well in both clinical and free-living contexts, but are
  otherwise signal agnostic and not chosen with one particular phenotype
  or activity type in mind (task specific feature extraction functions,
  such as <monospace>get_walk_features</monospace>, may make use of
  default argument values to these otherwise task agnostic feature
  sets). For these reasons, mhealthtools is useful for both quickly
  generating feature sets for exploratory analysis as well as
  coordinating the extraction of features across multiple packages for
  more advanced data pipelines.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-bot_2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Bot</surname><given-names>Brian M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Suver</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>Elias Chaibub</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kellen</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>Arno</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bare</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Doerr</surname><given-names>Megan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pratap</surname><given-names>Abhishek</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilbanks</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dorsey</surname><given-names>E. Ray</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Friend</surname><given-names>Stephen H.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The mPower study, Parkinson disease mobile data collected using ResearchKit</article-title>
        <source>Nature Scientific Data</source>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-03">2016</year><month>03</month>
        <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/sdata201611</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sdata.2016.11</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-coravos_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Coravos</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Khozin</surname><given-names>Sean</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mandl</surname><given-names>Kenneth D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Developing and adopting safe and effective digital biomarkers to improve patient outcomes</article-title>
        <source>npj Digital Medicine</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-03">2019</year><month>03</month>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-019-0090-4</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41746-019-0090-4</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-czech_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Czech</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>Shyamal</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GaitPy: An open-source python package for gait analysis using an accelerometer on the lower back</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-11">2019</year><month>11</month>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>43</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01778</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01778</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-goldsack_chasse_wood_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Goldsack</surname><given-names>Jen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chasse</surname><given-names>Rachel A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>William A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Digital endpoints library can aid clinical trials for new medicines</article-title>
        <source>STAT</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-11">2019</year><month>11</month>
        <uri>https://www.statnews.com/2019/11/06/digital-endpoints-library-clinical-trials-drug-development/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-hadley_2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>Hadley</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Tidy data</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Statistical Software, Articles</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <issn>1548-7660</issn>
        <uri>https://www.jstatsoft.org/v059/i10</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v059.i10</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-jacobson_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>Nicholas C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weingarden</surname><given-names>Hilary</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>Sabine</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Digital biomarkers of mood disorders and symptom change</article-title>
        <source>npj Digital Medicine</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-02">2019</year><month>02</month>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-019-0078-0</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41746-019-0078-0</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-kourtis_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kourtis</surname><given-names>Lampros C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Regele</surname><given-names>Oliver B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>Justin M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Graham B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Digital biomarkers for Alzheimer’s disease: The mobile/wearable devices opportunity</article-title>
        <source>npj Digital Medicine</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-02">2019</year><month>02</month>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-019-0084-2</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41746-019-0084-2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-kumar_nilsen_2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Santosh</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>Wendy J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Abernethy</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>Audie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pavel</surname><given-names>Misha</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>William T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shar</surname><given-names>Albert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Spring</surname><given-names>Bonnie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Spruijt-Metz</surname><given-names>Donna</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>al.</surname></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mobile health technology evaluation: The mHealth evidence workshop</article-title>
        <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>
        <publisher-name>U.S. National Library of Medicine</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013-08">2013</year><month>08</month>
        <volume>45</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <uri>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3803146/</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2013.03.017</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-majumder_deen_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>Sumit</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Deen</surname><given-names>M Jamal</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Smartphone sensors for health monitoring and diagnosis</article-title>
        <source>Sensors (Basel, Switzerland)</source>
        <publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-05">2019</year><month>05</month>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <uri>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6539461/</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s19092164</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-monje_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Monje</surname><given-names>Mariana H.g.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Foffani</surname><given-names>Guglielmo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Obeso</surname><given-names>José</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sánchez-Ferro</surname><given-names>Álvaro</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>New sensor and wearable technologies to aid in the diagnosis and treatment monitoring of Parkinson’s disease</article-title>
        <source>Annual Review of Biomedical Engineering</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-04">2019</year><month>04</month>
        <volume>21</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-bioeng-062117-121036</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-neto_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>Elias Chaibub</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pratap</surname><given-names>Abhishek</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Perumal</surname><given-names>Thanneer M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tummalacherla</surname><given-names>Meghasyam</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>Phil</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bot</surname><given-names>Brian M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Trister</surname><given-names>Andrew D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Friend</surname><given-names>Stephen H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mangravite</surname><given-names>Lara</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Omberg</surname><given-names>Larsson</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Detecting the impact of subject characteristics on machine learning-based diagnostic applications</article-title>
        <source>npj Digital Medicine</source>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-10">2019</year><month>10</month>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <uri>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-019-0178-x</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41746-019-0178-x</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-omberg_2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="manuscript">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Omberg</surname><given-names>Larsson</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Validation of a smartphone measure of VO2max</article-title>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-perumal_2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Perumal</surname><given-names>Thanneer M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tummalacherla</surname><given-names>Meghasyam</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>Phil</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>Elias Chaibub</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dorsey</surname><given-names>E. Ray</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mangravite</surname><given-names>Lara</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Omberg</surname><given-names>Larsson</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Remote assessment, in real-world setting, of tremor severity in Parkinson’s disease patients using smartphone inertial sensors</article-title>
        <source>ACM Digital Library</source>
        <publisher-name>ACM</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-10">2018</year><month>10</month>
        <uri>https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3267612</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3267305.3267612</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-saez-pons_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Saez-Pons</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stamate</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Roussos</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PDkit: An open source data science toolkit for Parkinson’s disease</article-title>
        <source>Adjunct proceedings of the 2019 ACM international joint conference on pervasive and ubiquitous computing and proceedings of the 2019 ACM international symposium on wearable computers</source>
        <publisher-name>ACM</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <isbn>978-1-4503-6869-8</isbn>
        <uri>http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/3341162.3346277</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3341162.3346277</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-paul_van_gent_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>van Gent</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>de Bruin</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kris</surname></name>
          <name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>Glenn</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Paulvangentcom/heartrate_analysis_python 1.2.5</source>
        <publisher-name>Zenodo</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-12">2019</year><month>12</month>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3563546</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.3563546</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
