<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3435</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03435</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>pollucheck v1.0: A package to explore open-source air
pollution data</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-1764-1379</contrib-id>
<string-name>Adithi R. Upadhya</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Pratyush Agrawal</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0400-6584</contrib-id>
<string-name>Sreekanth Vakacherla</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Meenakshi Kushwaha</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>ILK Labs, Bengaluru, India</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Center for Study of Science, Technology and Policy,
Bengaluru, India</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-06-12">
<day>12</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>63</issue>
<fpage>3435</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>open-source</kwd>
<kwd>air quality</kwd>
<kwd>shiny</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Air pollution impacts human health, quality of living, climate, and
  the economy
  (<xref alt="Hystad et al., 2020" rid="ref-HystadU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Hystad
  et al., 2020</xref>). To assess its impact and facilitate mitigation
  actions, quantification of air pollution is vital. Measurements are
  the most accurate way of quantifying air pollution. Many countries
  conduct regulatory measurements of various air pollutants (e.g., fine
  and respirable particulate matter, nitrogen dioxide, sulfur dioxide,
  and surface ozone) and make the data available publicly.</p>
  <p>Air pollution data sets typically span several seasons or years and
  real-time data are recorded typically every hour or at a higher
  frequency. With the ever increasing amount of data and number of data
  providers, there is a clear need for tools to handle, analyze, and
  visualize large data sets. The current Shiny app
  <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> aims at a simple workflow to
  generate a suite of statistical plots and summary statistics
  (<xref alt="Chang et al., 2021" rid="ref-ShinyU003A2021" ref-type="bibr">Chang
  et al., 2021</xref>). Users do not need any programming background to
  analyze time series data and generate a variety of plots.</p>
  <p><monospace>pollucheck</monospace> can handle real-time pollution
  and co-located meteorological data (if available) from the three most
  popular open-source air pollution databases:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="openaq.org">OpenAQ</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="airnow.gov">AirNow</ext-link>,
  and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="app.cpcbccr.com">Indian
  Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB) dashboard</ext-link>. While
  CPCB data are specific to Indian regulatory monitoring stations,
  OpenAQ hosts the global open-source pollution databases and AirNow
  hosts the global PM<sub>2.5</sub> (mass concentration of particulate
  matter with an aerodynamic diameter less than or equal to 2.5 microns)
  data, collected under the United States Embassy and Consulates’ air
  quality monitoring programmes.</p>
  <p>The output of <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> is displayed in
  seven tabs. Different packages used for building
  <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> include
  <monospace>tidyverse</monospace>, <monospace>openair</monospace>,
  <monospace>shiny</monospace>, <monospace>bslib</monospace>,
  <monospace>forecast</monospace>, <monospace>biwavelet</monospace>,
  <monospace>readxl</monospace>, <monospace>DT</monospace>,
  <monospace>data.table</monospace>, <monospace>nortest</monospace>, and
  <monospace>zoo</monospace>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of Need</title>
  <p>Pollution data from these sources are typically in different file
  formats and templates that require customised codes or programmes for
  analysis. Also, a rigorous quality check of the data is preferred
  before visualization (plotting) and reporting.
  <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> offers a single-stop solution
  for</p>
  <list list-type="roman-lower">
    <list-item>
      <label>(i)</label>
      <p>handling the pollution data from the open-source databases,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>(ii)</label>
      <p>applying a suite of quality check options,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>(iii)</label>
      <p>generating a variety of summary statistics at various averaging
      intervals,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>(iv)</label>
      <p>performing time series analysis,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>(v)</label>
      <p>generating a bunch of temporal and statistical plots, and</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>(vi)</label>
      <p>comparing data from two input files.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>To our knowledge, currently there is no application that can
  generate utilisable summary statistics and plots using the data from
  the pollution databases. However, there are a few Shiny apps that deal
  with data cleaning and visualization of pollution data collected from
  single/multiple air quality instruments
  (<xref alt="Salmon et al., 2017" rid="ref-SalmonU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Salmon
  et al., 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Upadhya et al., 2020" rid="ref-UpadhyaU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Upadhya
  et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="app-display">
  <title>App Display</title>
  <list list-type="roman-lower">
    <list-item>
      <label>i)</label>
      <p>The <monospace>File</monospace> tab is used to upload the input
      file and to specify the source and time resolution of the input
      data. The default time zone is set to
      <italic>Asia/Kolkata</italic>. For OpenAQ and AirNow data sets,
      appropriate time zones need to be selected based on the input
      file. For the CPCB data set, the time zone option is default and
      inactive. A set of quality check options for the (a) removal of
      negative values, (b) removal of consecutive duplicate values, and
      (c) detection of outliers are provided. Data completeness criteria
      (minimum percentage of data required) for computing daily mean
      values can be specified. If the input file contains simultaneous
      PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> (mass concentration of
      particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter less than or equal
      to 10 microns) data, the app computes the
      PM<sub>2.5</sub>/PM<sub>10</sub> ratio, a useful metric in the air
      pollution field to identify sources of PM and to estimate
      PM<sub>2.5</sub> when only PM<sub>10</sub> is available
      (<xref alt="Chan &amp; Yao, 2008" rid="ref-ChanU003A2008" ref-type="bibr">Chan
      &amp; Yao, 2008</xref>;
      <xref alt="Chu et al., 2015" rid="ref-ChuU003A2015" ref-type="bibr">Chu
      et al., 2015</xref>;
      <xref alt="Spandana et al., 2021" rid="ref-SpandanaU003A2021" ref-type="bibr">Spandana
      et al., 2021</xref>). The selected quality check or completeness
      criteria will be applied to all the parameters of the input file.
      Hourly or daily mean values of all the parameters can be displayed
      and downloaded (as <monospace>.csv</monospace>) from this tab.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>ii)</label>
      <p>The <monospace>Summary</monospace> tab provides various
      statistics (central tendencies, percentiles, minimum, maximum,
      standard deviation, interquartile range, etc.) for all the
      parameters in the input file at three different averaging
      intervals. The averaging intervals can be selected using the
      drop-down menu. The displayed statistics can be downloaded.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>iii)</label>
      <p>The <monospace>Summary Plots</monospace> tab generates (a) a
      data availability plot for all the parameters (based on daily mean
      values), (b) a time series plot, (c) box and whisker plots, (d) a
      vertical bar plot, and (e) diurnal variability plots. Except for
      the data availability plot, the parameter of interest to plot
      needs to be selected from the drop-down menu. Plots can be
      generated using hourly or daily mean data. The diurnal variability
      plots can be plotted either by aggregating the whole data in the
      input file or month wise. Considering the general log-normal
      nature of the pollution data, an option is provided for the
      diurnal variability plots to be plotted using mean and standard
      deviations or median and interquartile ranges. The title and
      y-axis labels of the plots are editable.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>iv)</label>
      <p>The <monospace>Statistical Plots</monospace> tab can be used to
      conduct normality tests (Anderson-Darling and Shapiro-Wilk),
      generate density and quantile-quantile (QQ) plots, generate
      autocorrelogram, and conduct trends and periodicity analysis on
      the parameter selected. While autocorrelogram is generated based
      on monthly mean values, trend (the Mann-Kendall test) and
      periodicity (wavelet analysis) analyses are conducted on daily
      mean values of the selected parameter. For trend and periodicity
      analyses and generating autocorrelogram, the missing daily mean
      values are imputed using the <monospace>forecast</monospace>
      package
      (<xref alt="Hyndman &amp; Khandakar, 2008" rid="ref-HyndmanU003A2008" ref-type="bibr">Hyndman
      &amp; Khandakar, 2008</xref>).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>v)</label>
      <p>The <monospace>Linear Regression</monospace> tab allows a user
      to perform univariable and multiple linear regression analyses
      among the parameters of choice. For univariable linear regression,
      a scatter plot will be generated with least-squares linear fit.
      For multiple linear regression, multiple independent parameters
      can be selected. A scatter plot between the dependent variable and
      fitted data (using regression coefficients) will be generated.
      Relevant statistical coefficients are provided along with the
      plots.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>vi)</label>
      <p>The <monospace>Compare</monospace> tab allows users to upload a
      second data file to compare data between the selected parameters
      from the two input files. The selected quality check criteria
      conditions applied on the parameters of the first input file will
      be automatically applied to the parameters in the second input
      file. Time-series, scatter, and diurnal variability plots of the
      two parameters of interest will be generated.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>vii)</label>
      <p>Some features of the widely used <monospace>openair</monospace>
      package
      (<xref alt="Carslaw &amp; Ropkins, 2012" rid="ref-CarslawU003A2012" ref-type="bibr">Carslaw
      &amp; Ropkins, 2012</xref>) are integrated into
      <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> with permission. Calendar and
      time variation plots of the selected parameter are generated in
      this tab. Daily data will be used for Calendar plots and hourly
      data will be used for time variation plots.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>An extensive list of frequently asked questions (FAQs) is provided
  as a separate tab for a better understanding of the
  <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> functioning, detailed features of
  the plots, and analysis and the various packages used to build
  <monospace>pollucheck</monospace>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="limitations">
  <title>Limitations</title>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <label>1)</label>
      <p><monospace>pollucheck</monospace> does not download data
      automatically from the cloud. Downloaded files need to be provided
      as input.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>2)</label>
      <p>Multiple files cannot be uploaded to
      <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> at a given time.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>3)</label>
      <p>The current version of <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> is
      limited to accepting real-time data files from only three data
      sources.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>4)</label>
      <p>Some analyses (e.g., periodicity analysis) can be performed
      using daily mean values only.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>5)</label>
      <p>Caution needs to be exercised when using the averaged wind
      direction data, since wind direction is a vector quantity; hence
      it needs to be processed in a different way which has not been
      implemented here. Only wind direction data at one hour resolution
      is processed correctly.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>6)</label>
      <p>Any manipulation or alteration to the downloaded file before
      giving it as input to the app can lead to erroneous results.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="installation">
  <title>Installation</title>
  <p><monospace>pollucheck</monospace> is hosted online on
  <italic>shinyapps.io</italic> and can be installed to serve locally
  from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/">GitHub</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Load and run <monospace>pollucheck</monospace> as follows:</p>
  <code language="r script">install.packages(&quot;devtools&quot;)
devtools::install_github(&quot;adithirgis/pollucheck&quot;)
pollucheck::pollucheck_run()</code>
  <p><monospace>pollucheck</monospace> is furnished with a preloaded
  data set for a quick user tour of the analysis, plotting options, and
  the functions available. In the <monospace>Compare</monospace> tab,
  the preloaded data set acts as the second input file if no second file
  is uploaded.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="case-study">
  <title>Case Study</title>
  <p>For better understanding of the major functionalities of
  <monospace>pollucheck</monospace>, we present a case study based on 18
  months of pollution data set. This data is downloaded from the Central
  Pollution Control Board dashboard for the monitoring station located
  at Hebbal, Bengaluru, India at a time resolution of 60 minutes. Only
  plots related to PM<sub>2.5</sub> data generated through the app are
  shown here. Figure 1 depicts the efficiency of the app in detecting
  the outliers. The top panel of Figure 1 shows the hourly time series
  of the raw PM<sub>2.5</sub> (few outliers were synthetically added to
  the data), while the bottom panel depicts the quality checked data.
  Almost all the sporadically high values were detected by the app as
  outliers and removed.</p>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="inst/shiny/WWW/figure1a.JPG" />
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Hourly time series of raw (top panel) and cleaned
    (bottom panel) PM<sub>2.5</sub>.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="inst/shiny/WWW/figure1b.JPG" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>Figure 2 depicts the difference between <bold>Month and year box
  plot</bold> and <bold>Monthly box plot</bold>. These plots are highly
  useful if the dataset length is more than a year. <bold>Monthly box
  plot</bold> (bottom panel) partitions all the data points into the
  calendar month bins irrespective of the year. While <bold>Month and
  year box plot</bold> (top panel) accounts for the entire timeline,
  i.e., including the year.</p>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="inst/shiny/WWW/figure2a.JPG" />
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Box plots depicting the monthly variations in hourly
    PM<sub>2.5</sub>.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="inst/shiny/WWW/figure2b.JPG" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>Diurnal variation in PM<sub>2.5</sub> based on mean (and standard
  deviation) and median (and interquartile range) are shown in the top
  and bottom panels of Figure 3, respectively. The choice between mean
  and median is useful when the distribution of the data deviates from
  normal. In the top panel, the line depicts the mean and the vertical
  bars depict standard deviation. In the bottom panel, the line depicts
  the median and the vertical bars depict the interquartile range.</p>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="inst/shiny/WWW/figure3a.JPG" />
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Diurnal variations in PM<sub>2.5</sub>.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="inst/shiny/WWW/figure3b.JPG" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>In Figure 4, a linear regression is shown between PM<sub>2.5</sub>
  and the PM<sub>2.5</sub>/PM<sub>10</sub> ratio. The app computes the
  ratio using the individual PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> data
  sets. The blue line depicts the least square linear fit. The R-square
  and the equation of the linear fit are also provided on the panel.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Linear regression analysis.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="inst/shiny/WWW/figure4.JPG" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>The periodicity in PM<sub>2.5</sub> is shown as a wavelet
  periodogram (Figure 5). Wavelet analysis is useful in analysing
  non-stationary time series data. Only daily averaged data will be used
  for this analysis and missing data is imputed to perform the wavelet
  analysis.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>PM<sub>2.5</sub> periodicity analysis based on wavelet
    transform.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="inst/shiny/WWW/figure5.JPG" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We wish to thank Prof. Julian D. Marshall (University of
  Washington, Seattle), Prof. Joshua Apte (University of California,
  Berkeley), Dr. Jai Asundi (Center for Study of Science, Technology and
  Policy, Bengaluru), Dr Saumya Singh (University of California,
  Berkeley), and the R community for their help and support.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-HystadU003A2020">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hystad</surname><given-names>Perry</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>Salim</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Air pollution health impacts: the knowns and unknowns for reliable global burden calculations</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cvr/cvaa092</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-HyndmanU003A2008">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hyndman</surname><given-names>Rob J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Khandakar</surname><given-names>Yeasmin</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Automatic time series forecasting: the forecast package for R</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Statistical Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <uri>https://www.jstatsoft.org/article/view/v027i03</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v027.i03</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ShinyU003A2021">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Winston</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Joe</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Allaire</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sievert</surname><given-names>Carson</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schloerke</surname><given-names>Barret</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Yihui</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>Jeff</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dipert</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>shiny: Web Application Framework for R</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <uri>https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-CarslawU003A2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Carslaw</surname><given-names>David C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ropkins</surname><given-names>Karl</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>openair — An R package for air quality data analysis</article-title>
        <source>Environmental Modelling &amp; Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>27–28</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <issn>1364-8152</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envsoft.2011.09.008</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SalmonU003A2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>Maëlle</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vakacherla</surname><given-names>Sreekanth</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Milà</surname><given-names>Carles</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tonne</surname><given-names>Cathryn</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>rtimicropem: an R package supporting the analysis of RTI MicroPEM output files</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>16</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00333</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-UpadhyaU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Upadhya</surname><given-names>Adithi R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>Pratyush</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vakacherla</surname><given-names>Sreekanth</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kushwaha</surname><given-names>Meenakshi</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>mmaqshiny v1.0: R-Shiny package to explore Air-Quality Mobile-Monitoring data</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>50</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02250</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SpandanaU003A2021">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Spandana</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S Srinivasa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Upadhya</surname><given-names>Adithi R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>Padmavati</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sreekanth</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PM2.5/PM10 ratio characteristics over urban sites of India</article-title>
        <source>Advances in Space Research</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <volume>67</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.asr.2021.02.008</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ChanU003A2008">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Chak K</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Xiaohong</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Air pollution in mega cities in China</article-title>
        <source>Atmospheric environment</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
        <volume>42</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2007.09.003</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ChuU003A2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Hone-Jay</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Chuan-Yao</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Modeling the spatio-temporal heterogeneity in the PM10-PM2.5 relationship</article-title>
        <source>Atmospheric Environment</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>102</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2014.11.062</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
