<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2410</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02410</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Viime: Visualization and Integration of Metabolomics
Experiments</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Roni Choudhury</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Jon Beezley</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Brandon Davis</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Jared Tomeck</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Samuel Gratzl</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Lilian Golzarri-Arroyo</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Jun Wan</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-5"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Daniel Raftery</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-6"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Jeff Baumes</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Thomas M. O’Connell</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-7"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Kitware Inc.</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Indiana
University School of Public Health</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Medical and Molecular Genetics, Indiana
University School of Medicine</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-4">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Center for Computational Biology and Bioinformatics,
Indiana University School of Medicine</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-5">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of BioHealth Informatics, Indiana University
School of Informatics and Computing</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-6">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Anesthesiology and Pain Medicine, University
of Washington</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-7">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery, Indiana
University School of Medicine</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-03-11">
<day>11</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>54</issue>
<fpage>2410</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>metabolomics</kwd>
<kwd>visualization</kwd>
<kwd>web application</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Metabolomics involves the comprehensive measurement of metabolites
  from a biological system. The resulting metabolite profiles are
  influenced by genetics, lifestyle, biological stresses, disease, diet
  and the environment and therefore provides a more holistic biological
  readout of the pathological condition of the organism
  (<xref alt="Beger et al., 2016" rid="ref-begerU003A2016" ref-type="bibr">Beger
  et al., 2016</xref>;
  <xref alt="Wishart, 2016" rid="ref-wishartU003A2016" ref-type="bibr">Wishart,
  2016</xref>). The challenge for metabolomics is that no single
  analytical platform can provide a truly comprehensive coverage of the
  metabolome. The most commonly used platforms are based on
  mass-spectrometry (MS) and nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR).
  Investigators are increasingly using both methods to increase the
  metabolite coverage. The challenge for this type of multi-platform
  approach is that the data structure may be very different in these two
  platforms. For example, NMR data may be reported as a list of spectral
  features, e.g., bins or peaks with arbitrary intensity units or more
  directly with named metabolites reported in concentration units
  ranging from micromolar to millimolar. Some MS approaches can also
  provide data in the form of identified metabolite concentrations, but
  given the superior sensitivity of MS, the concentrations can be
  several orders of magnitude lower than for NMR. Other MS approaches
  yield data in the form of arbitrary response units where the dynamic
  range can be more than 6 orders of magnitude. Importantly, the
  variability and reproducibility of the data may differ across
  platforms. Given the diversity of data structures (i.e., magnitude and
  dynamic range) integrating the data from multiple platforms can be
  challenging. This often leads investigators to analyze the datasets
  separately, which prevents the observation of potentially interesting
  relationships and correlations between metabolites detected on
  different platforms. Viime (VIsualization and Integration of
  Metabolomics Experiments) is an open-source, web-based application
  designed to integrate metabolomics data from multiple platforms. The
  workflow of Viime for data integration and visualization is shown in
  Figure 1.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="user-interface-features-and-architecture">
  <title>User Interface Features and Architecture</title>
  <sec id="data-upload">
    <title>Data Upload</title>
    <p>Data upload can be a cumbersome step in many data analysis
    packages. Often the data must be provided in a specified format in
    order to be properly read and the details of the requisite format
    are not always clear. To facilitate the easy import of data, we have
    designed an interactive drag and drop data upload interface which
    currently accepts .xlsx and .csv files.</p>
    <p>The UI begins by presenting the user with an upload screen, which
    reports whether any errors were encountered in the file. The user
    then is able to correct any errors, designating any column as the
    primary ID, masked/hidden, a factor, the group, or a metabolite
    concentration column (see Figure 1). The table view and its
    associated server support have been designed to support tables that
    scale to hundreds of rows and thousands of columns, enabling support
    for a wide range of experimental data sizes.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>The data ingestion view.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure1.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
    <p>Any errors encountered during parsing are prompted for
    correction. Errors that are detected include levels of missing data
    that exceed a default threshold within a group or across all
    samples, non-numeric data in concentration data, the lack of a
    primary ID, and non-uniqueness of the primary ID. The UI guides the
    user through each error and warning until the data is ready for
    analysis. As seen in Figure 2, a low-variance metabolite is being
    flagged for possible omission from analysis.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>The ingestion error and warning panel.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure2.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
  </sec>
  <sec id="data-imputation">
    <title>Data Imputation</title>
    <p>Once errors are corrected, data imputation is automatically
    performed. For metabolites with missing values, the type of
    missingness is classified as missing completely at random (MCAR) or
    missing not at random (MNAR). For each type, an imputation mode is
    automatically performed but the options may be adjusted to apply
    different algorithms, including random forest, K neareset neighbors,
    mean, or median imputation modes for completely at random
    missingness (MCAR) and zero or half-minimum imputation for
    not-at-random missingness (MNAR).</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>Dynamically updating customizable plots which animate
      to show immediate feedback when adjusting pretreatment
      options.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure3.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
  </sec>
  <sec id="dataset-details">
    <title>Dataset Details</title>
    <p>Viime includes a dataset details page which includes size,
    creation time, and enables the user to update the name and
    description for each dataset (see Figure 4). It is also a central
    location for assigning colors and descriptions to groups, and
    keeping track of provenance for merged datasets.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>Dataset details page.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure4.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
    <p>A download page enables users to export their cleaned and
    processed dataset, or download the currently selected metabolite
    list.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="data-treatment">
    <title>Data Treatment</title>
    <p>The most critical step in the process of integrating multiple
    datasets is setting the optimal data treatment parameters for the
    individual datasets. The first step in this process is data
    normalization. In this step, the measurement values of each sample
    are made consistent with the other samples in the dataset. This can
    be accomplished by normalizing values of each sample to that of a
    reference sample. In this process, the sum of all metabolite values
    for the reference sample is determine and this value is then used to
    provide a normalization factor for the other samples based on their
    metabolite sums. Similarly, the sum of all values for each sample
    can be scaled to a set value. The default value in Viime is 100.
    Other options include normalization based on a column containing
    sample weights or volumes. The next step is data transformation.
    Often times, data is transformed to bring the distribution closer to
    normality and to compress the dynamic range. The options in this
    step are Log10, Log2, square root and cube root.</p>
    <p>The final step is scaling. This also addresses the issue of large
    dynamic range by scaling the variance of the data. The options here
    include autoscaling, Pareto scaling, range scaling, vast scaling and
    level scaling.</p>
    <p>A very important feature of the whole data treatment process is
    the interactive use of principal component analysis (PCA) to examine
    the similarity and dissimilarity of individual groups in the dataset
    for different data treatment options. Viime provides an interactive
    PCA score plot, showing how the selection of each treatment option
    affects the separation of the individual groups in the data. In this
    way, a user can quickly examine a number of different treatments to
    better understand their data. A loadings plot shows how each
    treatment option affects the contributions of the metabolites to the
    separations. Often data with no transformation or scaling may be
    dominated by only a few of the very high concentration metabolites.
    In those cases, some separation of the groups may be present, but
    are the result of looking at only those metabolites. Autoscaling is
    often a default selection in some metabolomics data analysis
    packages, but this runs the risk of increasing the noise in the
    data. This is characterized by a loadings plot where all of the
    metabolites display large loading values which is typically not a
    biologically plausible condition
    (<xref alt="Berg et al., 2006" rid="ref-vandenbergU003A2006" ref-type="bibr">Berg
    et al., 2006</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="data-analysis-and-visualization">
    <title>Data Analysis and Visualization</title>
    <p>Viime supports several downstream analyses and visualizations.
    Univariate analyses using the Wilcoxon rank sum test and
    multivariate ANOVA can be carried out on data with two or more
    groups, respectively. For the ANOVA, a post-hoc Tukey test is
    automatically applied so that p-values for each of the inter-group
    comparisons are calculated for all metabolites. Metabolites that are
    significantly different in each of the intergroup comparisons can be
    selected for further analysis with a check box at the top of each
    column. This enables very large datasets with potentially hundreds
    of metabolites to be easily reduced to datasets containing only
    significantly altered metabolites.</p>
    <sec id="volcano-plots">
      <title>Volcano plots</title>
      <p>To simultaneously visualize the magnitude of the change in a
      metabolite along with the statistical significance of that change,
      Viime offers an interactive volcano plot option. As shown in
      Figure 8, the horizontal axis displays the Log2 Fold change while
      the vertical axis displays the -log10 of the p-value. This type of
      plot is useful when making two-group comparisons; the specific
      group pairs can be selected from the Group Combination menu. The
      minimum fold change and p-values can be interactively adjusted to
      highlight larger or smaller metabolite changes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="heatmaps">
      <title>Heatmaps</title>
      <p>Heatmaps of the data can be generated to help visualize
      metabolites changes (Figure 6). The metabolite filter option on
      the Heatmaps page allows the option to include all metabolites in
      the heatmap versus only the significant metabolites. When the
      dataset is comprised of data from multiple platforms, the
      metabolite filter option also enables the selection of data from
      any of the separate platforms. The Sample Filter option allows
      only specific groups of samples to be included in the heatmap. The
      metabolite color option changes the color along with the vertical
      axis related to the metabolites. The options include coloring
      based on significance or based on data source. Hierarchical
      clustering analysis is carried out on both the samples and
      metabolites to help cluster the most similar sample and metabolite
      patterns. Both of these options can be toggled on or off if it
      would be beneficial to maintain the order of the samples and/or
      metabolites in the heatmap.</p>
      <fig>
        <caption><p>Heatmap with interactive collapsible clustering
        dendrograms for samples and metabolites.</p></caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure6.png" xlink:title="" />
      </fig>
      <fig>
        <caption><p>Boxplots of each metabolite, colored and separated
        by experimental group.</p></caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure5.png" xlink:title="" />
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="network-correlation-diagrams">
      <title>Network Correlation Diagrams</title>
      <p>An interactive spring-embedded metabolite network correlation
      diagram can be generated for the data. The plot contains nodes for
      all of the metabolites connected by edges when the correlation
      between metabolite pairs is sufficiently high. The Methods options
      enable the correlations to be based on Pearson, Kendall Tau or
      Spearman rank correlations. The Node Filter and Node Color options
      enables the nodes to be selected or colored based on the data
      source or significance. The advanced options enable all metabolite
      nodes or edges to be labeled. The minimum correlation used for
      visualization can be interactively adjusted. Using the left mouse
      button the map can be moved and using the wheel, the map can be
      expanded. To help clean up and interrogate the data, individual
      metabolites can be selected, moved and pinned in the map. This
      enables a cleaner visualization of selected metabolite groups.
      Hovering over nodes or edges brings up the metabolite
      identification information and the strength of the correlations
      respectively.</p>
      <p>Viime also includes a fully interactive heatmap with row and
      column dendrograms (see Figure 6). Selected metabolites are
      highlighted in orange on the left. Sample groups are colored along
      the bottom to provide additional context.</p>
      <p>Unique to Viime is a metabolite correlation network diagram
      (see Figure 7). The color in the diagram represents whether the
      metabolite was significantly different across groups (orange) or
      not (blue). Metabolites are linked if the correlation coefficient
      between them exceeds a configurable value. Negative correlations
      are in red, while positive correlations are in gray. The width of
      the link encodes the strength of the correlation.</p>
      <fig>
        <caption><p>Correlation network diagram.</p></caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure7.png" xlink:title="" />
      </fig>
      <p>Volcano plots (see Figure 8) were added to the software to
      highlight the metabolites that meet a specified threshold for fold
      change and significance (p-value). For datasets with only two
      groups, the data from the Wilcoxon analysis is plotted.
      Interactive threshold adjustments for both fold change and p-value
      enable a simplified view. For datasets with more than two groups,
      the data from an ANOVA analysis is used and has options to plot
      data from selected groups. Options include selecting the group
      combination to analyze, the minimum fold change to highlight, and
      the minimum p-value to highlight. The thresholds are live controls
      which provide immediate feedback showing which metabolites meet
      the criteria. Once the proper thresholds are set, the user may
      download the resulting plot image, and also can save and download
      the metabolites that fall into above the thresholds. When the
      significant metabolites are selected, the user may move to any
      other plot to see those same metabolites highlighted in a
      different context, such as the heatmap view or correlation
      network.</p>
      <fig>
        <caption><p>Volcano plot with interactive
        controls.</p></caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure8.png" xlink:title="" />
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="data-integration">
    <title>Data Integration</title>
    <p>Viime supports multiple approaches for combining multiple data
    sources into a joint analysis. From the data upload page, the user
    may initiate a dataset merge, selecting the datasets to merge along
    with the algorithm to perform the integration.</p>
    <p>Supported algorithms are simple column concatenation, PCA data
    fusion (concatenating the normalized scores of PCAs applied to each
    data set, keeping all variables and avoiding any loss of
    information, and leaving only common major effects
    (<xref alt="Spiteri et al., 2016" rid="ref-spiteriU003A2016" ref-type="bibr">Spiteri
    et al., 2016</xref>)), and multi-block PCA fusion (by normalizing
    each of the individual data sets so that their first principal
    component has the same length (as measured by the first singular
    value of each data table) and then combining these data tables to a
    grand table.
    (<xref alt="Abdi et al., 2013" rid="ref-abdiU003A2013" ref-type="bibr">Abdi
    et al., 2013</xref>)). After choosing an algorithm and two or more
    datasets, the interface indicates how many of the samples will match
    after the merging process. When the integration algorithm completes,
    the new integrated dataset appears in the list of data for the user
    to perform analyses (see Figure 9).</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>The interface for selecting the data and algorithm for
      integration.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figures/figure9.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="backend-processing">
  <title>Backend Processing</title>
  <p>Viime’s processing backend is implemented as a RESTful API using
  the Flask web framework. Data persistence is provided through
  normalized CSV files stored on a filesystem and associated data in a
  SQLite database through SQLAlchemy’s ORM. Files stored internally are
  linked with rows in the database using custom fields provided by File
  Depot
  (<xref alt="DEPOT, n.d." rid="ref-filedepotU003Aweb" ref-type="bibr"><italic>DEPOT</italic>,
  n.d.</xref>). The backend leverages Pandas for raw file parsing and
  normalization. Data processing is done by a combination of
  Scikit-learn for common statistical algorithms and R packages for
  specialized algorithms. The R-python integration is provided by a
  secondary REST service exposed internally via OpenCPU.</p>
  <p>Upon uploading a new dataset from an Excel or raw CSV file, the
  server begins by constructing a Pandas dataframe. Any parsing errors
  due to malformed files immediately result in an error response from
  the server. The Pandas object is used to populate a new row in the
  primary data table with associated metadata and processing defaults.
  Every row and column from the parsed dataset is also added to related
  tables including header information, detected data type, and an
  initial table structure determining properties such as which rows and
  columns contain metadata, group information, or raw metabolite
  values.</p>
  <p>The cleanup phase of the workflow allows users to override the
  initial table structure for example by marking specific columns as
  metadata or by “masking” rows so they are ignored in the processing
  steps. Each time the user makes a change to the table structure the
  dataset is processed by a validation function that determines whether
  the dataset is ready for processing. This validation checks many
  properties of the dataset including that all metabolite values are
  numeric and metabolite names are unique. In addition, the validation
  will warn the user of likely problems such as too many missing or “not
  a number” values within a metabolite or group or columns containing an
  excessively low variance.</p>
  <p>Once validated, the original dataset is broken down into three
  tables, one containing the raw metabolite measurements and two
  containing metadata about each row and column in the measurement
  table. The measurement table is then processed through imputation
  which fills in missing data using a series of user-configurable
  algorithms. A function defines which metabolites have missing data
  according to the Missing Not at Random (MNAR) or Missing Completely At
  Random (MCAR) models, depending on the percentage of missing values
  per group per metabolite. For each type of missingness the user can
  choose different imputation methods; MNAR allows users to impute using
  the Zero or Half Minimum strategies while MCAR allows imputation via
  Random Forest, K-Nearest Neighbor, Mean, or Median. Most of the
  imputation methods were implemented in R, while Random Forest and
  K-Nearest Neighbor were implemented with the R packages
  <monospace>missForest</monospace> and <monospace>impute</monospace>,
  respectively.</p>
  <p>Before statistical analysis is performed, the imputed dataset is
  passed through a series of optional, user-configurable preprocessing
  steps including normalization (min max, sum, reference Sample,
  weight/volume), transformation (log base 10, log base 2, square root,
  cube root), and scaling (autoscaling, Pareto Scaling, range scaling,
  vast scaling, level scaling). All preprocessing functions were
  programmed in R. After preprocessing, the dataset is ready for input
  into the analysis methods.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="related-work">
  <title>Related Work</title>
  <p>New analytical approaches to effectively measure more and more of
  the metabolome are continually being developed. The data produced from
  these different approaches requires different handling in order to
  transform the data into useful biological information. Recently,
  Spicer et al.
  (<xref alt="Spicer et al., 2017" rid="ref-spicerU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Spicer
  et al., 2017</xref>) reviewed the most popular freely-available
  software tools for metabolomics analysis. Based on their intended
  functionality the tools were classified into the following five
  groups: pre-processing, annotation, post-processing, statistical
  analysis, and workflows. Pre-processing and annotation tools are often
  very specific to the type, make, and model of the analytical
  instrument used to collect the data and therefore require specific
  tools. Once these steps are carried out, more general workflow tools
  can be used to complete the analysis. The intent of Viime package is
  to pick up the workflow after preprocessing and annotation and go all
  the way through statistical analysis and visualization. Note that
  annotation is not required and data can be analyzed that is
  unannotated or incompletely annotated.</p>
  <p>Spicer et al., briefly described seven popular metabolomics
  workflow packages that met a threshold of at least 50 citations on Web
  of Science (as of August 2016) or were reported in a recent survey of
  the Metabolomics Society. The packages MZmine
  (<xref alt="Pluskal et al., 2010" rid="ref-pluskalU003A2010" ref-type="bibr">Pluskal
  et al., 2010</xref>) and MAIT
  (<xref alt="Fernández-Albert et al., 2014" rid="ref-fernandezU003A2014" ref-type="bibr">Fernández-Albert
  et al., 2014</xref>) specifically focus on the analysis of
  mass-spectrometry data. The MAVEN package
  (<xref alt="Clasquin et al., 2012" rid="ref-clasquinU003A2012" ref-type="bibr">Clasquin
  et al., 2012</xref>;
  <xref alt="Melamud et al., 2010" rid="ref-melamudU003A2010" ref-type="bibr">Melamud
  et al., 2010</xref>) is focused on isotope tracer studies. The
  Workflow4Metabolomics
  (<xref alt="Giacomoni et al., 2014" rid="ref-giacomoniU003A2014" ref-type="bibr">Giacomoni
  et al., 2014</xref>) and Galaxy-M
  (<xref alt="Davidson et al., 2016" rid="ref-davidsonU003A2016" ref-type="bibr">Davidson
  et al., 2016</xref>) packages are built upon the Galaxy web-based
  platform and are composed of various modules and workflows. Among the
  most well-known metabolomics workflow tools are MetaboAnalyst
  (<xref alt="Chong &amp; Xia, 2020" rid="ref-chongU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Chong
  &amp; Xia, 2020</xref>) and XCMS Online
  (<xref alt="Tautenhahn et al., 2012" rid="ref-tautenhahnU003A2012" ref-type="bibr">Tautenhahn
  et al., 2012</xref>). These are both workflow tools which include MS
  spectral processing and have statistical analyses and visualization
  tools that are generally similar to Viime.</p>
  <p>An exhaustive feature comparison with these other platforms is
  beyond the scope of this paper, but a major distinguishing feature of
  Viime is its emphasis on ease of use and interactivity. Only XCMS and
  MetaboAnalyst are simple, readily accessible web applications that
  require no existing package (e.g., R), downloads or connection to the
  Galaxy platform. The unique user interactivity in Viime starts with
  the ability to simply drag and drop CSV or Excel files and
  interactively assign the sample identifiers, comparison groups,
  metadata, and metabolites. Dynamic visualization of the PCA scores and
  loadings plots with different types of data (e.g., NMR, LC-MS, and
  GC-MS) and data treatments (e.g., normalization, scaling and
  transformation) aids in selecting the optimal data treatment. Viime
  also enables integration between different data modalities, offering
  simple (i.e., concatenative), mid-level, and multi-block data fusion
  approaches. The resulting fused datasets offer expanded metabolome
  coverage, enabling an analysis of the correlated behavior of
  metabolites detected by different platforms.</p>
  <p>Viime offers another value-added feature during data ingestion:
  imputation of missing data. Viime uses a sophisticated imputation
  strategy
  (<xref alt="Armitage et al., 2015" rid="ref-armitageU003A2015" ref-type="bibr">Armitage
  et al., 2015</xref>), heuristically classifying missing data as
  Missing Not At Random (MNAR) or Missing Completely At Random (MCAR).
  For MNAR data, the user can choose to replace the values with either
  zeros or half of the minimum value of that variable, while the MCAR
  options include imputation by Random Forest, K-Nearest Neighbors, the
  mean value, or the median value.</p>
  <p>Finally, visualization of heatmaps, volcano plots, and network
  correlation diagrams, which all offer state-of-the-art web-based
  interactivity, can all be adjusted to include user selected subsets of
  data based on statistical significance or the particular interest of
  the investigator. This philosophy of interactivity will drive further
  development in viime as the platform expands its capabilities for
  further types of data analyses and visualization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgments">
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>
  <p>This project has been funded in whole or in part with Federal funds
  from the National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health,
  Department of Health and Human Services, under Contract
  No. HHSN261201800044C (UPIID 75N91018C00044).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-begerU003A2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Beger</surname><given-names>Richard D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>Warwick</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>Michael A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>Steven S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kirwan</surname><given-names>Jennifer A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cascante</surname><given-names>Marta</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>Lorraine</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>David S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oresic</surname><given-names>Matej</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hankemeier</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>al.</surname></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Metabolomics enables precision medicine: A white paper, community perspective</article-title>
        <source>Metabolomics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-016-1094-6</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-wishartU003A2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>David S.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Emerging applications of metabolomics in drug discovery and precision medicine</article-title>
        <source>Nature Reviews Drug Discovery</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-11">2016</year><month>11</month>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd.2016.32</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-filedepotU003Aweb">
      <element-citation>
        <article-title>DEPOT: File Storage Made Easy</article-title>
        <publisher-name>https://depot.readthedocs.io/en/latest/</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-vandenbergU003A2006">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>Robert A Van Den</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hoefsloot</surname><given-names>Huub Cj</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Westerhuis</surname><given-names>Johan A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smilde</surname><given-names>Age K</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Werf</surname><given-names>Mariët J Van Der</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Centering, scaling, and transformations: Improving the biological information content of metabolomics data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Genomics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2006-08">2006</year><month>08</month>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-7-142</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-spiteriU003A2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Spiteri</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dubin</surname><given-names>Elodie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>Jérôme</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Poirel</surname><given-names>Marion</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Corman</surname><given-names>Bruno</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jamin</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>Michèle</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rutledge</surname><given-names>Douglas</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Data fusion between high resolution 1H-NMR and mass spectrometry: A synergetic approach to honey botanical origin characterization</article-title>
        <source>Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>408</volume>
        <issue>16</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00216-016-9538-4</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-abdiU003A2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Abdi</surname><given-names>Hervé</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Lynne J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Valentin</surname><given-names>Domininique</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multiple factor analysis: Principal component analysis for multitable and multiblock data sets</article-title>
        <source>Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Computational Statistics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wics.1246</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-armitageU003A2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>Emily Grace</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Godzien</surname><given-names>Joanna</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Alonso-Herranz</surname><given-names>Vanesa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>López-Gonzálvez</surname><given-names>Ángeles</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Barbas</surname><given-names>Coral</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Missing value imputation strategies for metabolomics data</article-title>
        <source>ELECTROPHORESIS</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>36</volume>
        <issue>24</issue>
        <uri>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/elps.201500352</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/elps.201500352</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-spicerU003A2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Spicer</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Salek</surname><given-names>Reza M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>Pablo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cañueto</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Steinbeck</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Navigating freely-available software tools for metabolomics analysis</article-title>
        <source>Metabolomics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-017-1242-7</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-pluskalU003A2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Pluskal</surname><given-names>Tomáš</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Villar-Briones</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Orešič</surname><given-names>Matej</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MZmine 2: Modular framework for processing, visualizing, and analyzing mass spectrometry-based molecular profile data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-11-395</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-fernandezU003A2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Fernández-Albert</surname><given-names>Francesc</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Llorach</surname><given-names>Rafael</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Andrés-Lacueva</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>Alexandre</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An r package to analyse LC/MS metabolomic data: MAIT (metabolite automatic identification toolkit)</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <volume>30</volume>
        <issue>13</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu136</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-melamudU003A2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Melamud</surname><given-names>Eugene</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vastag</surname><given-names>Livia</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rabinowitz</surname><given-names>Joshua D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Metabolomic analysis and visualization engine for LC−MS data</article-title>
        <source>Analytical Chemistry</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>82</volume>
        <issue>23</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac1021166</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-clasquinU003A2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Clasquin</surname><given-names>Michelle F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Melamud</surname><given-names>Eugene</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rabinowitz</surname><given-names>Joshua D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>LC-MS data processing with MAVEN: A metabolomic analysis and visualization engine</article-title>
        <source>Current Protocols in Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471250953.bi1411s37</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-giacomoniU003A2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Giacomoni</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Corguille</surname><given-names>G. Le</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Monsoor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Landi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pericard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Petera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Duperier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tremblay-Franco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J.-F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>al.</surname></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Workflow4Metabolomics: A collaborative research infrastructure for computational metabolomics</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <issue>9</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu813</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-davidsonU003A2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>Robert L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>Ralf J. M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Haoyu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sharma-Oates</surname><given-names>Archana</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Viant</surname><given-names>Mark R.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Galaxy-m: A galaxy workflow for processing and analyzing direct infusion and liquid chromatography mass spectrometry-based metabolomics data</article-title>
        <source>GigaScience</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13742-016-0115-8</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-chongU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>Jasmine</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Jianguo</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Using MetaboAnalyst 4.0 for metabolomics data analysis, interpretation, and integration with other omics data</article-title>
        <source>Computational Methods and Data Analysis for Metabolomics Methods in Molecular Biology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-0716-0239-3_17</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-tautenhahnU003A2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Tautenhahn</surname><given-names>Ralf</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Patti</surname><given-names>Gary J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rinehart</surname><given-names>Duane</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Siuzdak</surname><given-names>Gary</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>XCMS online: A web-based platform to process untargeted metabolomic data</article-title>
        <source>Analytical Chemistry</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>84</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac300698c</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
