<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1007</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01007</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>idpflex: Analysis of Intrinsically Disordered Proteins by
Comparing Simulations to Small Angle Scattering
Experiments</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-0866-8158</contrib-id>
<string-name>Jose M. Borreguero</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-0265-0256</contrib-id>
<string-name>Fahima Islam</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-6985-6657</contrib-id>
<string-name>Utsab R. Shrestha</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-8569-060X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Loukas Petridis</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Neutron Scattering Division, Oak Ridge National Laboratory,
Oak Ridge TN, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Biosciences Division, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak
Ridge TN, USA.</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>32</issue>
<fpage>1007</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>sans</kwd>
<kwd>neutron scattering</kwd>
<kwd>saxs</kwd>
<kwd>intrinsically disoreded proteins</kwd>
<kwd>simulations</kwd>
<kwd>molecular dynamics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>It is estimated that about 30% of the eucariotic proteome consists
  of intrinsically disordered proteins (IDP’s), yet their presence in
  public structural databases is severely underrepresented. IDP’s adopt
  heterogeneous inter-converting conformations with similar
  probabilities, preventing resolution of structures with X-Ray
  diffraction techniques. An alternative technique with wide application
  on IDP systems is small angle scattering (SAS). SAS can measure
  average structural features of IDP’s when in vitro solution, or even
  at conditions mimicking protein concentrations found in the cell’s
  cytoplasm.</p>
  <p>Despite these advantages, the averaging nature of SAS measurements
  will prove unsatisfactory if one aims to differentiate among the
  different conformations that a particular IDP can adopt. Different
  distributions of conformations can yield the same average therefore it
  is not possible to retrace the true distribution if all that SAS
  provides is the average conformation.</p>
  <p>To address this shortcoming, atomistic molecular dynamics (MD)
  simulations of IDP systems combined with enhanced sampling methods
  such as the Hamiltonian replica exchange method are specially suitable
  (<xref alt="Affentranger, 2006" rid="ref-Affentranger06" ref-type="bibr">Affentranger,
  2006</xref>). These simulations can probe extensive regions of the
  IDP’s conformational space and have the potential to offer a
  full-featured description of the conformational landscape of IDP’s.
  The results of these simulations should not be taken at faith value,
  however. First, a proper comparison against available experimental SAS
  data is a must. This validation step is the requirement that prompted
  the development of <monospace>idpflex</monospace>.</p>
  <p>The python package <monospace>idpflex</monospace> clusters the 3D
  conformations resulting from an MD simulation into a hierarchical tree
  by means of structural similarity among pairs of conformations. The
  conformations produced by the simulation take the role of Leafs in the
  hierarchichal tree. Nodes in the tree take the role of IDP substates,
  with conformations under a particular Node making up one substate.
  Strictly speaking, <monospace>idfplex</monospace> does not require the
  IDP conformations to be produced by an MD simulation. Alternative
  conformation generators can be used, such as torsional sampling of the
  protein backbone
  (<xref alt="Curtis, 2012" rid="ref-Curtis12" ref-type="bibr">Curtis,
  2012</xref>). In contrast to other methods
  (<xref alt="Rozycki, 2011" rid="ref-Rozycki11" ref-type="bibr">Rozycki,
  2011</xref>), <monospace>idpflex</monospace> does not initially
  discard any conformation by labelling it as incompatible with the
  experimental data. This data is an average over all conformations, and
  using this average as the criterion by which to discard any specific
  conformation can lead to erroneous discarding decisions due to the
  reasons stated above.</p>
  <p>Default clustering is performed according to structural similarity
  between pairs of conformations, defined by the root mean square
  deviation algorithm
  (<xref alt="Kabsch, 1976" rid="ref-Kabsch76" ref-type="bibr">Kabsch,
  1976</xref>). Alternatively, <monospace>idpflex</monospace> can
  cluster conformations according to an Euclidean distance in an
  abstract space spanned by a set of structural properties, such as
  radius of gyration and end-to-end distance. Comparison to experimental
  SAS data is carried out first by calculating the SAS intensities
  (<xref alt="Svergun, 1995" rid="ref-Svergun95" ref-type="bibr">Svergun,
  1995</xref>) for each conformation produced by the MD simulation. This
  result in SAS intensities for each Leaf in the hierarchical tree.
  Intensities are then propagated up the hierarchical tree, yielding a
  SAS intensity for each Node. Because each Node takes the role of a
  conformational substate, we obtain SAS intensities for each substate.
  <monospace>idpflex</monospace> can compare the SAS intensity of each
  substate against the experimental SAS data. Also, it can average
  intensities from different substates and compare against experimental
  SAS data. The fitting functionality included in
  <monospace>idpflex</monospace> allows for selection of the set of
  substates that will yield maximal similarity between computed and
  experimental SAS intensities. Thus, arranging tens of thousands of
  conformations into (typically) less than ten substates provides the
  researcher with a manageable number of conformations from which to
  derive meaningful conclusions regarding the conformational variability
  of IDP’s.</p>
  <p><monospace>idpflex</monospace> also provides a set of convenience
  functions to compute structural features of IDP’s for each of the
  conformations produced by the MD simulation. These properties can then
  be propagated up the hierarchical tree much in the same way as SAS
  intensities are propagated. Thus, one can compute for each substate
  properties such as radius of gyration, end-to-end distance,
  asphericity, solvent exposed surface area, contact maps, and secondary
  structure content. All these structural properties require atomistic
  detail, thus <monospace>idpflex</monospace> is more apt for the study
  of IDP’s than for the study of quaternary protein arrangements, where
  clustering of coarse-grain simulations becomes a better option
  (<xref alt="Rozycki, 2011" rid="ref-Rozycki11" ref-type="bibr">Rozycki,
  2011</xref>). <monospace>idpflex</monospace> wraps other python
  packages (MDAnalysis
  (<xref alt="Michaud-Agrawal, 2011" rid="ref-Michaud11" ref-type="bibr">Michaud-Agrawal,
  2011</xref>),
  (<xref alt="Gowers, 2016" rid="ref-Gowers2016" ref-type="bibr">Gowers,
  2016</xref>), mdtraj
  (<xref alt="McGibbon, 2015" rid="ref-McGibbon15" ref-type="bibr">McGibbon,
  2015</xref>)) and third party applications (CRYSOL
  (<xref alt="Svergun, 1995" rid="ref-Svergun95" ref-type="bibr">Svergun,
  1995</xref>), DSSP
  (<xref alt="Kabsch, 1983" rid="ref-Kabsch83" ref-type="bibr">Kabsch,
  1983</xref>)) that actually carry out the calculation of said
  properties. Additional properties can be incorporated by inheriting
  from the base Property classes.</p>
  <p>To summarize, <monospace>idpflex</monospace> integrates MD
  simulations with SAS experiments in order to obtain a manageable
  representation of the rich conformational diversity of IDP’s, a
  pertinent problem in structural biology.</p>
  <p>The “notebooks” directory within the source contains two Jupyter
  notebooks that illustrate the use of idpflex when clustering an
  example MD trajectory.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="notice-of-copyright">
  <title>Notice of Copyright</title>
  <p>This manuscript has been authored by UT-Battelle, LLC under
  Contract No. DE-AC05-00OR22725 with the U.S. Department of Energy. The
  United States Government retains and the publisher, by accepting the
  article for publication, acknowledges that the United States
  Government retains a non-exclusive, paid-up, irrevocable, worldwide
  license to publish or reproduce the published form of this manuscript,
  or allow others to do so, for United States Government purposes. The
  Department of Energy will provide public access to these results of
  federally sponsored research in accordance with the DOE Public Access
  Plan (http://energy.gov/downloads/doe-public-access-plan).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This work is sponsored by the Laboratory Directed Research and
  Development Program of Oak Ridge National Laboratory, managed by
  UT-Battelle LLC, for DOE. Part of this research is supported by the
  U.S. Department of Energy, Office of Science, Office of Basic Energy
  Sciences, User Facilities under contract number DE-AC05-00OR22725.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Curtis12">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>Joseph E.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SASSIE: A program to study intrinsically disordered biological molecules and macromolecular ensembles using experimental scattering restraints</article-title>
        <source>Computer Physics Communications</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>183</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <issn>{0010-4655}</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpc.2011.09.010</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Svergun95">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>CRYSOL - A program to evaluate X-ray solution scattering of biological macromolecules from atomic coordinates</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Applied Crystallography</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
        <volume>28</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <issn>{0021-8898}</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0021889895007047</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Affentranger06">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Affentranger</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A novel Hamiltonian replica exchange MD protocol to enhance protein conformational space sampling</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <issn>{1549-9618}</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct050250b</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Rozycki11">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Rozycki</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SAXS Ensemble Refinement of ESCRT-III CHMP3 Conformational Transitions</article-title>
        <source>Structure</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>{0969-2126}</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2010.10.006</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Kabsch76">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Solution for best rotatation to relate 2 sets of vectors</article-title>
        <source>Acta Crystallograpica Section A</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1976">1976</year>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <issue>SEP1</issue>
        <issn>{0108-7673}</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0567739476001873</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Michaud11">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Michaud-Agrawal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MDAnalysis: A Toolkit for the Analysis of Molecular Dynamics Simulations</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Computational Chemistry</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21787</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Gowers2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gowers</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MDAnalysis: A Python package for the rapid analysis of molecular dynamics simulations</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of the 15th Python in Science Conference</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Kabsch83">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Dictionary of protein secondary structure: Pattern recognition of hydrogen-bonded and geometrical features</article-title>
        <source>Biopolymers</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1983">1983</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bip.360221211</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-McGibbon15">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>McGibbon</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MDTraj: A Modern Open Library for the Analysis of Molecular Dynamics Trajectories</article-title>
        <source>BIOPHYSICAL JOURNAL</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>109</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <issn>{0006-3495}</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2015.08.015</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
