<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">878</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00878</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Containershare: Open Source Registry to build, test,
deploy with CircleCI</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4387-3819</contrib-id>
<string-name>Vanessa Sochat</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Stanford University Research Computing</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-08-04">
<day>4</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>28</issue>
<fpage>878</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>containers</kwd>
<kwd>continuous integration</kwd>
<kwd>circleci</kwd>
<kwd>docker</kwd>
<kwd>api</kwd>
<kwd>reproducibility</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Containershare is an open source library of containers, both
  providing itself as a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.github.com/vsoch/containershare">template</ext-link>,
  a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://vsoch.github.io/containershare">library</ext-link>,
  and production
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://vsoch.github.io/containershare/library.json">application
  programming interface</ext-link> (API) for interested users.
  Specifically, it is a complete metadata registry that can be freely
  deployed directly from a Github repository to validate and serve
  tested, tagged, and version controlled containers, each maintained
  from independent Github repositories. The registry uses several open
  source and free to use solutions to accomplish this, and brings them
  together programatically with steps that are easy for the user to set
  up. Specifically, the user must connect the repository to the
  continuous integration service CircleCI
  (<xref alt="Continuous Integration and Deployment, n.d." rid="ref-noauthor_undated-nt" ref-type="bibr"><italic>Continuous
  Integration and Deployment</italic>, n.d.</xref>) and then turn on
  Github Pages
  (<xref alt="GitHub Pages, n.d." rid="ref-noauthor_undated-vt" ref-type="bibr"><italic>GitHub
  Pages</italic>, n.d.</xref>) from the repository web interface. After
  these steps, adding text files to describe other container
  repositories via pull requests will test the submissions, and
  programatically add them to all components of the library.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>https://vsoch.github.io/assets/images/posts/containershare/table.png</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://vsoch.github.io/assets/images/posts/containershare/table.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>While several frameworks exist with a primary goal to provide a
  listing of container builds (e.g., biocontainers
  (<xref alt="Veiga Leprevost et al., 2017" rid="ref-Da_Veiga_Leprevost2017-xx" ref-type="bibr">Veiga
  Leprevost et al., 2017</xref>)) containershare is unique in its
  requirement for each container to serve more substantial metadata. For
  example, while biocontainers also takes advantage of services like
  Docker Hub to provision a build, it doesn’t go out of its way to
  provide any more metadata than a standard image manifest. Each
  repository is required to serve a listing of tags, image inspections
  (files with sizes and package versions) and image manifests via Github
  pages, and also a LICENSE and README file from the master branch.
  Further, there is no additional software or server dependency on
  serving the API, because the entire operation happens via Github Pages
  and continuous integration. The manifests themselves and the container
  listings are served using a distributed strategy so that the primary
  containershare repository is not eventually overwhelmed with growing
  size, and a listing of tags are provided to discover container
  metadata for current and past builds, each associated with a Github
  commit. While biocontainers shines and succeeds to provide a listing
  of bioinformatics containers, it seems to require an additional
  registry backend and setup. In comparison, containershare is a more
  lightweight solution intended to empower other users to deploy similar
  initatives branded for their containers. Whereas the containershare
  Github repository works as an API, biocontainers does not appear to
  have any metadata served from the respository directly, container
  versions are not obviously linked to Github commits, and previous tags
  are not directly accessible. Further, containershare takes a
  distributed strategy of serving metadata from each included
  repository, allowing for individual containers to have unique and
  distinct tests, if wanted.</p>
  <sec id="container-repository-templates">
    <title>Container Repository Templates</title>
    <p>The individual container repository is responsible for serving
    its own metadata that the containershare can discover, validate, and
    provide for the user. It is also driven by a simple definition of a
    general CircleCI workflow, including building of a container,
    extraction of metadata, and then deployment of the container to
    Docker Hub and metadata files and user interface back to Github
    Pages. The workflow definitions to accomplish this are provided by
    containershare, and include:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>A table of version controlled containers, where each commit
        is associated with a tagged container for the user to interact
        with</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>https://vsoch.github.io/assets/images/posts/containershare/share.png</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://vsoch.github.io/assets/images/posts/containershare/share.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>A complete list of tags for a program to discover and
        consistently query for the associated container metadata</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>The traditional image manifests that are provided by Docker
        Hub</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>An “inspection” of the container that includes package
        manager packages and versions, along with a listing of files and
        sizes inside of the container, extracted during the build step
        using the open source Container Diff
        (<xref alt="Container-Diff, n.d." rid="ref-noauthor_undated-hl" ref-type="bibr"><italic>Container-Diff</italic>,
        n.d.</xref>) tool provided by Google Open Source.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>https://vsoch.github.io/assets/images/posts/containershare/inspect.png</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://vsoch.github.io/assets/images/posts/containershare/inspect.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
    <p>Containershare serves as a general skeleton that can be extended
    to several use cases and themes, including sharing of containers for
    behavioral paradigms, open source publications, or components to
    scientific workflows. The use of open source tools like Github and
    CircleCI means that the implementation is completely transparent and
    customizable for an individual or institutional needs. For a
    research scientist, submission of a container repository to a
    containershare gives confidence that the container can be
    discovered. For a service provider, deployment of a container share
    (and subsequent provision of containers using it) gives confidence
    that the service users have a central location to discover
    containers, and API to discover them programmatically.
    Containershare and links to container repository templates are
    provided for use from
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.github.com/vsoch/containershare">the
    containershare repository</ext-link>, contributions in the way of
    code or issues are encouraged, and for interested readers, a more
    descriptive writeup
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://vsoch.github.io/2018/build-deploy-docs/">is
    available</ext-link>.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Da_Veiga_Leprevost2017-xx">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Veiga Leprevost</surname><given-names>Felipe da</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grüning</surname><given-names>Björn A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Alves Aflitos</surname><given-names>Saulo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Röst</surname><given-names>Hannes L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Uszkoreit</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Barsnes</surname><given-names>Harald</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vaudel</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>Pablo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>Jonas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Mingze</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>Rafael C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sachsenberg</surname><given-names>Timo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pfeuffer</surname><given-names>Julianus</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vera Alvarez</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Griss</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nesvizhskii</surname><given-names>Alexey I</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Perez-Riverol</surname><given-names>Yasset</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BioContainers: An open-source and community-driven framework for software standardization</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-08">2017</year><month>08</month>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <issue>16</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-noauthor_undated-vt">
      <element-citation>
        <article-title>GitHub pages</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Github</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-noauthor_undated-hl">
      <element-citation>
        <article-title>Container-diff</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Github</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-noauthor_undated-nt">
      <element-citation>
        <article-title>Continuous integration and deployment</article-title>
        <publisher-name>https://circleci.com/dashboard</publisher-name>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
