<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">35</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00035</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>LAS: an integrated language analysis tool for multiple
languages</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-4692-3225</contrib-id>
<string-name>April M Wright</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Southeastern Louisiana University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-08-31">
<day>31</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>1</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>35</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>biology</kwd>
<kwd>paleobiology</kwd>
<kwd>phylogeny</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>treesiftr is a Shiny
  (<xref alt="Chang et al., 2018" rid="ref-shiny" ref-type="bibr">Chang
  et al., 2018</xref>)
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wrightaprilm.shinyapps.io/treesiftr_app/">application</ext-link>
  for visualizing the relationship between phylogenetic trees and the
  underlying data used to estimate them. It can also be used in RStudio
  (<xref alt="RStudio Team, 2015" rid="ref-RStudio" ref-type="bibr">RStudio
  Team, 2015</xref>) or at the command line as an R package
  (<xref alt="R Core Team, 2018" rid="ref-R" ref-type="bibr">R Core
  Team, 2018</xref>). treesiftr works by subsetting a phylogenetic
  matrix according to user-provided input about which characters to
  visualize. A maximum parsimony tree is then estimated from each data
  subset. Maximum parsimony was chosen for speed and analytical
  simplicity. Under the parsimony optimality criterion, the preferred
  tree is the one that suggests the fewest evolutionary steps, or
  character changes over evolutionary history. The tree is scored under
  both parsimony and Lewis’ Mk model
  (<xref alt="Lewis, 2001" rid="ref-Lewis2001" ref-type="bibr">Lewis,
  2001</xref>), a maximum likelihood model for estimating phylogeny from
  discrete character data. The data and tree are then visualized using
  ggtree
  (<xref alt="Yu et al., 2017" rid="ref-ggtree" ref-type="bibr">Yu et
  al., 2017</xref>), based upon the ggplot2
  (<xref alt="Wickham, 2016" rid="ref-ggplot2" ref-type="bibr">Wickham,
  2016</xref>) package. Expected outputs are the same whether the
  learner is interacting via the GUI or the RStudio interface; however,
  the RStudio interface does have additional options not available in
  the GUI.</p>
  <p>The included Shiny
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wrightaprilm.shinyapps.io/treesiftr_app/">application</ext-link>
  renders the visual output of the subsetting and estimation process,
  and can be used to provide further input to the treesiftr functions,
  such as decorating the trees with scores under different optimality
  criteria. It can be run locally or used via the web without installing
  any R packages or having knowledge of R. The web instance can
  accommodate 150 concurrent users.</p>
  <p>Also included in the package are two worksheets and an instructor
  guide. The worksheet intended for use with the Shiny app, “treesiftr
  GUI”, introduces the application, the underlying data, and the
  application functions. It includes several questions, and a glossary.
  The worksheet for the RStudio interface, “treesiftr Advanced”, asks
  the same questions, but also emphasizes general R skills, such as
  subsetting data, and specific R skills, such as interacting with
  phylogenetic data. And instructor guide contains answers to the
  questions, as well as renderings of the outputs students should see.
  treesiftr is not intended to replace a lecture on phylogeny, but to
  supplement student understanding.</p>
  <p>Phylogenetic trees represent the evolutionary relationships between
  a set of taxa. These taxa can be species, higher-level biological
  groupings (e.g., genera or families), lower-level groupings (e.g.,
  populations or strains) or even individuals. Estimating phylogenetic
  trees is crucial in many areas of biology. Phylogenetic trees are
  built from homologous characters, characters which are similar in
  multiple taxa because they were inherited from the most recent common
  ancestor
  (<xref alt="Darwin, 1859" rid="ref-Darwin1859" ref-type="bibr">Darwin,
  1859</xref>). For morphological traits, homology is assigned by
  experts by evaluating the character’s evolutionary history and
  ontology. In molecular characters, it is typically assigned via
  multiple sequence alignment
  (<xref alt="Feng &amp; Doolittle, 1987" rid="ref-feng" ref-type="bibr">Feng
  &amp; Doolittle, 1987</xref>).</p>
  <p>Once homology is assigned, a phylogeny is estimated from the data.
  Several optimality criteria may be used to do this. They broadly fall
  into parametric methods, such as maximum likelihood
  (<xref alt="J. Felsenstein, 1973" rid="ref-Felsenstein1973" ref-type="bibr">J.
  Felsenstein, 1973</xref>) and Bayesian methods
  (<xref alt="Huelsenbeck &amp; Ronquist, 2001" rid="ref-Huelsenbeck2001a" ref-type="bibr">Huelsenbeck
  &amp; Ronquist, 2001</xref>), and non-parametric methods, such as
  maximum parsimony
  (<xref alt="Farris et al., 1970" rid="ref-FarrisKluge" ref-type="bibr">Farris
  et al., 1970</xref>) and neighbor-joining
  (<xref alt="Gower &amp; Ross, 1969" rid="ref-gower1969" ref-type="bibr">Gower
  &amp; Ross, 1969</xref>). Parametric methods assume a model of
  underlying character evolution, while non-paramtric methods do not.
  Parametric methods have been shown in many instances to be more
  accurate
  (<xref alt="Joseph Felsenstein, 1978" rid="ref-Felsenstein1978" ref-type="bibr">Joseph
  Felsenstein, 1978</xref>) and, as they enable a rigorous framework of
  model testing, should be preferred over non-parametric methods.
  However, they are also compute-intensive, and so treesiftr makes use
  of the maximum parsimony criterion for analytical simplicity. Under
  maximum parsimony, the tree that is favored for a set of taxa is the
  one which implies the fewest evolutionary changes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of Need</title>
  <p>Understanding phylogenetic trees is challenging for students Meisel
  (<xref alt="2010" rid="ref-Meisel2010" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).
  Some of this challenge comes from inherently misunderstanding
  evolution in pre-Darwinian terms, such as a Platonic ‘great chain of
  being’ or as being ladder-like Sandvik
  (<xref alt="2008" rid="ref-sandvik2008" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).
  This is often inherently coupled to the idea of humans being the
  pinnacle of evolution
  (<xref alt="O’Hara, 1997" rid="ref-ohara1997" ref-type="bibr">O’Hara,
  1997</xref>). treesfitr, therefore, by default uses a non-human
  dataset to decouple tree-thinking from preconceived notions of
  organismal hierarchy. Students also have difficulty simply reading
  phylogenetic trees - often reading along the tips of a tree, as
  opposed to looking at the internal nodes Meisel
  (<xref alt="2010" rid="ref-Meisel2010" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).
  To counter this misconception, treesiftr continuously estimates new
  phylogenies, moving both tips and nodes. This causes students to have
  to continually re-evaluate the tree and the information on it
  (<xref alt="Eli Meir, 2007" rid="ref-meir2007" ref-type="bibr">Eli
  Meir, 2007</xref>).</p>
  <p>There are many phylogenetic tree viewers on the market such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/">FigTree</ext-link>,
  IcyTree
  (<xref alt="Vaughan, 2017" rid="ref-icytree" ref-type="bibr">Vaughan,
  2017</xref>), and Phylogeny.IO
  (<xref alt="Jovanovic &amp; Mikheyev, 2016" rid="ref-phylogenyio" ref-type="bibr">Jovanovic
  &amp; Mikheyev, 2016</xref>). But visualizing the data that underlie a
  particular tree is still largely accomplished via the Mesquite
  software
  (<xref alt="Maddison &amp;., 2008" rid="ref-Maddison2008" ref-type="bibr">Maddison
  &amp;., 2008</xref>). To use Mesquite, one must perform local
  installs. The software must also be interacted with via a GUI, without
  the opportunity for learners to practice programmatic skills while
  learning about phylogenetic trees and data. I wrote this package to
  allow students to learn about phylogenetic trees and data without
  performing local installs, and to give the option for students to
  practice programmatic skills while doing so.</p>
  <p>treesiftr was initially written for use in the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.analytical.palaeobiology.de/">Analytical
  Paleobiology Workshop</ext-link> in summer 2018. This course is an
  intensive 30-day paleobiological workshop predominantly for graduate
  students. treesiftr was used in the last week of the course, by which
  time the learners had been working with R via the RStudio application
  for three weeks. In this setting, the exercise itself took about 45
  minutes, and was embedded in a 3-hour lecture block (see below). I
  also added a web-based GUI for portability, and use in undergraduate
  biology classrooms. In undergraduate biology classrooms, learners are
  largely naive with respect to scientific computing, and performing
  installations on school or personal computers for a single class
  period may not be feasible. In particular, I am faculty at
  Southeastern Louisiana University, which is an institution serving
  students in a low-income region of a low-income state. Many students
  do not have reasonable computers to perform local installs of
  software. For demonstrating phylogeny and evolutionary history in my
  genetics class, a web-based viewer and activity set is, therefore,
  preferable. The discussion of phylogeny is one hour and fifteen minute
  class period, with the hands-on activity taking about 30 minutes,
  preceded by lecture on the basics of tree thinking
  (<xref alt="Baum et al., 2005" rid="ref-Baum979" ref-type="bibr">Baum
  et al., 2005</xref>) and tree reading.</p>
  <p>The included worksheets and package are not intended to be a
  replacement for a lecture. They are instead intended to be a hands-on
  supplement for the lecturer to use in class. By allowing the student
  to choose subsets of data, and have a tree of those data appear
  instantly, the relationship between the data and the estimated tree is
  enforced visually. Each worksheet does come with a glossary of terms
  that are required to describe phylogenetic trees, and it is the
  responsibility of the instructor to help students learn these terms
  before they start the activity. There is one example slideshow
  included in the <monospace>inst/slides</monospace> directory. These
  slides are written in RMarkdown, with executable R code segments that
  illustrate skills such as interacting with phylogenetic trees in R,
  and terminology to describe phylogenies. An overview of different
  methodologies in phylogeny estimation is also provided. This is an
  example of a lecture that could be used to explain the terminology
  presented in the worksheets. It is not necessary to use these
  particular slides for the activity to function.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Baum979">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>David A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Stacey DeWitt</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>Samuel S. S.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The tree-thinking challenge</article-title>
        <source>Science</source>
        <publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
        <volume>310</volume>
        <issue>5750</issue>
        <issn>0036-8075</issn>
        <uri>http://science.sciencemag.org/content/310/5750/979</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1117727</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Darwin1859">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Darwin</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>On the origin of species by means of natural selection, or the preservation of favoured races in the struggle for life</source>
        <publisher-name>Murray</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1859">1859</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Felsenstein1978">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The number of evolutionary trees</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Zoology</source>
        <publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis, Ltd. for the Society of Systematic Biologists</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1978">1978</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>00397989</issn>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Felsenstein1973">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Maximum Likelihood and Minimum-Steps Methods for Estimating Evolutionary Trees from Data on Discrete Characters</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Zoology</source>
        <publisher-name>JSTOR</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1973">1973</year>
        <volume>22</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-feng">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Da-Fei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>Russell F</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Progressive sequence alignment as a prerequisitetto correct phylogenetic trees</article-title>
        <source>Journal of molecular evolution</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1987">1987</year>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-FarrisKluge">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>James S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kluge</surname><given-names>Arnold G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Eckardt</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A numerical approach to phylogenetic systematics</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Biology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1970">1970</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2412452</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2412452</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ggplot2">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>Hadley</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>ggplot2: Elegant graphics for data analysis</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag New York</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <isbn>978-3-319-24277-4</isbn>
        <uri>http://ggplot2.org</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ggtree">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Guangchuang</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Huachen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>Tommy Tsan-Yuk</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ggtree: An r package for visualization and annotation of phylogenetic trees with their covariates and other associated data.</article-title>
        <source>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <uri>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.12628/abstract</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12628</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-gower1969">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gower</surname><given-names>John C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>Gavin JS</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Minimum spanning trees and single linkage cluster analysis</article-title>
        <source>Applied statistics</source>
        <publisher-name>JSTOR</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1969">1969</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Huelsenbeck2001a">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford Univ Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Lewis2001">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>Paul O.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A Likelihood Approach to Estimating Phylogeny from Discrete Morphological Character Data</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year>
        <volume>50</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/106351501753462876</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Maddison2008">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>W. P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>.</surname><given-names>D. R. Maddison.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mesquite: A modular system for evolutionary analysis. Version 2.5</article-title>
        <publisher-name>http://mesquiteproject.org</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
        <uri>http://mesquiteproject.org</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-R">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>R Core Team</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source>
        <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>https://www.R-project.org/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-RStudio">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>RStudio Team</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <source>RStudio: Integrated development environment for r</source>
        <publisher-name>RStudio, Inc.</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <uri>http://www.rstudio.com/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shiny">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Winston</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Joe</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Allaire</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Yihui</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Shiny: Web application framework for r</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-icytree">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>IcyTree: Rapid browser-based visualization for phlogenetic trees and networks</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btx155</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-phylogenyio">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Jovanovic</surname><given-names>Nikola</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mikheyev</surname><given-names>Alexander S</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Interactive web-based visualization of phylogenetic trees using phylogeny.IO</article-title>
        <source>PeerJ Preprints</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issn>2167-9843</issn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.7287/peerj.preprints.2579v1</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7287/peerj.preprints.2579v1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-rudolph1998">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>John L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evolution and the nature of science: On the historical discord and its implications for education</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Research in Science Teaching: The Official Journal of the National Association for Research in Science Teaching</source>
        <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-sandvik2008">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Sandvik</surname><given-names>Hanno</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Tree thinking cannot taken for granted: Challenges for teaching phylogenetics</article-title>
        <source>Theory in Biosciences</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
        <volume>127</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ohara1997">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>O’Hara</surname><given-names>Robert J</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Population thinking and tree thinking in systematics</article-title>
        <source>Zoologica scripta</source>
        <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Meisel2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Meisel</surname><given-names>Richard P.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Teaching tree-thinking to undergraduate biology students</article-title>
        <source>Evolution: Education and Outreach</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010-12-01">2010</year><month>12</month><day>01</day>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <issn>1936-6434</issn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12052-010-0254-9</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12052-010-0254-9</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-meir2007">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Eli Meir</surname><given-names>Jon C. Herron</given-names><suffix>Judy Perry</suffix></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>College students’ misconceptions about evolutionary trees</article-title>
        <source>The American Biology Teacher</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
        <volume>69</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1662/0002-7685(2007)69[71:CSMAET]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
