<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">58</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00058</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>SEP: Source Extractor as a library</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-2532-3696</contrib-id>
<string-name>Kyle Barbary</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2016-08-29">
<day>29</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>1</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>58</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>astronomy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Source Extractor
  (<xref alt="Emanuel Bertin, 2016" rid="ref-sextractor" ref-type="bibr">Emanuel
  Bertin, 2016</xref>;
  <xref alt="E. Bertin &amp; Arnouts, 1996" rid="ref-bertin96" ref-type="bibr">E.
  Bertin &amp; Arnouts, 1996</xref>) is a widely used command-line
  program for segmentation and analysis of astronomical images. It reads
  in FITS format files, performs a configurable series of tasks,
  including background estimation, source detection, deblending and a
  wide array of source measurements, and finally outputs a FITS format
  catalog file.</p>
  <p>While Source Extractor is highly useful, the fact that it can only
  be used as an executable – reading input files, producing output files
  and controlled by a limited set of configuration options specified in
  another file – can limit its applicability or lead to awkward
  workflows. There is often a desire to have programmatic access to
  perform one or more of the above tasks on in-memory images as part of
  a larger custom analysis.</p>
  <p>SEP makes available the core algorithms of Source Extractor in a
  library of stand-alone functions and classes. These operate directly
  on in-memory arrays (no FITS files or configuration files). The code
  is derived from the Source Extractor code base (written in C) and aims
  to produce results compatible with Source Extractor whenever possible.
  SEP consists of a C library with no dependencies outside the standard
  library, and a Python module that wraps the C library in a Pythonic
  API. The Python wrapper operates on NumPy arrays with NumPy as its
  only dependency. It is generated using Cython.</p>
  <p>From Source Extractor, SEP includes background estimation, image
  segmentation (including on-the-fly filtering and source deblending),
  aperture photometry in circular and elliptical apertures, and source
  measurements such as Kron radius, “windowed” position fitting, and
  half-light radius. Additionally, several features not in Source
  Extractor have been added:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Optimized matched filter for variable noise in source
      extraction.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Circular annulus and elliptical annulus aperture photometry
      functions.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Local background subtraction in shape consistent with aperture
      in aperture photometry functions.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Exact pixel overlap mode in all aperture photometry
      functions.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Masking of elliptical regions on images.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Finally, note that SEP is essentially a fork of Source Extractor
  that has already diverged significantly from the original code base.
  One might ask why SEP is not part of Source Extractor itself: the
  command-line interface in Source Extractor could be built on top of
  such a library. The answer is that a vast array of changes were
  necessary in order to expose the functionality as stand-alone C
  functions. It would be a lot of work to rewrite Source Extractor
  itself in this way, with little gain for the executable itself.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-bertin96">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Arnouts</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SExtractor: Software for source extraction.</article-title>
        <source></source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1996-06">1996</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>117</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/aas:1996164</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-sextractor">
      <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>Emanuel</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SExtractor</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2016-08-25">2016</year><month>08</month><day>25</day></date-in-citation>
        <uri>http://www.astromatic.net/software/sextractor</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
