<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">542</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00542</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>IDESolver: a general purpose integro-differential
equation solver</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-5968-9373</contrib-id>
<string-name>Joshua T Karpel</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Wisconsin - Madison</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-01-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>21</issue>
<fpage>542</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Integro-Differential Equations</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>IDESolver provides a general-purpose numerical integro-differential
  equation (IDE) solver based on an iterative algorithm devised by Gelmi
  and Jorquera
  (<xref alt="Gelmi &amp; Jorquera, 2014" rid="ref-Gelmi2014" ref-type="bibr">Gelmi
  &amp; Jorquera, 2014</xref>). IDEs appear in many contexts,
  particularly when trying to describe a system whose current behavior
  depends on its own history. A common example is in electronics, where
  the governing equation for a circuit made only of resistors,
  capacitors, and inductors can be written in a mixed form where both
  the derivative and integral of the current appear (for the inductors
  and capacitors respectively). More complicated examples may contain
  convolutions of the unknown function against some kernel function, or
  even be nonlinear in the unknown function.</p>
  <p>Simple IDEs can often by solved using integral transforms. For
  example, Laplace and Fourier transforms are often used to solve simple
  circuit problems analytically. Finding analytic solutions for more
  complicated IDEs is an area of active research and tends to require a
  special approach for each one. Even these techniques often produce
  non-closed forms for the result, which can be difficult to apply
  practically depending on their convergence properties. The details of
  these methods are often far more complicated than a researcher who
  just wants a numerical solution to their IDE will want to deal
  with.</p>
  <p>In 2014, Gelmi and Jorquera published a simple and robust algorithm
  for finding numeric solutions of generic integro-differential
  equations. IDESolver implements a modified and expanded version of
  this algorithm as a Python library. It handles both real-valued and
  complex-valued IDEs, allows for configuration of the error estimator,
  and provides control over the error tolerances of the internal parts
  of the algorithm through a convenient interface. The typical user
  should not need to think about the methodology of solving their IDE at
  all (but advanced users can provide alternate subroutines if
  desired).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-algorithm">
  <title>The Algorithm</title>
  <p>Gelmi and Jorquera’s algorithm is conceptually similar to iterative
  approximation methods in linear algebra
  (<xref alt="Axelsson, 1994" rid="ref-Axelsson1996" ref-type="bibr">Axelsson,
  1994</xref>), but repurposed for use with an IDE. At each step it
  produces a new guess of the solution by solving the IDE as if it was
  an ODE (ordinary differential equation), but using the previous guess
  to evaluate the new derivative. This means that there is never a need
  to solve the actual IDE, just a series of ODEs. Once the guess stops
  changing dramatically (according to some tolerance set by the user) or
  a maximum number of iterations is reached (again, set by the user) the
  algorithm terminates.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Gelmi2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gelmi</surname><given-names>Claudio A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jorquera</surname><given-names>Héctor</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>IDSOLVER: A general purpose solver for nth-order integro-differential equations</article-title>
        <source>Computer Physics Communications</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <volume>185</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>0010-4655</issn>
        <uri>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0010465513003093</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpc.2013.09.008</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Axelsson1996">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Axelsson</surname><given-names>Owe</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Iterative solution methods</source>
        <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1994">1994</year>
        <isbn>0521555698</isbn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/CBO9780511624100</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
