<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3094</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03094</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>WhaleMap: a tool to collate and display whale survey
results in near real-time</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3086-6759</contrib-id>
<string-name>Hansen Johnson</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Daniel Morrison</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Christopher Taggart</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Oceanography Department, Dalhousie University, 1355 Oxford
Street, Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada B3H 4R2</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-02-18">
<day>18</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>62</issue>
<fpage>3094</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>oceanography</kwd>
<kwd>marine mammals</kwd>
<kwd>conservation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of Need</title>
  <p>Baleen whales of the Northwest Atlantic live in a highly urbanized
  ocean. Their recovery from commercial whaling is impeded by
  anthropogenic risks from ocean industry, pollution, and climate
  change. Effective research, conservation and risk-reduction action
  requires near real-time knowledge of whale distribution measured using
  various methods including visual surveys from vessels or planes or
  acoustic surveys from autonomous platforms. The rapid collation and
  dissemination of whale detections and survey effort is critical but
  challenging given the number and variety of survey organizations and
  methodologies at work along the east coast of the US and Canada. There
  are long term databases for whale survey data, such as that maintained
  by the North Atlantic Right Whale Consortium
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://narwc.org">narwc.org</ext-link>),
  and crowd-source reporting tools (e.g.,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.whalealert.org/">Whale
  Alert</ext-link>) but <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> is the only
  dedicated system specifically designed to collate and display all
  available near real-time whale detections and survey effort. Use cases
  vary widely. For example, <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> is currently
  used by: government managers to design and implement risk-mitigation
  strategies, members of military or industry to plan safe operations,
  researchers to coordinate survey efforts and explore patterns in whale
  distribution, and members of the general public to learn about and
  follow along with whale conservation activities.</p>
  <p><monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> was designed with several specific
  goals:
  - Incorporate whale detection and survey effort from all survey
  methods in near real-time
  - Allow survey teams to easily contribute and retain complete control
  over their data
  - Provide the latest data in an accurate, user-friendly, and publicly
  accessible format
  - Operate transparently using open-source tools and with limited
  supervision</p>
  <p>Critically, <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> does <bold>not</bold>:
  - Perform any quality-control, or take responsibility for the veracity
  of information contributed
  - Provide a long-term database for survey results
  - Allow access to raw or processed data without approval from the data
  originator</p>
</sec>
<sec id="system">
  <title>System</title>
  <p>The <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> system workflow can be
  separated into data processing and visualization components (Figure
  1). The following provides a brief overview of each. Additional
  details as well as specific references to all software used is
  available in the source code documentation.</p>
  <sec id="data-processing">
    <title>Data processing</title>
    <p>Survey teams provide <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> access to a
    remote repository of their choice (e.g., Google Drive, Dropbox)
    where they upload their survey data. The
    <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> curator writes a custom script to
    extract the detection and effort data from each survey team and
    convert it to a common <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> format. This
    method eases the burden on the survey teams by allowing any team to
    submit data in nearly any format, provided the format is consistent
    and well-documented. This is essential for rapid data collection, as
    survey teams in the field typically lack the time and resources to
    reformat their data.</p>
    <p>A scheduled job regularly clones the data from the remote
    repositories onto the <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> server and
    uses a makefile to dynamically and efficiently process the data from
    each platform and coerce it into a common format. Formatting errors
    in a remote data repository are automatically flagged and the
    contributor is notified. This ensures that any changes to the raw
    survey data quickly propagate through the entire system, which
    allows survey teams to retain complete control of their data and
    perform quality control as needed. It also guarantees that the
    <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> always contains the latest available
    information.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="visualization">
    <title>Visualization</title>
    <p>Once the survey data are processed, they are visualized using two
    different methods. The first is the construction of self-contained
    HTML summary maps containing sufficient information to satisfy most
    casual viewers (typically the last 14-days of survey results). These
    can be conveniently embedded in various webpages (e.g.,
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://whalemap.org">whalemap.org</ext-link>)
    and browsed without requiring server-side processing. These maps are
    dynamically regenerated as the final step in the data processing
    workflow, so they always contain the latest available information.
    The second visualization method is an interactive online application
    (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://whalemap.org/WhaleMap/">whalemap.org/WhaleMap</ext-link>).
    This provides users with numerous tools with which to filter the
    latest processed data. The selected data are displayed in several
    formats including an interactive map, interactive timeseries plot,
    and table of summary statistics.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusions">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Since its launch in 2018, <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> has been
  constantly refined and optimized to better serve the overall goal of
  providing a common source for all near real-time whale survey data in
  the Northwest Atlantic. It has demonstrably improved conservation
  outcomes for endangered whales in this region by optimizing research
  activities, facilitating dynamic risk-mitigation measures, and
  engaging with the ocean industry and the public.
  <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> has also already been cited in several
  scientific publications
  (<xref alt="Baumgartner et al., 2020" rid="ref-baumgartnerU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Baumgartner
  et al., 2020</xref>;
  <xref alt="Gervaise et al., 2021" rid="ref-gervaiseU003A2021" ref-type="bibr">Gervaise
  et al., 2021</xref>;
  <xref alt="Johnson et al., 2020" rid="ref-johnsonU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Johnson
  et al., 2020</xref>;
  <xref alt="Koubrak et al., 2021" rid="ref-koubrakU003A2021" ref-type="bibr">Koubrak
  et al., 2021</xref>;
  <xref alt="Kowarski et al., 2020" rid="ref-kowarskiU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Kowarski
  et al., 2020</xref>). We are not aware of any equivalent software in
  existence. It is our hope that <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace>
  continues to serve the conservation community in perpetuity, and that
  this system can be readily adapted to benefit other regions facing
  similar conservation challenges.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Conceptual overview of WhaleMap data processing and
    display</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="figure_1.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We gratefully acknowledge the support of Pamela Emery, Stephanie
  Ratelle, Angelia Vanderlaan, Hilary Moors-Murphy and many other
  colleagues at Fisheries and Oceans Canada, as well as Tim Cole,
  Elizabeth Josephson, Leah Crowe, Christin Khan, Danielle Cholewiak and
  others at the NOAA Northeast Fisheries Science Center. This work would
  not have been possible without them. We also thank Mark Baumgartner,
  Kim Davies, and members of the Taggart lab for advice and helpful
  conversations. We are indebted to the fantastic community of open
  source developers that constructed many of the tools on which
  <monospace>WhaleMap</monospace> relies. These are referenced in detail
  in the system documentation. Finally, we give our most sincere thanks
  to the many survey teams and numerous agencies that continue to place
  their trust in this system and praise their tireless efforts to
  protect these vulnerable species. Supporting funds generously provided
  by Fisheries and Oceans Canada and the Natural Sciences and
  Engineering Research Council of Canada.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-kowarskiU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kowarski</surname><given-names>Katie A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gaudet</surname><given-names>Briand J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>Arthur J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Maxner</surname><given-names>Emily E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>Stephen P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S Bruce</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Hansen D</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Moloney</surname><given-names>John E</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Near real-time marine mammal monitoring from gliders: Practical challenges, system development, and management implications</article-title>
        <source>Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>148</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1121/10.0001811</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-johnsonU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Hansen D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>Mark F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Taggart</surname><given-names>Christopher T.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Estimating North Atlantic right whale (Eubalaena glacialis) location uncertainty following visual or acoustic detection to inform dynamic management</article-title>
        <source>Conservation Science and Practice</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>2</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/csp2.267</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-baumgartnerU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>Mark F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bonnell</surname><given-names>Julianne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Corkeron</surname><given-names>Peter J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Van Parijs</surname><given-names>Sofie M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hotchkin</surname><given-names>Cara</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>Ben A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bort Thornton</surname><given-names>Jacqueline</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mensi</surname><given-names>Bryan L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bruner</surname><given-names>Scott M.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Slocum Gliders Provide Accurate Near Real-Time Estimates of Baleen Whale Presence From Human-Reviewed Passive Acoustic Detection Information</article-title>
        <source>Frontiers in Marine Science</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issn>2296-7745</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmars.2020.00100</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-koubrakU003A2021">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Koubrak</surname><given-names>Olga</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>VanderZwaag</surname><given-names>David L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Worm</surname><given-names>Boris</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Saving the North Atlantic right whale in a changing ocean: Gauging scientific and law and policy responses</article-title>
        <source>Ocean &amp; Coastal Management</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <volume>200</volume>
        <issn>0964-5691</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2020.105109</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-gervaiseU003A2021">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gervaise</surname><given-names>Cédric</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>Yvan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Aulanier</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>Nathalie</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Optimizing passive acoustic systems for marine mammal detection and localization: Application to real-time monitoring north Atlantic right whales in Gulf of St. Lawrence</article-title>
        <source>Applied Acoustics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <volume>178</volume>
        <issn>0003-682X</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apacoust.2021.107949</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
