<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2769</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02769</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>ropenblas: Download, Compile and Link OpenBLAS Library
with R</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1591-8300</contrib-id>
<string-name>Pedro Rafael Diniz Marinho</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Statistics, Federal University of Paraíba,
João Pessoa, Paraíba - PB, Brazil</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-03-30">
<day>30</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>59</issue>
<fpage>2769</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Compiling R and OpenBLAS</kwd>
<kwd>Link OpenBLAS</kwd>
<kwd>Switch between versions of R</kwd>
<kwd>Fast algebraic computing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The <monospace>ropenblas</monospace> package provides improved
  performance on GNU/Linux systems and allows for passing additional
  compilation flags for more technical users. Through the
  <monospace>ropenblas()</monospace> and
  <monospace>rcompiler()</monospace> functions, the user will be able to
  compile and link the GNU/Linux distribution R language with the
  OpenBLAS library, all within R and in a very simple fashion. It works
  for all GNU/Linux distributions. Linking the OpenBLAS library to R
  brings better computational performance to the language in the most
  diverse algebraic operations commonly used in areas such as
  statistics, data science, and machine learning.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>Computational efficiency is important for those who program
  statistical methods since they often involve algebraic operations
  reproduced in computationally intensive simulations, such as
  Monte-Carlo simulations and resampling methods, as is the case with
  bootstrap resampling. Statistics is just one example within other
  areas that need good performance and use the R language.</p>
  <p>In addition to the adoption of good programming practices and the
  maximum, efficient and adequate use of available computational
  resources, such as code parallelization, through multicore parallelism
  procedures allowed by most current processors and operating systems,
  small adjustments and linkage of libraries can provide useful
  benefits.</p>
  <p>The <monospace>ropenblas</monospace> package aims to be easy to use
  for R (<xref alt="R Core Team, 2016" rid="ref-R" ref-type="bibr">R
  Core Team, 2016</xref>) programmers who work on GNU/Linux operating
  systems. For example, a user can link any version of the OpenBLAS
  (<xref alt="Xianyi, Zhang, Wang Qian, and Werner Saar, 2016" rid="ref-openblas" ref-type="bibr">Xianyi,
  Zhang, Wang Qian, and Werner Saar, 2016</xref>) library to the R
  language and install and link various versions of R to make them
  available on their operating system as well as switch between these
  versions.</p>
  <p>Linking the R language to the OpenBLAS library can bring several
  benefits to algebraic computing in R. OpenBLAS is an Open-Source
  implementation of the Basic Linear Algebra Subprograms - BLAS library
  that is often the first library option for algebraic computing to be
  linked in the installation of R on many GNU/Linux distributions. The
  OpenBLAS library is available at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/xianyi/OpenBLAS">https://github.com/xianyi/OpenBLAS</ext-link>
  and adds optimized implementations of linear algebra kernels that can
  run optimized on various processor architectures. OpenBLAS is based on
  the GotoBLAS2 project code in version 1.13
  (<xref alt="Goto, 2010" rid="ref-gotoblas2" ref-type="bibr">Goto,
  2010</xref>), code available under the terms of the BSD license.</p>
  <p>The <monospace>ropenblas</monospace> is a package designed to
  facilitate the linking of the library OpenBLAS with the language R.
  The package, which works only for Linux systems, will automatically
  download the latest source code from the OpenBLAS library and compile
  the code. The package will automatically bind the language R, through
  the <monospace>ropenblas()</monospace> function, to use the OpenBLAS
  library. Everything will be done automatically regardless of the Linux
  distribution you are using. Enumerating some advantages of the
  package:</p>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <p>Everything is done within the R language;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The procedure (use of functions) will be the same for any Linux
      distribution;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The OpenBLAS library will be compiled and you will choose which
      build version to bind to R, regardless of your Linux
      distribution;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The package allows you to install R
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\geq 3.1.0]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.1</mml:mn><mml:mn>.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
      also allowing you to install one more version, in addition to
      allowing you to easily switch between those versions;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The linked versions of R will continue to be recognized by
      their Integrated Development Environment - IDE and nothing will
      have to be adjusted in your GNU/Linux distribution after using any
      function of the package;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Unnecessary builds will be avoided. Therefore, if you need to
      switch between compiled versions of the R language, the use of
      binaries compiled compiled previously will be suggested;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>If any errors occur, the functions of the package will not
      damage the previous installation of the language;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>If something better can be done or if a newer version of what
      you want to install (R or OpenBLAS) exists, the functions will
      automatically suggest that you should consider installing newer
      versions.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>The <monospace>ropenblas</monospace> package is already available
  on the Comprehensive R Archive Network - CRAN, currently in version
  0.2.9, and the project is maintained on GitHub
  at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/prdm0/ropenblas">https://github.com/prdm0/ropenblas</ext-link> where
  contributors can find other details of the code, information, as well
  as being able to contribute with the development of the project. On
  the website, it is also possible to read the
  <monospace>NEWS.md</monospace> file with details of the versions and
  the focus of the current development. The site is deposited
  at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://prdm0.github.io/ropenblas/">https://prdm0.github.io/ropenblas/</ext-link>.
  Suggestions for improvements and bug reports can be sent via the
  link <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/prdm0/ropenblas/issues">https://github.com/prdm0/ropenblas/issues</ext-link>.
  You can find out how to contribute to the package by accessing the
  <monospace>CONTRIBUTING.md</monospace> file
  at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/prdm0/ropenblas/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.md">https://github.com/prdm0/ropenblas/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.md</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="brief-explanation">
  <title>Brief explanation</title>
  <p>The <monospace>ropenblas</monospace> library exports six functions
  for use which are the <monospace>rcompiler()</monospace>,
  <monospace>ropenblas()</monospace>,
  <monospace>last_version_r()</monospace>,
  <monospace>last_version_openblas()</monospace>,
  <monospace>link_again()</monospace> and
  <monospace>rnews()</monospace>. All of them are very simple to use and
  have few arguments that are sufficient to maintain the flexibility of
  use. Also, functions like <monospace>rcompiler()</monospace> and
  <monospace>ropenblas()</monospace> do not return content or data
  structures that are of any practical use. What these functions do is
  configure the GNU/Linux system to use R, configure different versions
  of the language, switch between versions, and link with the OpenBLAS
  library. It is also possible to obtain a summary of the versions of R
  and the OpenBLAS library that are available.</p>
  <p>Table 1 below presents the benefit of considering an optimized
  version of BLAS. Computational costs are presented in the calculation
  of the singular decomposition in a rectangular matrix
  (<monospace>svd()</monospace> function) and in the calculation of the
  inverse of that same matrix (<monospace>solve()</monospace> function).
  Some repetitions (100 repetitions) of each of the respective functions
  were performed. The benchmark can be better observed through the
  violin plots shown in Figure 2.</p>
  <table-wrap>
    <caption>
      <p>Comparison of the computational costs of the
      <monospace>svd()</monospace> and <monospace>solve()</monospace>
      functions (average of 100 repetitions).</p>
    </caption>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Functions</th>
          <th>Library</th>
          <th align="center">Time (seconds)</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td><monospace>svd(x)</monospace></td>
          <td>BLAS</td>
          <td align="center">6.520</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><monospace>svd(x)</monospace></td>
          <td>OpenBLAS</td>
          <td align="center">0.641</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><monospace>solve(x)</monospace></td>
          <td>BLAS</td>
          <td align="center">1.640</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><monospace>solve(x)</monospace></td>
          <td>OpenBLAS</td>
          <td align="center">0.640</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </table-wrap>
  <p>Through a benchmark it is possible to better understand the
  performance gain that can be achieved by linking the R language to the
  OpenBLAS library. Figure 2 presents the benchmarks in the form of a
  violin plot, in which 100 reproductions of the
  <monospace>svd(X)</monospace> expression were considered, in the form
  of the code above, with the R linked to the BLAS library and linked to
  the OpenBLAS library, respectively, on the same hardware. It was
  observed that the average time of execution of the routine
  <monospace>svd(X)</monospace> considering the OpenBLAS library was
  less than 10 times the time necessary to execute it in R linking to a
  non-optimized version of BLAS, being the average time of 0.64 and 6.52
  seconds, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="improvements">
  <title>Improvements</title>
  <p>The package will continue to evolve and code reviews will always be
  carried out. In addition, contributions to the development of the
  package are always welcome, especially those that aim to allow the
  <monospace>rcompiler()</monospace> and
  <monospace>ropenblas()</monospace> functions to work on Windows
  systems. There is also an interest that the
  <monospace>ropenblas</monospace> package will allow the linking of the
  Intel Math Kernel Library - MKL, just as it is done with the OpenBLAS
  library. All of these are improvements that we would like to see in
  future versions of the package.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-R">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>R Core Team</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source>
        <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <uri>https://www.R-project.org/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-gotoblas2">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>Kazushige</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GotoBLAS2 1.13 BSD version</article-title>
        <source>Texas Advanced Computing Center</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <uri>https://www.tacc.utexas.edu/research-development/tacc-software/gotoblas2</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-openblas">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Xianyi, Zhang, Wang Qian, and Werner Saar</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>OpenBLAS: An optimized BLASLibrary</article-title>
        <source>Texas Advanced Computing Center</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <uri>http://www.openblas.net/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
