<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1650</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01650</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>feign: a Python package to estimate geometric efficiency
in passive gamma spectroscopy measurements of nuclear
fuel</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2339-4340</contrib-id>
<string-name>Zsolt Elter</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-5708-9999</contrib-id>
<string-name>Aron Cserkaszky</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5133-6829</contrib-id>
<string-name>Sophie Grape</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Uppsala University, Division of Applied Nuclear
Physics</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Pazmany Peter Catholic University, Faculty of Information
Technology</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-08-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>42</issue>
<fpage>1650</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>nuclear safeguards</kwd>
<kwd>gamma spectroscopy</kwd>
<kwd>ray tracing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The operator declarations of spent nuclear fuel assemblies are
  routinely verified for nuclear safeguards purposes to ensure their
  non-diversion and integrity. Many countries consider the possibility
  of eventually placing the fuel in a geological repository and prior to
  this it is expected that the fuel assemblies need to be carefully
  characterized and verified, for instance using gamma spectroscopy
  measurements. It can be expected that in connection to such
  activities, verifying parameters such as burnup (the energy outtake
  from the nuclear fuel), cooling time (the time the fuel spent outside
  the reactor after operation), initial enrichment (the amount of
  fissile material in the fuel before operation) and integrity (whether
  pins inside the assembly have been manipulated) may become an
  important task of nuclear safeguards inspectors, since discrepancies
  may indicate unauthorized activities at the facilities. Ideally, the
  verification should be done with non-destructive assay systems.</p>
  <p>Passive gamma spectroscopy provides a robust and relatively simple
  method to analyze spent fuel since the characteristics of spent
  nuclear fuel strongly affect the gamma radiation emitted from the fuel
  (<xref alt="Jansson, 2002" rid="ref-Janssonthesis" ref-type="bibr">Jansson,
  2002</xref>). Lately, passive gamma tomography has also become a
  possible method to characterize and analyze properties of spent
  nuclear fuels
  (<xref alt="Mayorov et al., 2017" rid="ref-pget" ref-type="bibr">Mayorov
  et al., 2017</xref>). In both cases, gamma radiation is measured
  around the fuel assembly from a distance using one or more collimated
  detectors with spectroscopic capabilities. Of great interest is the
  detector efficiency of these systems, i.e., the ratio between number
  of detected particles and number of particles emitted by the source.
  The detector efficiency is the product of the geometric efficiency
  (probability that emitted particles reach the detector region) and the
  intrinsic efficiency of the detector (probability that the particles
  are detected).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>The detector efficiency is usually estimated with Monte Carlo
  simulations, typically using the MCNP particle transport code
  (<xref alt="Goorley et al., 2012" rid="ref-mcnp" ref-type="bibr">Goorley
  et al., 2012</xref>). Monte Carlo simulations of spent fuel passive
  gamma measurements are extremely time consuming even if variance
  reduction techniques are applied. This is because the source (the
  spent fuel assembly) is both highly radioactive and highly attenuating
  (made of high-density uranium dioxide), and the strong radiation field
  around the source often makes it difficult to place it near the
  detectors. In addition, it is not uncommon to use collimators with
  narrow slits around the detectors, something that makes the simulation
  of the detection process even more time consuming. Thus, only a tiny
  fraction of source particles reach the detector.</p>
  <p>The time requirements become daunting if the efficiency curves of a
  large number of assembly configurations are needed, for example when
  training machine learning algorithms for classification analysis of
  intact and manipulated fuel assemblies based on the measured gamma
  spectrum
  (<xref alt="Elter et al., 2018" rid="ref-elterMVA" ref-type="bibr">Elter
  et al., 2018</xref>). Furthermore, when prototyping with such
  algorithms, the accuracy of a Monte Carlo code may be unnecessary. One
  could argue that in collimated passive gamma spectroscopy setups only
  the uncollided gamma rays contribute significantly to the gamma peaks
  in the spectrum (if the background is removed), and if the distance
  between the detector and the source is much larger than the size of
  the detector, computing the uncollided point-detector response of the
  setup would be satisfactory to get an estimate of the detector
  geometric efficiency. Computing the uncollided point-detector flux
  does not require a transport code such as MCNP, and the task can be
  solved with a program that feigns to be a transport code such as the
  one presented here.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="feign">
  <title>feign</title>
  <p><monospace>feign</monospace> is a Python package that implements a
  2D point-kernel method to estimate the uncollided point-detector gamma
  flux around a rectangular spent fuel assembly. It is intended for
  nuclear safeguards specialists and nuclear engineers who want to get a
  quick estimate on the geometric efficiency in their passive gamma
  setup. The package relies on NumPy
  (<xref alt="Walt et al., 2011" rid="ref-numpy" ref-type="bibr">Walt et
  al., 2011</xref>) for data handling and Matplotlib
  (<xref alt="Hunter, 2007" rid="ref-matplotlib" ref-type="bibr">Hunter,
  2007</xref>) for plotting the geometry and the results. The user
  defines the experimental setup: materials, pin types (consisting of
  nested annular material regions), assembly lattice, detector locations
  and optionally collimators and additional absorber elements. The
  program iterates through each lattice position containing source
  material and calculates the distance traveled in various materials
  towards the detector point by a gamma-ray emitted from the given
  lattice position. Based on the user input, the actual source location
  is either the center of the pin or a randomly selected location inside
  the pin (the user also sets the number of randomly selected locations
  per pin, in order to estimate the standard deviation of the traveled
  distances).</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Example of distance traveled in uranium-dioxide and
    water for a 17x17 PWR assembly being measured at the Swedish Central
    Interim Storage Facility for Spent Nuclear Fuel (Clab). The detector
    point is facing the upper right corner and is 270 cm away from the
    center of the assembly. Each pixel represents the distance traveled
    in a certain material by a gamma ray emitted from that position to
    the
    detector.<styled-content id="figU003Adistance"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="article_distancetravelled.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>A traveled distance map can be seen in Fig.
  <xref alt="1" rid="figU003Adistance">1</xref> for a 17x17 pressurized
  water reactor (PWR) fuel assembly measured at the passive gamma
  spectroscopy station of the Swedish Central Interim Storage Facility
  for Spent Nuclear Fuel (Clab) as described by Vaccaro et al.
  (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-Vaccaro2016" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).
  The detector point is facing the upper right corner. Based on the
  traveled distance maps and user-provided mass attenuation coefficient
  data, the program evaluates the probabilities
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[P_i(E)]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  (or point-flux per source particle)</p>
  <p><disp-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[P_i(E) =\frac{1}{4\pi R_{i}^2}\prod\limits_m e^{-\mu_m(E) d_{i,m}}]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="block" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
  <p>that a gamma ray emitted from position
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[i]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  with energy <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[E]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  hits the detector without collision. <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[R_i]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  is the distance between the source position and the detector,
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[\mu_m]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  is the total attenuation coefficient of material
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[m]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  and <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[d_{i,m}]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  is the distance traveled by a gamma ray emitted from position
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[i]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  through material <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[m]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.
  A relative contribution map can be seen in Fig.
  <xref alt="2" rid="figU003Acontribution">2</xref> for the same 17x17
  assembly. When summing the contributions made by each pin for each
  energy, one gets the geometric efficiency curve of the system. Fig.
  <xref alt="3" rid="figU003Ageomeff">3</xref> illustrates one case when
  the source locations are the center of the pins and another case when
  ten source locations were randomly selected in each pin. One can see
  that the pin center approximation has a lower efficiency as compared
  to the case with randomly selected source locations inside the pin.
  This is due to the fact that assuming all emissions originate from the
  center of the pin overestimates the traveled distances (thus
  underestimating the geometric efficiency).</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Example of contributions made by a pin position to a
    detector facing the corner of a 17x17 PWR assembly at Clab. Each
    pixel represents the relative contribution that a gamma ray emitted
    from that position directly hits the
    detector.<styled-content id="figU003Acontribution"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="article_contribution.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>The program makes several approximations, which limit its areas of
  application. These approximations and the rationale behind them are
  the following:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>The program is limited to 2D geometries. For a long collimator
      with a narrow horizontal slit that is placed in front of the
      detector, the axial dependence is negligible.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The build-up factor is neglected. If the detector has a high
      energy-resolution, then it becomes a valid approximation to
      consider that for a given gamma peak only photons directly hitting
      the detector can contribute, and photons participating in
      scattering reactions will contribute only to the background, which
      ideally should be removed during the analysis of the spectrum.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>For typical spent fuel passive gamma spectroscopy setups,
  <monospace>feign</monospace> will produce a reliable estimate of the
  geometric efficiency curve. Even where its approximations are not
  valid, the package can be used as a fast way to estimate the
  uncollided point flux in order to aid setting up variance reduction
  methods in Monte Carlo calculations (e.g., importance values or weight
  windows).</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Example geometric efficiency curve calculated for a
    17x17 PWR assembly being measured at Clab. Errorbar represents three
    standard
    deviations.<styled-content id="figU003Ageomeff"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="article_geomeffave.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>The package was developed within a project funded by the Swedish
  Radiation Safety Authority (SSM), grant number SSM2015-4125. Special
  thanks to Lajos Nagy for the useful advices on the structure of the
  geometry module.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Janssonthesis">
      <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Studies of nuclear fuel by means of nuclear spectroscopic methods</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Uppsala University, Department of Nuclear; Particle Physics; Uppsala University, Department of Nuclear; Particle Physics; Acta Universitatis Upsaliensis</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
        <isbn>91-554-5315-5</isbn>
        <issn>1104-232X</issn>
        <uri>http://www.diva-portal.org/smash/record.jsf?pid=diva2%3A161704&amp;dswid=8533</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-mcnp">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Goorley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>James</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Durkee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Elson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fensin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hendricks</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kiedrowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Martz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mashnik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pelowitz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Prael</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sweezy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zukaitis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Initial MCNP6 release overview</article-title>
        <source>Nuclear Technology</source>
        <publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>180</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13182/NT11-135</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-pget">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mayorov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brutscher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Keubler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Honkamaa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peura</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dahlberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gamma emission tomography for the inspection of spent nuclear fuel</article-title>
        <source>2017 IEEE Nuclear Science Symposium and Medical Imaging Conference (NSS/MIC)</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-10">2017</year><month>10</month>
        <issn>2577-0829</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/NSSMIC.2017.8533017</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Vaccaro2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Vaccaro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Favalli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grogan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Liljenfeldt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mozin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schwalbach</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sjöland</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Trellue</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PWR and BWR spent fuel assembly gamma spectra measurements</article-title>
        <source>Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, Detectors and Associated Equipment</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>833</volume>
        <issn>0168-9002</issn>
        <uri>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0168900216307707</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nima.2016.07.032</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-elterMVA">
      <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Elter</surname><given-names>Zsolt</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Caldeira Balkeståhl</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grape</surname><given-names>Sophie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hellesen</surname><given-names>Carl</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Partial defect identification in PWR spent fuel using passive gamma spectroscopy</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of PHYSOR 2018, Cancun, Mexico</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-numpy">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Walt</surname><given-names>Stéfan van der</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Colbert</surname><given-names>S. Chris</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Varoquaux</surname><given-names>Gaël</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The NumPy array: A structure for efficient numerical computation</article-title>
        <source>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MCSE.2011.37</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-matplotlib">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>John D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Matplotlib: A 2D graphics environment</article-title>
        <source>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MCSE.2007.55</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
