<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2034</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02034</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>CapacityExpansion: A capacity expansion modeling
framework in Julia</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-1992-310X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Lucas Elias Kuepper</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4061-2226</contrib-id>
<string-name>Holger Teichgraeber</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-2528-1473</contrib-id>
<string-name>Adam R. Brandt</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Energy Resources Engineering, Stanford
University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-10-04">
<day>4</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>52</issue>
<fpage>2034</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>energy</kwd>
<kwd>optimization</kwd>
<kwd>storage</kwd>
<kwd>time series</kwd>
<kwd>teaching</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p><monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> is a Julia
  (<xref alt="Bezanson et al., 2017" rid="ref-BezansonU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Bezanson
  et al., 2017</xref>) implementation of a scale-independent capacity
  expansion modelling framework. It provides an extensible,
  multi-carrier, simple-to-use generation and transmission capacity
  expansion model that allows users to address a diverse set of research
  questions in the area of energy systems planning and can be used to
  plan and validate energy systems at scales ranging from districts to
  entire global regions. <monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace>
  provides simple integration of (clustered) time-series, geographical,
  cost, and technology input data. The software features a modular model
  setup and an investment and dispatch optimization that uses the JUMP
  modelling language
  (<xref alt="Dunning et al., 2017" rid="ref-DunningU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Dunning
  et al., 2017</xref>). The software further provides an interface
  between the optimization result and further analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="infrastructure-planning-in-the-energy-sector">
  <title>Infrastructure planning in the energy sector</title>
  <p>Energy systems convert different energy resources to meet desired
  demands like electric and thermal energy demands. Political, economic,
  and technological changes require expansions of the infrastructure of
  energy systems. Expanding the infrastructure has to balance multiple
  political, environmental, and economic objectives. Capacity expansion
  planning can be an essential tool during the planning process
  (<xref alt="Gacitua et al., 2018" rid="ref-GacituaU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">Gacitua
  et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
  <p>Capacity expansion planning is used to compute cost-optimal energy
  system designs under given sets of constraints from the perspective of
  a central planner. The resulting cost-optimal energy system design can
  be used to inform policy decisions that incentivize the industry to
  invest in this design
  (<xref alt="Johnston et al., 2013" rid="ref-JohnstonU003A2013" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  et al., 2013</xref>). Similarly, cost-optimal energy system designs
  can be used by companies for their investment strategies.</p>
  <p>Aspects of the energy system design that capacity expansion
  planning aims to answer are what the optimal technology mix is in
  regards to location, time, and installed generation, conversion,
  storage, and transmission capacities. The design optimization is done
  while using an integrated dispatch formulation to ensure that supply
  can equal demand at all nodes and time steps. The model determines the
  costs, emissions, power generation, energy storage, and power flows
  based on the installed capacities.</p>
  <p>Capacity expansion planning is formulated as a mathematical
  optimization problem. Like any optimization problem, capacity
  expansion planning has certain degrees of freedom, consisting of
  constraints and an objective function that is minimized: Typical
  degrees of freedom (also called decision variables) are installed
  capacities, power generation, energy storage, and power flows. Some
  constraints ensure that the model is physically consistent in itself
  and following the rules of thermodynamics, e.g. energy balances ensure
  energy conservation over time. Other constraints restrict the solution
  space to external conditions like costs, demands, available energy
  resources as well as other political, environmental, economic, or
  technological constraints. The objective function to determine
  cost-optimal investment can be the total system cost, the net present
  value, or another business-oriented cost measure.</p>
  <p>Dispatch planning formulations are very similar to capacity
  expansion formulations. However, the installed capacity is no degree
  of freedom but introduced as an external constraint.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="package-features">
  <title>Package features</title>
  <p>The model class of <monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> is
  capacity expansion planning, and it combines generation and
  transmission capacity expansion planning. The model is set up as a
  linear optimization model that models energy systems based on the
  provided input data. One can model multiple energy carriers, which
  makes the software suitable for research of sector coupling
  technologies. One can define technologies that belong to a
  dispatchable or non-dispatchable generation, conversion, storage,
  transmission, or demand. The decision variables of the model are
  investment and dispatch, and the total system costs are minimized.</p>
  <p>The following key features are provided by
  <monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace>. The software’s documentation
  explains the usage and mathematical formulation in detail.</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><italic>Modeling language</italic>: The implementation in Julia
      enables the usage of a high-level programming language and short
      times for data handling at the same time. The implementation in
      Julia also allows the usage of the mathematical optimization
      language JUMP, which enables the optimization formulation close to
      mathematical writing
      (<xref alt="Dunning et al., 2017" rid="ref-DunningU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Dunning
      et al., 2017</xref>). The integration into the Julia ecosystem
      further allows handling the process from data preparation to
      figure export within one programming language and software.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic>Provided input data</italic>: The input data for single
      and multi-node representations of electricity systems are provided
      for California (USA) and Germany (EU). The input data provides
      hourly time-series input data for multiple years, aggregated
      geographic information about existing generation and transmission,
      cost information including the monetary and life cycle assessment
      costs, and necessary technical data. This input data can be used
      to address many research questions.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic>The generalized import of input data</italic>: Modeling
      other energy systems is possible by adjusting the input data. The
      package extracts all information needed to model a specific energy
      system based on a few standardized input files. The time-series,
      geographic, and cost data can be edited as tables and integrated
      using the <monospace>.csv</monospace>-file format. The technology
      input data can be edited like a tree structure and integrated
      using the <monospace>.yml</monospace>-file format.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic>Integration of
      <monospace>TimeSeriesClustering</monospace></italic>: Time-series
      data like the demand, available solar factors, and available wind
      factors are used as an input to model the temporal variance of the
      energy system. Aggregating the time-series input data is commonly
      done to reduce the computational complexity of the optimization.
      <monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> is well integrated with
      the Julia package <monospace>TimeSeriesClustering</monospace>
      (<xref alt="Teichgraeber et al., 2019" rid="ref-TeichgraeberU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Teichgraeber
      et al., 2019</xref>). This integration allows using the typical
      time-series aggregation methods
      (<xref alt="Teichgraeber &amp; Brandt, 2019" rid="ref-TeichgraeberU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">Teichgraeber
      &amp; Brandt, 2019</xref>), integrated testing of the temporal
      resolution, and integrated feedback loops between the optimization
      result and time-series aggregation.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic>Seasonal storage</italic>: A recent seasonal storage
      formulation from Kotzur is implemented to allow time-series
      aggregation and modelling of seasonal storage at the same time
      (<xref alt="Kotzur et al., 2018" rid="ref-KotzurU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">Kotzur
      et al., 2018</xref>).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic>Modular model setup</italic>: The model setup is
      flexible and based on a modular setup. Depending on the
      configuration different technology groups can be activated or
      deactivated, a green or brownfield study performed, emissions
      limits can be enforced, different storage models can be used, and
      integrated investment and dispatch or pure dispatch optimization
      can be run.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="capacityexpansion-within-the-broader-ecosystem">
  <title><monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> within the broader
  ecosystem</title>
  <p><monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> is the first officially
  published package to provide capacity expansion planning in Julia.</p>
  <p>Multiple other software tools exist that support energy systems
  planning both in Julia and other programming languages. We provide an
  overview of the broader ecosystem for orientation.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/JuliaEnergy/Joulia.jl/"><monospace>Joulia</monospace></ext-link>
  package in Julia provides a modelling framework for electricity
  systems that optimizes dispatch
  (<xref alt="Weibezahn &amp; Kendziorski, 2019" rid="ref-WeibezahnU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Weibezahn
  &amp; Kendziorski, 2019</xref>). The generation, storage, and
  transmission capacities have to be provided as exogenous
  parameters.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/leonardgoeke/anyMOD.jl/"><monospace>anyMOD</monospace></ext-link>
  package in Julia provides a modelling framework for energy system
  models with a focus on multi-period capacity expansion. Each energy
  carrier can be modelled on separate geospatial and temporal sets.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/lanl-ansi/InfrastructureModels.jl"><monospace>InfrastructureModels</monospace></ext-link>
  package in Julia is a combination of multiple steady-state network
  optimization models to model electricity, gas, and water networks.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/calliope-project/calliope"><monospace>Calliope</monospace></ext-link>
  package in Python provides a framework to develop energy system models
  (<xref alt="Pfenninger &amp; Pickering, 2018" rid="ref-PfenningerU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">Pfenninger
  &amp; Pickering, 2018</xref>). An experimental back end for JUMP
  exists with the package
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/calliope-project/CalliopeJuMP.jl"><monospace>CalliopeJUMP</monospace></ext-link>.
  However, the <monospace>CalliopeJUMP</monospace> back end is called
  from within the <monospace>Calliope</monospace> framework in
  Python.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/tum-ens/urbs"><monospace>URBS</monospace></ext-link>
  package in Python provides a framework for capacity expansion planning
  that uses a single <monospace>.xlsx</monospace>-file including the
  input data in the form of tables and that contains information for the
  model configuration.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://switch-model.org/"><monospace>Switch</monospace></ext-link>
  package in Python provides a framework for capacity expansion planning
  of electricity systems. The switch framework allows modular
  optimization model setup and the integration of custom modules.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/PyPSA/PyPSA"><monospace>PyPSA</monospace></ext-link>
  package in Python provides a framework for capacity expansion planning
  and power flow modelling with a focus on the representation of the
  electricity network. The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/PyPSA/EnergyModels.jl"><monospace>EnergyModels</monospace></ext-link>
  package is an unpublished Julia implementation for capacity expansion
  planning of the PyPSA community with the focus on electricity network
  modelling.</p>
  <p>The model
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diw.de/dieter"><monospace>DIETER</monospace></ext-link>
  package provides a framework for capacity expansion planning using the
  proprietary GAMS software for optimization and
  <monospace>.xlsx</monospace>-files for data import and export.</p>
  <p>In combination <monospace>TimeSeriesClustering</monospace> and
  <monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> are the only packages written
  in Julia to intertwine aggregation methods of the input data and
  capacity expansion planning. E.g. time-series aggregation is gaining
  importance in designing future energy systems with high shares of
  non-dispatchable generation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="applications">
  <title>Applications</title>
  <p><monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> can be applied to plan and
  validate a variety of energy systems. The focus on time-series
  aggregation, storage modelling, and integration of multiple energy
  carriers make it especially valuable for the planning and validation
  of future energy systems with higher shares of non-dispatchable
  generation and sector coupling technologies. The scale of the modelled
  energy system can range from districts to entire global regions and is
  only restricted by the computational complexity of the model.</p>
  <p><monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> has been used in academic
  research. It was used to analyze and improve the impact of time series
  aggregation methods on low emission energy systems
  (<xref alt="Kuepper, 2019" rid="ref-KuepperU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Kuepper,
  2019</xref>).</p>
  <p>Furthermore, <monospace>CapacityExpansion</monospace> has been used
  as an educational tool. It is used for modelling exercises in the
  Stanford University course “Advanced Methods in Modeling for Climate
  and Energy Policy”. The teaching material is also provided open-source
  in the package.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-KotzurU003A2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kotzur</surname><given-names>Leander</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Markewitz</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Robinius</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stolten</surname><given-names>Detlef</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Time series aggregation for energy system design: Modeling seasonal storage</article-title>
        <source>Applied Energy</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>213</volume>
        <issue>October 2017</issue>
        <issn>03062619</issn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2018.01.023</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apenergy.2018.01.023</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-JohnstonU003A2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Josiah</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mileva</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>James H</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kammen</surname><given-names>Daniel M</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SWITCH-WECC: Data, assumptions, and model formulation</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <issue>October</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-TeichgraeberU003A2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Teichgraeber</surname><given-names>Holger</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kuepper</surname><given-names>Lucas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TimeSeriesClustering: An extensible framework in Julia</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>41</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01573</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-KuepperU003A2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kuepper</surname><given-names>Lucas Elias</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Investigation of time-series aggregation methods for infrastructure optimization of low emissions energy systems</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Stanford University, RWTH Aachen University</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Aachen</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-DunningU003A2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Dunning</surname><given-names>Iain</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Huchette</surname><given-names>Joey</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lubin</surname><given-names>Miles</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>JuMP: A modeling language for mathematical optimization</article-title>
        <source>SIAM Review</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/15M1020575</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-BezansonU003A2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Bezanson</surname><given-names>Jeff</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Karpinski</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Viral B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Julia: A Fresh Approach to Numerical Computing</article-title>
        <source>SIAM Review</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/141000671</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-WeibezahnU003A2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Weibezahn</surname><given-names>Jens</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kendziorski</surname><given-names>Mario</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Illustrating the benefits of openness: A large-scale spatial economic dispatch model using the julia language</article-title>
        <source>Energies</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>12</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <issn>1996-1073</issn>
        <uri>https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/6/1153</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en12061153</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-PfenningerU003A2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Pfenninger</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>Bryn</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Calliope: a multi-scale energy systems modelling framework</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <issue>29</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00825</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-GacituaU003A2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gacitua</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gallegos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Henriquez-Auba</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lorca</surname></name>
          <name><surname>Negrete-Pincetic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A comprehensive review on expansion planning: Models and tools for energy policy analysis</article-title>
        <source>Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>98</volume>
        <issue>October 2017</issue>
        <issn>18790690</issn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rser.2018.08.043</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2018.08.043</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-TeichgraeberU003A2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Teichgraeber</surname><given-names>Holger</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>Adam R.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Clustering methods to find representative periods for the optimization of energy systems: An initial framework and comparison</article-title>
        <source>Applied Energy</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <issn>03062619</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apenergy.2019.02.012</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
