<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2276</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02276</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>WDPM: the Wetland DEM Ponding Model</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0363-9929</contrib-id>
<string-name>Kevin Shook</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3513-6237</contrib-id>
<string-name>Raymond J. Spiteri</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4782-7457</contrib-id>
<string-name>John W. Pomeroy</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-2714-3103</contrib-id>
<string-name>Tonghe Liu</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1368-5670</contrib-id>
<string-name>Oluwaseun Sharomi</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Centre for Hydrology, University of
Saskatchewan</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Computer Science, University of
Saskatchewan</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-05-03">
<day>3</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>64</issue>
<fpage>2276</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>hydrology</kwd>
<kwd>Canadian Prairies</kwd>
<kwd>water distribution</kwd>
<kwd>connected fraction</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The hydrography of the Canadian Prairies and adjacent northern US
  Great Plains is unusual in that the landscape is flat and recently
  formed due to the effects of pleistocene glaciation and a semi-arid
  climate since holocene deglaciation. Therefore, there has not been
  sufficient energy, time, or runoff water to carve typical dendritic
  surface water drainage networks in many locations. In these regions,
  runoff is often detented and sometimes stored by the millions of
  depressions (known locally as “potholes” or “sloughs”) that cover the
  landscape.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of Need</title>
  <p>Conventional hydrological models are unable to simulate the spatial
  distribution of ponded water in prairie basins dominated by
  depressional storage. When the depressions are filled, the detented
  water may overflow to another depression, through a process known as
  “fill and spill”
  (<xref alt="Spence &amp; Woo, 2003" rid="ref-spenceHydrologySubarcticCanadian2003" ref-type="bibr">Spence
  &amp; Woo, 2003</xref>). Therefore, the fraction of a
  depression-dominated prairie basin that contributes flow to the outlet
  changes dynamically with the state of water storage within the basin.
  The WDPM simulates the spatial distribution of ponded water, as it is
  added, removed or drained, and can be used to calculate the changing
  connected/contributing fraction of a prairie basin.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="program-description">
  <title>Program Description</title>
  <p>The WDPM distributes simulated water over a digital elevation model
  (DEM), which is an array of land surface elevations. The program has
  three modules:
  - <bold>add</bold>, which adds specified depth of water to the DEM.
  Addition of water can be caused by rainfall, but in the Canadian
  Prairies, it is dominantly due to the melt of snow trapped in
  depressions and from runoff from adjacent areas
  (<xref alt="Hayashi et al., 1998" rid="ref-hayashiWaterSoluteTransfer1998" ref-type="bibr">Hayashi
  et al., 1998</xref>).
  - <bold>subtract</bold>, which subtracts a specified depth of water
  from the DEM. Subtraction of water may be caused by infiltration to
  the soils, but in the Canadian Prairies, it is dominantly due to
  evaporation
  (<xref alt="Hayashi et al., 1998" rid="ref-hayashiWaterSoluteTransfer1998" ref-type="bibr">Hayashi
  et al., 1998</xref>).
  - <bold>drain</bold>, which drains water from the lowest point in the
  DEM.</p>
  <p>WDPM does not attempt to compute the magnitudes of the additive or
  subtractive fluxes, which must be established by measurement or
  through the use of a physically based model of prairie hydrology such
  as the Cold Regions Hydrological Modelling platform (CRHM)
  (<xref alt="Pomeroy et al., 2007" rid="ref-pomeroyColdRegionsHydrological2007" ref-type="bibr">Pomeroy
  et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
  <p>The model output is the depth of water over each cell of the DEM.
  WDPM is not a hydraulic model; it is a model of the state of the
  distribution of water in a landscape after the fluxes have been
  redistributed. FLUXOS-OVERFLOW is a 2-D hydrodynamic model capable of
  modelling overland flow rates in the prairies
  (<xref alt="Costa et al., 2020" rid="ref-costaPredictingVariableContributing2020" ref-type="bibr">Costa
  et al., 2020</xref>), but it is much slower than WDPM, and it requires
  more parameters and more forcing data.</p>
  <p>The methodology of WDPM is similar to other simple water
  distribution models such as the Scalable Pothole terraIn anaLysis
  aLgorithm (SPILL)
  (<xref alt="Shaw et al., 2012" rid="ref-shawTopographicAnalysisPrairie2012" ref-type="bibr">Shaw
  et al., 2012</xref>), and FlowFill
  (<xref alt="Callaghan &amp; Wickert, 2019" rid="ref-callaghanComputingWaterFlow2019" ref-type="bibr">Callaghan
  &amp; Wickert, 2019</xref>) which also apply specified fluxes of water
  to DEMs. Apart from the differences in the algorithms used by these
  programs and that of WDPM (which is described below), the greatest
  difference between WDPM and these models is that WDPM is intended to
  model the state of water on a Prairie landscape, including its spatial
  distribution and the connected/contributing fraction of the basin.
  Thus WDPM is intended to be run using successive additions and
  removals of water. Although several models allow for landscapes to be
  filled with water, few simulate its removal.</p>
  <p>The WDPM also differs from simplified models such as the Pothole
  Cascade Model (PCM)
  (<xref alt="Shook et al., 2021" rid="ref-shookQuantifyingEffectsPrairie2021" ref-type="bibr">Shook
  et al., 2021</xref>,
  <xref alt="2013" rid="ref-shookStorageDynamicsSimulations2013" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>)
  which apply water fluxes to depressions that are modelled as discrete
  storage units. Although such models are very computationally
  efficient, and can reproduce the variable connected/contributing
  fractions of Prairie basins
  (<xref alt="Shook et al., 2013" rid="ref-shookStorageDynamicsSimulations2013" ref-type="bibr">Shook
  et al., 2013</xref>), very similarly to WDPM, they cannot simulate the
  aggregation and disaggregation of water areas, and cannot model the
  spatial distribution of water in a Prairie basin.</p>
  <p>The Prairie Region Inundation MApping (PRIMA) model is similar to
  WDPM in that it allows both additions and removals of water on Prairie
  landscape DEMs
  (<xref alt="Ahmed et al., 2020" rid="ref-ahmedNovelModelStorage2020" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed
  et al., 2020</xref>) through iterative movement of water. PRIMA has
  been shown to be more efficient than WDPM version 1.0, in that it
  moved more water per iteration, although WDPM had reduced
  computational cost per iteration
  (<xref alt="Ahmed et al., 2020" rid="ref-ahmedNovelModelStorage2020" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed
  et al., 2020</xref>). However, PRIMA does not yet use parallel
  processing, so its execution time cannot be compared to that of WDPM.
  Furthermore, PRIMA has not yet been compared to the newest version 2.0
  of WDPM, which is more efficient than version 1.0.</p>
  <p>All WDPM modules use the algorithm of Shapiro &amp; Westervelt
  (<xref alt="1992" rid="ref-shapiroMAPCALCAlgebraGIS1992" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>)
  to redistribute the simulated water. This algorithm is iterative. In
  each iteration, the excess water, which is the depth of water required
  to be removed to make the surface flat, is computed for each DEM cell.
  As shown in
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="figU003Awaterflow">Figure 1</xref>, water
  can be distributed to a lower cell or to a higher cell with
  insufficient water. In each iteration, up to one-eighth of available
  water can be distributed to any of the neighbouring cells. The
  algorithm is repeated until the water surface is flat, which is
  determined by the maximum difference between successive values of the
  matrix every 1000 iterations. When the maximum cell difference is
  within a specified tolerance or the volume of water draining in 1000
  iterations is smaller than a specified value, then the program
  terminates and the water depth is written to an ArcGIS .asc (ASCII)
  file.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Schematic diagram of water flow from a DEM cell using
    WDPM.<styled-content id="figU003Awaterflow"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="WaterFlowDiagram.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>The original version of WDPM was written by in Fortran
  (<xref alt="Shook &amp; Pomeroy, 2011" rid="ref-shookMemoryEffectsDepressional2011" ref-type="bibr">Shook
  &amp; Pomeroy, 2011</xref>) and parallelized using OpenMP. Because the
  program was so slow to run (taking hours or days to converge to a
  solution), the code was refactored. The program was converted to C,
  and an optional python GUI was added. Because the program is typically
  run by end-users on desktop computers, it was decided to use OpenCL to
  parallelise the code because this framework permits the use of CPUs
  and GPUs. Using OpenCL, the matrix was subdivided into 9 sets of
  cells, as shown in
  <xref alt="Figure 2" rid="figU003Aopencl">Figure 2</xref>, where each
  colour represents a separate subdivision each of which is acted upon
  by a separate set of threads. The matrix locations of each subdivision
  are separated by 3 rows and columns. Because transfers of water are
  only done from cells immediately adjacent to each cell of interest
  (i.e. at a distance of 1 cell), the points in each set are independent
  from each other, in that their water transfers do not affect those of
  the other cells in the set for a given iteration. Therefore the order
  of execution of the cells in each set does not matter, and race
  conditions are avoided. Note that water does transfer across the
  entire DEM, as is required by the algorithm, as each of the 9 sets of
  cells is solved.</p>
  <p>The refactoring of the WDPM was successful in greatly reducing
  execution time.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Schematic diagram of WDPM matrix subdivision for OpenCL.
    Each colour represents a separate set of
    threads.<styled-content id="figU003Aopencl"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="opencl4.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="examples">
  <title>Examples</title>
  <p>The WDPM is distributed with a sample DEM data set, which
  represents a small (~10 km<sup>2</sup>) sub-basin in southeastern
  Saskatchewan. The sub-basin (Smith Creek sub-basin 5) is described
  fully in Shook et al.
  (<xref alt="2013" rid="ref-shookStorageDynamicsSimulations2013" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).
  The sample DEM measures 471 x 483 elements with a horizontal
  resolution of 10 m and a vertical precision of less than 1 mm.</p>
  <p>In the first step, 300 mm of water was added, using the
  <bold>add</bold> module, distributed evenly over the basin. All of the
  water was allowed to run off the uplands, accumulating in the
  depressions. Prior to the addition of water, the basin was empty.
  <xref alt="Figure 3" rid="figU003Aadd">Figure 3</xref> shows the
  extent of water (depths greater than 1 mm) resulting from the WDPM
  simulation. The accumulation of water in the depressions is clearly
  visible. Because the edge of the DEM acts like a dam, water in the
  stream channel is unable to leave the basin, causing it to back up.
  This unrealistic behaviour was the reason for the development of the
  <bold>drain</bold> module.</p>
  <p>When the <bold>drain</bold> module was applied, the water in the
  stream channel was able to drain from the lowest point in basin,
  located at the basin outlet at the mouth of the stream. As shown in
  <xref alt="Figure 4" rid="figU003Adrain">Figure 4</xref>, the
  resulting distribution of water is a more realistic representation of
  the state of the basin after the cessation of runoff.</p>
  <p>Following the addition and draining of water, 200 mm of water was
  removed using the <bold>subtract</bold> module. As shown in
  <xref alt="Figure 5" rid="figU003Asubtract">Figure 5</xref>, the ponds
  are reduced in size, and many of the smaller ones have
  disappeared.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Plot of WDPM simulation of water (blue) and dry ground
    (yellow) for addition of 300 mm of water. The region outside the
    basin is shown in black. Smith Creek
    sub-basin 5.<styled-content id="figU003Aadd"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="300_0_0_0_u.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Plot of WDPM simulation of water (blue) and dry ground
    (yellow) for draining following the addition of 300 mm of water. The
    region outside the basin is shown in black. Smith Creek
    sub-basin 5.<styled-content id="figU003Adrain"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="300_0_0_0_d.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Plot of WDPM simulation of water (blue) and dry ground
    (yellow) for the removal of 200 mm of water following the addition
    of 300 mm of water and draining. The region outside the basin is
    shown in black. Smith Creek
    sub-basin 5.<styled-content id="figU003Asubtract"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="300_200_0_0_d.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>The WDPM is computationally expensive, requiring many thousands or
  millions of iterations to converge to a solution, depending on the DEM
  size, the depth of water used, and the tolerance(s) of the solution.
  In the examples above, the addition of 300 mm of water, smoothed to a
  resolution of 10 mm, required 179,000 iterations, taking 145.23 s on a
  system with an Intel i7 CPU (4 cores, 8 threads) running Linux Mint
  20. Draining the water to a tolerance of 0.1 mm/0.1 m<sup>3</sup>
  required 240,000 iterations and took 180.6 s on the same system.
  Removing the water and smoothing to a tolerance of 1 mm required 1,000
  iterations, which is the minimum possible because the program tests
  every 1000 iterations, taking 0.85 s on the same system.</p>
  <p>Despite the computational cost, the program’s great advantage is
  that it can simulate any storage state within a complex system of
  prairie depressions. This capability makes it useful for mapping the
  floodplains from non-riverine floods in the Canadian Prairies. The
  program outputs have been verified by remote sensing of recent floods
  in this region, and WDPM has been used to develop a simpler parametric
  model that is more easily incorporated in hydrological models
  (<xref alt="Shook et al., 2013" rid="ref-shookStorageDynamicsSimulations2013" ref-type="bibr">Shook
  et al., 2013</xref>). The program’s floodplain mapping capabilities
  have been used by researchers
  (<xref alt="Elboshy et al., 2019" rid="ref-elboshyFrameworkPluvialFlood2019" ref-type="bibr">Elboshy
  et al., 2019</xref>;
  <xref alt="Kiss, 2018" rid="ref-kissPredictiveMappingWetland2018" ref-type="bibr">Kiss,
  2018</xref>;
  <xref alt="Schellenberg, 2017" rid="ref-schellenbergHydrologyDeltaMarsh2017" ref-type="bibr">Schellenberg,
  2017</xref> ;
  <xref alt="Thapa et al., 2019" rid="ref-thapaGarbageGarbageOut2019" ref-type="bibr">Thapa
  et al., 2019</xref>), for operational flood hazard mapping in the
  Canadian Prairies by government agencies
  (<xref alt="Armstrong et al., 2013" rid="ref-armstrongUSINGWETLANDPONDING2013a" ref-type="bibr">Armstrong
  et al., 2013</xref>) and by private consultants
  (<xref alt="Venema, 2020a" rid="ref-venemahenrydavidClimateAdaptationUsing2020" ref-type="bibr">Venema,
  2020a</xref>,
  <xref alt="2020b" rid="ref-venemahenrydavidFloodRiskMapping2020" ref-type="bibr">2020b</xref>).
  As of July 2020, the program has been downloaded by at least 78
  different users from 11 countries.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="licence">
  <title>Licence</title>
  <p>The WDPM is licensed under the GNU GPL v3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowlegements">
  <title>Acknowlegements</title>
  <p>Funding was provided by the Canada First Research Excellence Fund’s
  Global Water Futures programme, Natural Sciences and Engineering
  Research Council of Canada’s Discovery Grants programme and by
  Agriculture and Agri-food Canada.</p>
  <p>We also wish to thank the reviewers whose suggestions have improved
  this paper and the program code.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-ahmedNovelModelStorage2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Mohamed Ismaiel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Elshorbagy</surname><given-names>Amin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pietroniro</surname><given-names>Alain</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A novel model for storage dynamics simulation and inundation mapping in the prairies</article-title>
        <source>Environmental Modelling &amp; Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-11">2020</year><month>11</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2021-04-04">2021</year><month>04</month><day>04</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>133</volume>
        <issn>1364-8152</issn>
        <uri>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364815220309075</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envsoft.2020.104850</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-armstrongUSINGWETLANDPONDING2013a">
      <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kayter</surname><given-names>Cameron</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shook</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Harvey</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>USING THE WETLAND DEM PONDING MODEL AS A DIAGNOSTIC TOOL FOR PRAIRIE FLOOD HAZARD ASSESSMENT</article-title>
        <source>Putting Prediction in Ungauged Basins into Practice</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-callaghanComputingWaterFlow2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Callaghan</surname><given-names>Kerry L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wickert</surname><given-names>Andrew D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Computing water flow through complex landscapes  Part 1: Incorporating depressions in flow routing using FlowFill</article-title>
        <source>Earth Surface Dynamics</source>
        <publisher-name>Copernicus GmbH</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-08">2019</year><month>08</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2021-04-04">2021</year><month>04</month><day>04</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <issn>2196-6311</issn>
        <uri>https://esurf.copernicus.org/articles/7/737/2019/</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/esurf-7-737-2019</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-costaPredictingVariableContributing2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>Diogo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shook</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>Jane</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baulch</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Henry</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pomeroy</surname><given-names>John W.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Predicting Variable Contributing Areas, Hydrological Connectivity, and Solute Transport Pathways for a Canadian Prairie Basin</article-title>
        <source>Water Resources Research</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2021-01-04">2021</year><month>01</month><day>04</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>56</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <issn>1944-7973</issn>
        <uri>http://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/2020WR027984</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2020WR027984</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-elboshyFrameworkPluvialFlood2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Elboshy</surname><given-names>Bahaa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kanae</surname><given-names>Shinjiro</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gamaleldin</surname><given-names>Mona</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ayad</surname><given-names>Hany</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Osaragi</surname><given-names>Toshihiro</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Elbarki</surname><given-names>Waleed</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A framework for pluvial flood risk assessment in Alexandria considering the coping capacity</article-title>
        <source>Environ Syst Decis</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-03">2019</year><month>03</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-07-14">2020</year><month>07</month><day>14</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>39</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>2194-5411</issn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10669-018-9684-7</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10669-018-9684-7</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-hayashiWaterSoluteTransfer1998">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kamp</surname><given-names>G Van Der</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>D L</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Water and solute transfer between a prairie wetland and adjacent uplands, 1. Water balance</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Hydrology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
        <volume>207</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">/10.1016/S0022-1694(98)00098-5</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-kissPredictiveMappingWetland2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>Jeremy</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Predictive mapping of wetland types and associated soils through digital elevation model analyses in the Canadian Prairie Pothole Region</article-title>
        <publisher-name>University of Saskatchewan</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-09">2018</year><month>09</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-07-14">2020</year><month>07</month><day>14</day></date-in-citation>
        <uri>https://harvest.usask.ca/handle/10388/11058</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-pomeroyColdRegionsHydrological2007">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Pomeroy</surname><given-names>J W</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>D M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hedstrom</surname><given-names>N R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Quinton</surname><given-names>W L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>R J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>S K</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The cold regions hydrological model : A platform for basing process representation and model structure on physical evidence</article-title>
        <source>Hydrological Processes</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007-09">2007</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>2667</volume>
        <issue>19</issue>
        <issn>08856087</issn>
        <uri>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/hyp.6787</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hyp.6787</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-schellenbergHydrologyDeltaMarsh2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="thesis">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Schellenberg</surname><given-names>Gregory John</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hydrology of the Delta Marsh Watershed: Water balance characterization and analysis of land use changes</article-title>
        <publisher-name>University of Manitoba</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-12">2017</year><month>12</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-07-14">2020</year><month>07</month><day>14</day></date-in-citation>
        <uri>https://mspace.lib.umanitoba.ca/xmlui/handle/1993/32779</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shapiroMAPCALCAlgebraGIS1992">
      <element-citation publication-type="report">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Westervelt</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>R.MAPCALC. An Algebra for GIS and Image Processing</article-title>
        <publisher-name>U.S. Army Construction Engineering Research Laboratory, Champaign, Illinois 61801, U.S.A.</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shawTopographicAnalysisPrairie2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pietroniro</surname><given-names>Al</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Martz</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Topographic analysis for the prairie pothole region of Western Canada</article-title>
        <source>Hydrological Processes</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012-06">2012</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <issue>22</issue>
        <issn>08856087</issn>
        <uri>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/hyp.9409</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hyp.9409</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shookMemoryEffectsDepressional2011">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Shook</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pomeroy</surname><given-names>John W</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Memory effects of depressional storage in Northern Prairie hydrology</article-title>
        <source>Hydrological Processes</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011-12">2011</year><month>12</month>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>25</issue>
        <issn>08856087</issn>
        <uri>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/hyp.8381</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hyp.8381</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shookQuantifyingEffectsPrairie2021">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Shook</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Papalexiou</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pomeroy</surname><given-names>John W.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Quantifying the effects of Prairie depressional storage complexes on drainage basin connectivity</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Hydrology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021-02">2021</year><month>02</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2021-01-06">2021</year><month>01</month><day>06</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>593</volume>
        <issn>0022-1694</issn>
        <uri>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002216942031307X</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2020.125846</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shookStorageDynamicsSimulations2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Shook</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pomeroy</surname><given-names>John W</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Boychuk</surname><given-names>Lyle</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Storage dynamics simulations in prairie wetland hydrology models: Evaluation and parameterization</article-title>
        <source>Hydrological Processes</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013-06">2013</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <issue>13</issue>
        <issn>08856087</issn>
        <uri>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/hyp.9867</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hyp.9867</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-spenceHydrologySubarcticCanadian2003">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>Ming Ko</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Hydrology of subarctic Canadian shield: Soil-filled valleys</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Hydrology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2003-08">2003</year><month>08</month>
        <volume>279</volume>
        <issue>1-4</issue>
        <issn>00221694</issn>
        <uri>http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0022169403001756</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-1694(03)00175-6</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-thapaGarbageGarbageOut2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Thapa</surname><given-names>Anuja</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>Lori</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Strickert</surname><given-names>Graham</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Xiaolei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anthony</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Watson-Daniels</surname><given-names>Kelsey</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Garbage in, Garbage Out Does Not Hold True for Indigenous Community Flood Extent Modeling in the Prairie Pothole Region</article-title>
        <source>Water</source>
        <publisher-name>Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/w11122486</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-venemahenrydavidClimateAdaptationUsing2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="report">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Venema</surname><given-names>Henry David</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Climate Adaptation Using Natural Infrastructure Town of Virden &amp; the Rural Municipality of Wallace - Woodworth</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Strategic Community Consulting</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-03">2020</year><month>03</month>
        <uri>www.strategiccc.ca</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-venemahenrydavidFloodRiskMapping2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="report">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Venema</surname><given-names>Henry David</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Flood Risk Mapping Study Rural Municipality of Springfield</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Strategic Community Consulting</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-06">2020</year><month>06</month>
        <uri>www.strategiccc.ca</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
