<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1635</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01635</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Spruceup: fast and flexible identification,
visualization, and removal of outliers from large multiple sequence
alignments</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0872-7098</contrib-id>
<string-name>Marek L. Borowiec</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Entomology, Plant Pathology and Nematology,
University of Idaho</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-09-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>42</issue>
<fpage>1635</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>bioinformatics</kwd>
<kwd>alignment trimming</kwd>
<kwd>phylogenetics</kwd>
<kwd>orthology</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p><monospace>spruceup</monospace> is an open-source Python software
  package that utilizes a novel algorithm and allows flexible
  identification, visualization, and removal of abnormal sequences from
  multiple sequence alignments (MSAs). The
  <monospace>spruceup</monospace> algorithm aims to solve the problem of
  individual poorly aligned sequences rarely addressed by other
  alignment trimming tools. It relies on computing distance metrics in a
  sliding window along an MSA and comparing them to metrics across all
  windows for each sample. While the program is designed with trimming
  phylogenetic datasets in mind, its output can be used for any task
  requiring computing of distances along MSAs with custom
  parameters.</p>
  <p>Evolutionary inference is increasingly reliant on large MSAs
  consisting of millions of sites from hundreds or thousands of samples.
  MSAs used for inference of evolutionary relationships should contain
  homologous nucleotides or amino acids (alignment columns) from
  different samples (alignment rows). However, MSAs may contain errors
  that violate this assumption of homology, resulting from
  cross-contamination, hidden paralogy, high divergence leading to
  insufficient information for accurate alignment, or other failures of
  alignment algorithms. These errors have been well-documented and shown
  to negatively impact phylogenetic inference. While many tools exist
  for trimming of poorly-aligned MSA columns, few allow identification
  of individual misaligned sequences. Tools for removal of poorly
  aligned columns address issues impacting most samples in the MSA but
  are not designed to identify misalignment limited to a single or few
  samples. Failure to remove such individual misaligned samples
  introduces errors into downstream analyses. Lack of tools for
  automated detection of these sequences means that most researchers
  simply do not address them and only few attempt manual alignment
  curation. Although visual inspection of data is always desirable,
  manual error correction is unsustainable with the alignment sizes used
  in modern phylogenetic studies. <monospace>spruceup</monospace> is
  intended for any phylogeneticist working with large datasets as a
  complement to commonly used tools that filter poorly-aligned MSA
  sites.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="overview">
  <title>Overview</title>
  <p>Evolutionary research relies on multiple sequence alignments (MSAs)
  which are matrix representations of hypotheses about the evolutionary
  history of genetic material. Rows in these matrices correspond to
  different samples, most often individual organisms representative of
  species or populations. The columns, which are called sites, contain
  nucleotides (in DNA and RNA sequences) or amino acids (in protein
  sequences) that should be homologous, meaning they are derived from
  the same ancestral nucleotide or amino acid in all included samples.
  Due to complexities of molecular evolution, aligning sequences such
  that they are homologous is a significant computational challenge
  (<xref alt="Morrison, 2018" rid="ref-morrison_2018multiple" ref-type="bibr">Morrison,
  2018</xref>). As a result, homology errors that have negative impact
  on downstream analyses, including phylogenetics and evolutionary
  inference
  (<xref alt="Ogden &amp; Rosenberg, 2006" rid="ref-ogden_2006msa" ref-type="bibr">Ogden
  &amp; Rosenberg, 2006</xref>), are widespread in currently published
  phylogenetic data
  (<xref alt="Philippe et al., 2017" rid="ref-philippe_2017" ref-type="bibr">Philippe
  et al., 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Springer &amp; Gatesy, 2018" rid="ref-springer_2018homology" ref-type="bibr">Springer
  &amp; Gatesy, 2018</xref>). Recent studies show that dramatically
  different phylogenetic trees can be produced by altering a few regions
  or even sites in very large MSAs
  (<xref alt="Brown &amp; Thomson, 2017" rid="ref-brown_2017bf" ref-type="bibr">Brown
  &amp; Thomson, 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Shen et al., 2017" rid="ref-shen_2017contentious" ref-type="bibr">Shen
  et al., 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Walker et al., 2018" rid="ref-walker_2018contentious" ref-type="bibr">Walker
  et al., 2018</xref>). Because of this, researchers often post-process
  MSAs following alignment to identify and filter out non-homologous
  matrix cells.</p>
  <p>Many tools exist that trim alignments based on low-quality sites
  (<xref alt="Capella-Gutierrez et al., 2009" rid="ref-capella_gutierrez_2009trimal" ref-type="bibr">Capella-Gutierrez
  et al., 2009</xref>;
  <xref alt="Criscuolo &amp; Gribaldo, 2010" rid="ref-criscuolo_2010bmge" ref-type="bibr">Criscuolo
  &amp; Gribaldo, 2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="Dress et al., 2008" rid="ref-dress_2008noisy" ref-type="bibr">Dress
  et al., 2008</xref>;
  <xref alt="Kück et al., 2010" rid="ref-kuck_2010" ref-type="bibr">Kück
  et al., 2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="Penn et al., 2010" rid="ref-penn_2010guidance" ref-type="bibr">Penn
  et al., 2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="Talavera &amp; Castresana, 2007" rid="ref-talavera_2007" ref-type="bibr">Talavera
  &amp; Castresana, 2007</xref>;
  <xref alt="Wu et al., 2012" rid="ref-wu_2012zorro" ref-type="bibr">Wu
  et al., 2012</xref>). These methods process MSAs on a column-by-column
  basis and can identify alignment blocks where many samples are
  problematic but may not have the power to identify errors affecting
  only one or few of the samples.</p>
  <p>Relatively few existing alignment trimming strategies have the
  ability to process data on a row-by-row basis and detect errors
  resulting from misalignment of one or few samples. An approach that
  has been successfully used in several phylogenomic studies uses
  information from phylogenetic trees inferred from individual locus or
  gene alignments to identify sequences characterized by unusually long
  branches
  (<xref alt="Borowiec et al., 2015" rid="ref-borowiec_2015ctenophora" ref-type="bibr">Borowiec
  et al., 2015</xref>;
  <xref alt="Yang &amp; Smith, 2014" rid="ref-yang_2014transcriptomes" ref-type="bibr">Yang
  &amp; Smith, 2014</xref>). Unfortunately, this approach may
  disproportionately affect genuinely divergent sequences, such as
  distantly related outgroup taxa. A more sophisticated version of this
  idea, capable of taking into account divergent samples, is implemented
  in TreeShrink
  (<xref alt="Mai &amp; Mirarab, 2018" rid="ref-mai_2018treeshrink" ref-type="bibr">Mai
  &amp; Mirarab, 2018</xref>). All tree-based approaches require
  phylogenetic analysis prior to and following alignment trimming, which
  may be computationally expensive.</p>
  <p>Two recently developed methods aim to identify artifacts affecting
  only one or few samples directly from sequence alignments: HmmCleaner
  (<xref alt="Di Franco et al., 2019" rid="ref-di_franco_2019hmmcleaner" ref-type="bibr">Di
  Franco et al., 2019</xref>) and PREQUAL
  (<xref alt="Whelan et al., 2018" rid="ref-whelan_2018prequal" ref-type="bibr">Whelan
  et al., 2018</xref>). Both tools build hidden Markov models of
  sequences within an alignment to identify poorly-aligned sequence
  fragments. They are designed to work with amino acid and
  protein-coding nucleotide sequences and are thus not suitable for some
  phylogenomic alignments, such as ones constructed from partially or
  largely non-coding ultraconserved elements
  (<xref alt="Faircloth et al., 2012" rid="ref-faircloth_2012uces" ref-type="bibr">Faircloth
  et al., 2012</xref>).</p>
  <p>Finally, visual inspection of alignment followed by manual
  correction has been proposed to deal with alignment issues
  (<xref alt="Springer &amp; Gatesy, 2018" rid="ref-springer_2018homology" ref-type="bibr">Springer
  &amp; Gatesy, 2018</xref>). Visual inspection of data is always
  desirable but it is unlikely to be used as a comprehensive
  error-removal strategy with alignments that now routinely include
  thousands of loci sequenced from dozens or even hundreds of samples
  (<xref alt="Edwards et al., 2016" rid="ref-edwards_2016" ref-type="bibr">Edwards
  et al., 2016</xref>).</p>
  <p>The Python software package <monospace>spruceup</monospace>
  introduced here was designed to perform fast detection of outlier
  sequences and alignment trimming without prior phylogenetic analysis
  and without penalizing genuinely divergent sequences. It is also
  capable of fine-scale alignment inspection that allows identification
  of errors affecting only parts of a locus or gene region. It fills a
  need for a user-friendly toolbox for flexible identification,
  visualization, and removal of individual misaligned sequence fragments
  from large multiple sequence alignments.</p>
  <p>The workflow of outlier detection and removal is as follows:</p>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <p>Split large phylogenomic alignment into windows of user-defined
      size and overlap.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Calculate genetic distances among samples in each window;
      distances can optionally be scaled by distance derived from a
      guide tree.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Compute distribution of distances across windows for each
      sample.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Fit a lognormal curve to distances observed for each sample
      (optional).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Using a user-defined cutoff, reject windows from the tail of
      the distribution in each sample. The cutoff can represent quantile
      of the fitted distribution or the mean of each sample’s distances
      across windows. The cutoff defined this way varies across samples
      and ensures that genuinely divergent samples are not
      disproportionately affected (Figure 1).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Plot and visualize distribution of distances and cutoffs for
      each sample.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p><monospace>spruceup</monospace> allows the user to calculate
  distances across alignment windows of arbitrary size and overlap. The
  resulting distances are written to a <monospace>json</monospace>
  format file. This distance output file can be later used for
  exploration of various outlier cutoff criteria and thresholds, or
  other applications where the user needs to know sample-specific
  distances across the alignment. Given user-defined criteria, the
  removal procedure identifies outliers and records their alignment
  coordinates to a file. Distribution of distances across all alignment
  windows are visualized for each sample along with thresholds chosen
  for trimming. The program can be used for outlier removal with
  variable amount of supervision, from trimming relying on default
  settings to assisted manual inspection of potentially erroneous
  regions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="availability-and-implementation">
  <title>Availability and Implementation</title>
  <p><monospace>spruceup</monospace> is written in Python 3 and
  supported on Linux operating systems. It is distributed under GNU
  GPLv3 license (https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-3.0.en.html). The
  source code, manual, tutorial, and example files are available on
  GitHub (https://github.com/marekborowiec/spruceup).
  <monospace>spruceup</monospace> is available on and can also be
  installed through the Python Package Index at
  (https://pypi.org/project/spruceup/).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="figure">
  <title>Figure</title>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Outlier removal from multiple sequence alignment by
    <monospace>spruceup</monospace>. This nucleotide alignment was
    simulated under a phylogenetic tree with topology and branch lengths
    taken from the empirical dataset of Ultraconserved Elements
    (<xref alt="Faircloth et al., 2012" rid="ref-faircloth_2012uces" ref-type="bibr">Faircloth
    et al., 2012</xref>) sequenced for a group of ants
    (<xref alt="Blaimer et al., 2016" rid="ref-blaimer_2016acropyga" ref-type="bibr">Blaimer
    et al., 2016</xref>). 100 alignments of 500 nucleotides each were
    simulated under the general time-reversible model (GTR) with state
    change rates between 0.1 and 1.0, base frequencies ranging from 0.1
    to 0.8, and branch length scaling between 0.1 and 50, each parameter
    selected randomly for each alignment. After the 100 alignments were
    concatenated, divergent (complemented) sequence fragments were
    introduced (left panels), and later trimmed using the
    <monospace>spruceup</monospace> workflow (right panels). The figure
    shows only a small window of the simulated concatenated alignment of
    50,000 nucleotides. Alignments visualized with AliView:
    https://ormbunkar.se/aliview/.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="spruceup-fig1.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>I would like to thank Philip S. Ward (UC Davis) for testing and
  valuable feedback on <monospace>spruceup</monospace>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-blaimer_2016acropyga">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Blaimer</surname><given-names>Bonnie B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>LaPolla</surname><given-names>John S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Branstetter</surname><given-names>Michael G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>Michael W.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>Seán G.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Phylogenomics, biogeography and diversification of obligate mealybug-tending ants in the genus Acropyga</article-title>
        <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-09">2016</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>102</volume>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.ympev.2016.05.030</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2016.05.030</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-borowiec_2015ctenophora">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Borowiec</surname><given-names>Marek L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Ernest K.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>Joanna C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Plachetzki</surname><given-names>David C.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Extracting phylogenetic signal and accounting for bias in whole-genome data sets supports the Ctenophora as sister to remaining Metazoa</article-title>
        <source>BMC Genomics</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015-11">2015</year><month>11</month>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1186%2Fs12864-015-2146-4</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-2146-4</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-brown_2017bf">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Jeremy M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>Robert C.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Bayes factors unmask highly variable information content, bias, and extreme influence in phylogenomic analyses</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>66</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1093%2Fsysbio%2Fsyw101</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syw101</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-capella_gutierrez_2009trimal">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Capella-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Silla-Martinez</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>trimAl: A tool for automated alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analyses</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2009-06">2009</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>15</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1093%2Fbioinformatics%2Fbtp348</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp348</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-criscuolo_2010bmge">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Criscuolo</surname><given-names>Alexis</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gribaldo</surname><given-names>Simonetta</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>BMGE (block mapping and gathering with entropy): A new software for selection of phylogenetic informative regions from multiple sequence alignments</article-title>
        <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1186%2F1471-2148-10-210</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-10-210</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-di_franco_2019hmmcleaner">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Di Franco</surname><given-names>Arnaud</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Poujol</surname><given-names>Raphaël</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baurain</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>Hervé</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evaluating the usefulness of alignment filtering methods to reduce the impact of errors on evolutionary inferences</article-title>
        <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-01">2019</year><month>01</month>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1186%2Fs12862-019-1350-2</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-019-1350-2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-dress_2008noisy">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Dress</surname><given-names>Andreas WM</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Flamm</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fritzsch</surname><given-names>Guido</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grünewald</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kruspe</surname><given-names>Matthias</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Prohaska</surname><given-names>Sonja J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>Peter F</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Noisy: Identification of problematic columns in multiple sequence alignments</article-title>
        <source>Algorithms for Molecular Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1186%2F1748-7188-3-7</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1748-7188-3-7</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-edwards_2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>Scott V.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Zhenxiang</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Janke</surname><given-names>Axel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Faircloth</surname><given-names>Brant C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>John E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>Travis C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Bojian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Shaoyuan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>Emily Moriarty</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>Alan R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Leaché</surname><given-names>Adam D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Liang</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Charles C.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Implementing and testing the multispecies coalescent model: A valuable paradigm for phylogenomics</article-title>
        <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier BV</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-01">2016</year><month>01</month>
        <volume>94</volume>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.ympev.2015.10.027</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2015.10.027</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-faircloth_2012uces">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Faircloth</surname><given-names>Brant C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>John E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>Nicholas G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>Michael G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brumfield</surname><given-names>Robb T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>Travis C.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Ultraconserved elements anchor thousands of genetic markers spanning multiple evolutionary timescales</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012-01">2012</year><month>01</month>
        <volume>61</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/sys004</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/sys004</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-kuck_2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kück</surname><given-names>Patrick</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Meusemann</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dambach</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thormann</surname><given-names>Birthe</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>von Reumont</surname><given-names>Björn M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wägele</surname><given-names>Johann W</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Misof</surname><given-names>Bernhard</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Parametric and non-parametric masking of randomness in sequence alignments can be improved and leads to better resolved trees</article-title>
        <source>Frontiers in Zoology</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1186%2F1742-9994-7-10</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-9994-7-10</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-mai_2018treeshrink">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>Uyen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mirarab</surname><given-names>Siavash</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>TreeShrink: Fast and accurate detection of outlier long branches in collections of phylogenetic trees</article-title>
        <source>BMC Genomics</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-05">2018</year><month>05</month>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <issue>S5</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1186%2Fs12864-018-4620-2</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4620-2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-morrison_2018multiple">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>David A</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multiple sequence alignment is not a solved problem</article-title>
        <source>arXiv</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.07717</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ogden_2006msa">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>T Heath</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>Michael S</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Multiple sequence alignment accuracy and phylogenetic inference</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2006-04">2006</year><month>04</month>
        <volume>55</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1080%2F10635150500541730</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150500541730</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-penn_2010guidance">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Privman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ashkenazy</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Landan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Graur</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pupko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>GUIDANCE: A web server for assessing alignment confidence scores</article-title>
        <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010-05">2010</year><month>05</month>
        <volume>38</volume>
        <issue>Web Server</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1093%2Fnar%2Fgkq443</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq443</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-philippe_2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>Hervé</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>de Vienne</surname><given-names>Damien M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ranwez</surname><given-names>Vincent</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Roure</surname><given-names>Béatrice</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baurain</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>Frédéric</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pitfalls in supermatrix phylogenomics</article-title>
        <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
        <publisher-name>Museum National DHistoire Naturelle</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-02">2017</year><month>02</month>
        <volume>283</volume>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.5852%2Fejt.2017.283</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5852/ejt.2017.283</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-shen_2017contentious">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Xing-Xing</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hittinger</surname><given-names>Chris Todd</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>Antonis</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Contentious relationships in phylogenomic studies can be driven by a handful of genes</article-title>
        <source>Nature Ecology and Evolution</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-04">2017</year><month>04</month>
        <volume>1</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fs41559-017-0126</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41559-017-0126</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-springer_2018homology">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>Mark S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gatesy</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>On the importance of homology in the age of phylogenomics</article-title>
        <source>Systematics and Biodiversity</source>
        <publisher-name>Informa UK Limited</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>16</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1080%2F14772000.2017.1401016</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14772000.2017.1401016</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-talavera_2007">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Talavera</surname><given-names>Gerard</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>Jose</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Improvement of phylogenies after removing divergent and ambiguously aligned blocks from protein sequence alignments</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007-08">2007</year><month>08</month>
        <volume>56</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10635150701472164</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150701472164</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-walker_2018contentious">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>Joseph F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Joseph W</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Stephen A</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Analyzing contentious relationships and outlier genes in phylogenomics</article-title>
        <source>Systematic Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-06">2018</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>67</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1093%2Fsysbio%2Fsyy043</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syy043</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-whelan_2018prequal">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Irisarri</surname><given-names>Iker</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Burki</surname><given-names>Fabien</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PREQUAL: Detecting non-homologous characters in sets of unaligned homologous sequences</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-06">2018</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <issue>22</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1093%2Fbioinformatics%2Fbty448</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty448</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-wu_2012zorro">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chatterji</surname><given-names>Sourav</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>Jonathan A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Accounting for alignment uncertainty in phylogenomics</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science (PLoS)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012-01">2012</year><month>01</month>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0030288</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030288</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-yang_2014transcriptomes">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Ya</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Stephen A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Orthology inference in nonmodel organisms using transcriptomes and low-coverage genomes: Improving accuracy and matrix occupancy for phylogenomics</article-title>
        <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014-08">2014</year><month>08</month>
        <volume>31</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1093%2Fmolbev%2Fmsu245</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu245</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
