<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1880</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01880</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>rnassqs: An R package to access agricultural data via the
USDA National Agricultural Statistics Service (USDA-NASS) 'Quick Stats'
API</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3410-3732</contrib-id>
<string-name>Nicholas A. Potter</string-name>
<email>potter.nicholas@gmail.com</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Washington State University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-06-09">
<day>9</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>43</issue>
<fpage>1880</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>API</kwd>
<kwd>reproducibility</kwd>
<kwd>agriculture</kwd>
<kwd>economics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ropensci/rnassqs">rnassqs</ext-link>
  <monospace>R</monospace> package provides a simple interface for
  accessing the United States Department of Agriculture National
  Agricultural Statistics Service (USDA-NASS)
  ‘<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://quickstats.nass.usda.gov/">Quick
  Stats</ext-link>’ API. The core functionality allows the user to query
  agricultural data from ‘Quick Stats’ in a reproducible and automated
  way. The primary benefit of <monospace>rnassqs</monospace> is that
  users need not download data through repeated use of the Quick Stats
  point-and-click interface, which reduces the chance of errors,
  eliminates the need for repeated manual downloads of new data over
  time or space, and allows for automated updates of web applications
  that rely on new releases of USDA-NASS data over time.</p>
  <p><monospace>rnassqs</monospace> manages API authentication by
  setting a system environmental variable for the duration of the
  <monospace>R</monospace> session. Convenience functions facilitate
  querying common data. Users can also use
  <monospace>rnassqs</monospace> to query the list of data parameters
  and available values for a given parameter (for example, to see the
  commodities available in a particular county and year). The query
  requests data as a JSON object and parses that data into a
  <monospace>data.frame</monospace> object.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="about-usda-nass-data-and-quick-stats">
  <title>About USDA-NASS data and ‘Quick Stats’</title>
  <p>‘Quick Stats’ is a web interface to access data produced by
  USDA-NASS. The data comes primarily from the Census of Agriculture,
  but also includes data from USDA-NASS surveys on a wide range of
  topics. The Census of Agriculture is conducted every five years in
  years ending in ‘2’ and ‘7’. The earliest year available on Quick
  Stats is 1997. Surveys have different collection periods, but most are
  collected annually. Some specific data such as the average value of
  agricultural land and buildings by state is reported as early as
  1850.</p>
  <p>Aggregate data from the census and surveys is released primarily at
  the national, state, and county level, though some data may be
  released for congressional districts, watersheds, and zip codes. It
  includes a range of data classified under five sectors: Animals &amp;
  Products, Crops, Demographics, Economics, and Environmental. Examples
  of data available in these sectors include counts of farms, farm
  operators, acres of cropland, farm sales, farm expenses, and crop
  yields to name a few.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="benefits-of-rnassqs-over-quick-stats">
  <title>Benefits of <monospace>rnassqs</monospace> over ‘Quick
  Stats’</title>
  <p>‘Quick Stats’ provides a number of selection fields in which the
  user can select categories of data. Each selection causes the options
  in other fields to update to reflect available options available
  options based on other selections that the user has made. This makes
  the selection of multiple different variables an at times frustrating
  process. In addition, data requests are limited to 50,000 records. If
  a user wants to access more records they must manually subset their
  data request. For example, requesting crop yields by county for all
  counties and census years for 1997 to 2017 requires either downloading
  each state’s counties separately or, where possible, downloading all
  counties for each year separately. The Quick Stats interface works
  well for quick access or a single use. However, there are several
  cases in which the ‘Quick Stats’ interface is not ideal:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Requests for a combination of measures, years, and geographies
      that exceed 50,000 records.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Requests for newly released data that are identical to previous
      requests.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Requests that are reproducible.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p><monospace>rnassqs</monospace> addresses each of these issues by
  making the ‘Quick Stats’ API accessible with <monospace>R</monospace>
  code. This allows the user to loop over a series of requests to
  address the first issue, to execute (perhaps automated on a schedule)
  a data request repeatedly to access new data with the same query to
  address the second, and to make code available that allows others to
  reproducibly access the same data to address the third.</p>
  <p>For example, there are currently there are currently 332,125
  records of crop yields in all U.S. counties from 2000 to 2018.
  Accessing this data through ‘Quick Stats’ would require manually
  selecting either a set of years or a set of states to reduce each
  request to less than 50,000 records and then aggregating that data.
  With <monospace>rnassqs</monospace> this can be done with:</p>
  <code language="r script"># Access yields for all counties and all crops
params &lt;- list(sector_desc = &quot;CROPS&quot;,
               group_desc = c(&quot;FIELD CROPS&quot;, &quot;FRUIT &amp; TREE NUTS&quot;, 
                              &quot;HORTICULTURE&quot;, &quot;VEGETABLES&quot;),
               statisticcat_desc = &quot;YIELD&quot;, 
               agg_level_desc = &quot;COUNTY&quot;)

# Get all years from 2000 to 2018 in a list of data.frames
data_list &lt;- lapply(2000:2018, function(yr) { 
  params$year &lt;- yr
  rnassqs::nassqs(params, url_only = TRUE)
})

# Aggregate the list of data.frames into a single data.frame
d &lt;- do.call(&quot;rbind&quot;, data_list)</code>
  <p>This results in significant time savings, increases the
  reproducibility of the data, and allows for easy updating of the
  request when a new year is made available.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="alternatives-to-rnassqs">
  <title>Alternatives to <monospace>rnassqs</monospace></title>
  <p>USDA-NASS also provides FTP access to text data
  files<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>. By accessing the data via
  FTP users can avoid using the selection interface of ‘Quick Stats’ and
  avoid limitations on the number of records per request, but do not
  resolve issues of automated repeated requests or of making data
  requests reproducible. Other <monospace>R</monospace> packages have
  also been released since the development of
  <monospace>rnassqs</monospace> that provide access to Quick Stats
  data, though somewhat differently, include
  <monospace>usdarnass</monospace> and <monospace>tidyUSDA</monospace>,
  which uses US Census maps to create maps of Quick Stats data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>Thank you to Jonathan Adams, Julia Piaskowski, and Joseph Stachelek
  for code contributions. A huge thanks to reviewers Adam H Sparks and
  Neal Richardson for their thoughtful feedback to improve the package
  and documentation.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
  <fn id="fn1">
    <label>1</label><p>Available at:
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.nass.usda.gov/quickstats/">ftp://ftp.nass.usda.gov/quickstats/</ext-link></p>
  </fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
