<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2637</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02637</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>pvpumpingsystem: A Python package for modeling and sizing
photovoltaic water pumping systems</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3008-1422</contrib-id>
<string-name>Tanguy R. Lunel</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-7247-5705</contrib-id>
<string-name>Daniel R. Rousse</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Industrial Research Group In Technologies of Energy and
Energy Efficiency (T3E), Department of Mechanical Sciences, Ecole de
Technologie Supérieure Montreal</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Material Science and Engineering, Institut
National des Sciences Appliquées Rennes</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-04-14">
<day>14</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>54</issue>
<fpage>2637</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>sizing</kwd>
<kwd>modeling</kwd>
<kwd>water pumping</kwd>
<kwd>photovoltaics</kwd>
<kwd>solar energy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>According to the World Health Organization, one tenth of the world
  population still lacks access to basic water supply. One of the
  reasons for this is the remoteness of these populations from modern
  water collection and distribution technologies, often coupled with an
  unfavorable socio-economic situation. Photovoltaic (PV) pumping
  technology makes it possible to respond both to this problem and to
  the criteria of sustainable development. However, these pumping
  systems must be carefully modeled and sized in order to make the water
  supply cost efficient and reliable.</p>
  <p>Pvpumpingsystem was conceived in order to tackle this issue. It is
  an open source package providing various tools aimed at facilitating
  the modeling and the sizing of photovoltaic powered water pumping
  systems. Even though the package is originally targeted at researchers
  and engineers, three practical examples are provided in order to help
  anyone to use pvpumpingsystem.</p>
  <p>Python is the programming language used in the software, and the
  code is structured with an object-oriented approach. Continuous
  integration services allow for lint checking and to test automation.
  Each class and function are documented with reference to the
  literature when applicable. Pvpumpingsystem is released under a GPL-v3
  license.</p>
  <p>Pvpumpingsystem relies on already existing packages for
  photovoltaic and fluid mechanics modeling, namely “pvlib-python”
  (<xref alt="Holmgren et al., 2018" rid="ref-pvlib-python" ref-type="bibr">Holmgren
  et al., 2018</xref>) and “fluids”
  (<xref alt="Bell, 2020" rid="ref-fluids" ref-type="bibr">Bell,
  2020</xref>). pvpumpingsystem’s originality lies in the implementation
  of various motor-pump models for finite power sources and in the
  coupling of the distinct component models. In order to increase the
  understandability of the code, each physical component of the PV
  pumping system corresponds to a class, like for example the classes
  <monospace>Pump()</monospace>, <monospace>MPPT()</monospace>,
  <monospace>PipeNetwork()</monospace>,
  <monospace>Reservoir()</monospace>, and
  <monospace>PVGeneration()</monospace>. The previous objects are then
  gathered in the class <monospace>PVPumpSystem()</monospace> which
  allows running a comprehensive model of the pumping system.</p>
  <p>The main inputs to the simulation are an hourly weather file, water
  source characteristics, expected water consumption profile, and
  specifications of the photovoltaic array, motor-pump and water
  reservoir. Typical outputs are hourly flow rates, unused electric
  power, efficiency of components, life cycle cost and loss of load
  probability. The sizing module then builds on the modeling tools, and
  uses them to provides functions to help choose the best combination of
  components in order to minimize the total life cycle cost.
  Nevertheless, sizing such complex systems is still an active field of
  research, and this module is subsequently expected to be expanded with
  time.</p>
  <p>Two software packages with similar scope already exist: PVsyst and
  online tool SISIFO, developed by the MASLOWATEN consortium.
  Nevertheless, both are closed source, with restricted information on
  models used internally, and no API is made accessible. Pvpumpingsystem
  also has the advantage of providing ways to size PV pumping systems
  thanks to automation of pump and PV array choices.</p>
  <p>Pvpumpingsystem is the second academic contribution of a broader
  research program on photovoltaic water pumping launched in the
  Technologies of Energy and Energy Efficiency research group at Ecole
  de Technologie Supérieure Montreal, and is expected to grow with new
  features and accuracy assessment provided by experimental studies. The
  authors also want to give full access and help to anyone else
  interested in the use of the software.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>The authors would like to acknowledge Mr. Michel Trottier for his
  generous support to the T3E research group, as well as the NSERC and
  the FRQNT for their grants and subsidies. The first author
  acknowledges the contributions and fruitful discussions with Louis
  Lamarche and Sergio Gualteros that inspired and helped with the
  current work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="reference">
  <title>Reference</title>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-pvlib-python">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>William F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>Clifford W.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mikofski</surname><given-names>Mark A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pvlib python: A python package for modeling solar energy systems</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00884</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-fluids">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>Caleb</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>fluids: Fluid dynamics component of Chemical Engineering Design Library (ChEDL)</article-title>
        <source>GitHub repository</source>
        <publisher-name>GitHub</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <uri>https://github.com/CalebBell/fluids</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
