<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">886</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00886</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Combining a Probability and a Non-Probability Sample in a
Capture-Recapture Setting</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-8474-5066</contrib-id>
<string-name>Benjamin Williams</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Statistical Science, Southern Methodist
University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-08-06">
<day>6</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>28</issue>
<fpage>886</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>non-probability sampling</kwd>
<kwd>combining data sources</kwd>
<kwd>capture-recapture sampling</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Statistical sampling plays a vital role in understanding and making
  inferences with respect to all types of populations and is especially
  salient in a world where populations are large and big data is the new
  standard. In an ideal situation, samplers have access to a list of all
  the units in a population, called a sampling frame, from which to draw
  a sample. This allows them to select individual population units with
  known probabilities, producing a probability sample
  (<xref alt="Lohr, 2010" rid="ref-lohr_samplingU003A_2010" ref-type="bibr">Lohr,
  2010</xref>). A sample for which probabilities of selection are not
  known is called a non-probability sample. Probability samples are
  preferred to non-probability samples because the sampling variance of
  the estimators calculated from probability samples can be determined
  using standard sampling theory. The primary disadvantage of
  non-probability samples is the potential for biased estimation
  stemming from undercoverage and a lack of representativeness in the
  samples. Without external sources of information, these sample
  deficiencies cannot be detected.</p>
  <p>It is usually easier to obtain a non-probability sample than a
  probability sample. For example, a frame may not be available, which
  complicates the selection of a probability sample. A non-probability
  sample, such as one using data from volunteers, does not require an
  expensive nonresponse follow-up. The larger the sample, the more
  information it may contain. This is an attractive option for analysts
  working with limited resources while studying elusive populations. As
  a result, statisticians have begun to investigate methods for
  improving estimation using data from non-probability samples (for
  example, Elliott &amp; Haviland
  (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-elliott_use_2007" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>)).
  One way to improve such estimation is to combine a non-probability
  sample with a probability sample.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/williamsbenjamin/blendR">blendR</ext-link>
  package (available on
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/williamsbenjamin/blendR">GitHub</ext-link>)
  provides four statistically valid estimators of total when combining a
  non-probability sample with a probability sample. These estimators
  have applications in many areas, such as: the internet of things,
  where a non-probability sample could be taken from devices connected
  to the internet; insurance claims, where claims could be voluntarily
  reported; and estimation of the death toll due to a natural disaster,
  where survivors could self-report deaths in a family. In each of these
  situations, the estimators from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/williamsbenjamin/blendR">blendR</ext-link>
  can combine the information from the respective non-probability
  samples with a probability sample to make more accurate estimates. The
  prevalence of non-probability samples continues to grow in both
  academia and industry, due in large part to technological advances and
  the availability of big data.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/williamsbenjamin/blendR">blendR</ext-link>
  is needed to allow analysts from a variety of disciplines to use
  non-probability samples to improve estimation.</p>
  <p>The estimators are taken from Liu et al.
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-liu_estimation_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
  and Breidt et al.
  (<xref alt="2018" rid="ref-breidt_model-assisted_2018" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).
  The sampling program considers the non-probability sample as a capture
  sample and the probability sample as a recapture sample, meaning units
  selected into the non-probability sample can be again sampled into the
  probability sample. Capture-recapture methodology provides powerful
  tools to estimate the total number of units in a population
  (<xref alt="Le Cren, 1965" rid="ref-cren_note_1965" ref-type="bibr">Le
  Cren, 1965</xref>). The goal of the four estimators presented is to
  make valid estimates of the total of some variable of interest
  gathered in both samples. The values may disagree for units which are
  part of both samples (due to measurement error, for example).</p>
  <p>The estimators from Liu et al.
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-liu_estimation_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
  are ratio estimators and the one from Breidt et al.
  (<xref alt="2018" rid="ref-breidt_model-assisted_2018" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)
  is a difference estimator. One ratio estimator uses whether or not the
  unit was a part of the non-probability sample as auxiliary
  information, one uses the value of the variable of interest gathered
  in the non-probability sample as auxiliary information, and the third
  is a weighted combination of the first two estimators. The difference
  estimator adds the total value of the variable of interest gathered in
  the non-probability sample to the estimated difference between the
  value of the variable in the probability sample and the value of the
  variable in the non-probability sample. These estimators can be used
  in any situation of combining samples via a capture-recapture sampling
  program and have many exciting possible extensions.</p>
  <p>The estimators are currently used to estimate the total catch of
  the fish in several settings, including the fish Red Snapper by Texas
  Parks and Wildlife (TPWD). TPWD and other entities, including the
  National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) estimate the
  total fish catch in the Gulf of Mexico. The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/williamsbenjamin/blendR">blendR</ext-link>
  package provides data from a 2016 TPWD capture-recapture sampling
  program in which the capture sample was a non-probability sample of
  captains who reported the number of Red Snapper they caught via a
  smartphone app. The recapture sample was a dockside intercept sample
  in which boats were boarded and interviewers collected data about the
  number of Red Snapper caught (a probability sample).</p>
  <p>The National Research Council has advised NOAA to continue
  experiments with electronic reporting to better estimate the total
  fish caught in marine waters by recreational anglers
  (<xref alt="National Research Council, 2017" rid="ref-committee_on_the_review_of_the_marine_recreational_information_program_review_2017" ref-type="bibr">National
  Research Council, 2017</xref>). Accurate estimation is critical to
  setting approriate fishing seasons and bag limits. As such, this is an
  important research field.</p>
  <p>This work is part of dissertation research by the author (Benjamin
  Williams). It is also being used in working papers regarding
  non-sampling errors and sample size calculations for electronic
  reporting experiments by a fisheries research team at Southern
  Methodist University led by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.smu.edu/News/Experts/Lynn-Stokes">Lynne
  Stokes</ext-link>. Bug reports, contributions, and other useful
  comments are welcomed as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/williamsbenjamin/blendR/issues">issue
  tickets</ext-link> on Github and will be attended to in a timely
  manner.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-lohr_samplingU003A_2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Lohr</surname><given-names>Sharon L.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Sampling: Design and analysis</source>
        <publisher-name>Brooks/Cole</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-liu_estimation_2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Bingchen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>Lynne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Topping</surname><given-names>Tara</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stunz</surname><given-names>Greg</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Estimation of a Total from a Population of Unknown Size and Application to Estimating Recreational Red Snapper Catch in Texas</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Survey Statistics and Methodology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-09">2017</year><month>09</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2017-11-01">2017</year><month>11</month><day>01</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <issn>2325-0984, 2325-0992</issn>
        <uri>http://academic.oup.com/jssam/article/5/3/350/4036215/Estimation-of-a-Total-from-a-Population-of-Unknown</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jssam/smx006</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-committee_on_the_review_of_the_marine_recreational_information_program_review_2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>National Research Council</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Review of the marine recreational information program</source>
        <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-07-21">2017</year><month>07</month><day>21</day>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2017-10-05">2017</year><month>10</month><day>05</day></date-in-citation>
        <isbn>978-0-309-45374-5</isbn>
        <uri>https://www.nap.edu/catalog/24640</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17226/24640</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-breidt_model-assisted_2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Breidt</surname><given-names>Jay F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Opsomer</surname><given-names>Jean D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Chen-Min</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Model-assisted survey estimation with imperfectly matched auxiliary data</article-title>
        <source>Predictive econometrics and big data</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>753</volume>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-elliott_use_2007">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>Marc N.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Haviland</surname><given-names>Amelia</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Use of a Web-Based Convenience Sample to Supplement a Probability Sample</article-title>
        <source>Survey methodology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2017-02-07">2017</year><month>02</month><day>07</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <uri>http://www.thewitnessbox.com/10498-en.pdf</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-cren_note_1965">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Le Cren</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A Note on the History of Mark-Recapture Population Estimates</article-title>
        <source>The Journal of Animal Ecology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1965-06">1965</year><month>06</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2017-10-05">2017</year><month>10</month><day>05</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>34</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <issn>00218790</issn>
        <uri>http://www.jstor.org/stable/2661?origin=crossref</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2661</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
