<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">190</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00190</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Plotrr: Functions for making visual exploratory data
analysis with nested data easier.</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-5144-8671</contrib-id>
<string-name>Charles Crabtree</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-7665-7557</contrib-id>
<string-name>Michael J. Nelson</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Michigan</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Pennsylvania State University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2017-02-12">
<day>12</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<fpage>190</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>exploratory data analysis</kwd>
<kwd>nested data</kwd>
<kwd>visualization</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <sec id="note-this-paper-describes-the-0.3.0-version-of-the-software.-check-the-readme-for-current-info-about-the-package.">
    <title>Note: This paper describes the 0.3.0 version of the software.
    Check the README for current info about the package.</title>
    <p>Large social science literatures examine the role of an
    individual’s ethnicity or nationality on a host of behaviors. This
    means that they often want to know the ethnicities or nationalities
    of individuals. Not all pre-existing datasets contain this
    information, though, and it can be difficult for scholars to locate
    if they work with exotic samples. Even if reseachers do not have
    information about the ethnicity or nationality of individuals,
    though, they often know their names. Thanks to recent developments
    in machine learning, these names can be used to probabilistically
    identify the ethnic or national origins of their bearers. These
    exciting advancements can potentially catalyze existing research
    programs on race, ethnicity, and coethnicity.</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, most of the available name classifiers are very
    costly to use. While some allow free access, they typically impose
    extremely restrictive limits on the number of names that can be
    classified in a period, such as 100 per month (see
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.namsor.com/">NamSor</ext-link>).
    One free tool with a generous limit is
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://name-prism.com/">NamePrism</ext-link>
    (Ye et al. 2017), a non-commercial program intended to support
    academic research. At the time of this writing, NamePrism provides
    users with an accessible web-based interface that can classify names
    one at a time. Researchers who want to classify more than one name
    at a time can, in theory, use the publicly available
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://name-prism.com/api">API</ext-link>.
    In contrast to other tools and services, NamePrism allows up to 1000
    API requests per day.</p>
    <p>In order to classify names in bulk, however, researchers would
    need to write code to automatically query the API. That could be a
    significant barrier to use, though, as many scholars likely lack the
    requisite programming experience. The <monospace>nomine</monospace>
    package address that problem by providing two functions that make
    the task of quering NameSor’s API trivally easy. The first,
    <monospace>get_ethnicities</monospace>, takes a vector of names and
    returns a data frame that contains the predicted probability that
    each name bearer belongs to one of 6 U.S. ethnicities. The second,
    <monospace>get_nationalities</monospace>, performs the same function
    but for 39 lead nationalities instead. See
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://name-prism.com/about">http://name-prism.com/about</ext-link>
    for more information about the specific ethnicities and
    nationalities covered by NameSor.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
