<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">941</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00941</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Samewords: Automatic word disambigation in critical text
editions</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8190-679X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Saxo-Institute, University of Copenhagen</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Representation and Reality, University of
Gothenburg</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-07-03">
<day>3</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>36</issue>
<fpage>941</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>LaTeX</kwd>
<kwd>textual criticism</kwd>
<kwd>text editing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The presented software helps the editor of critical scholarly
  editions solve a common problem when presenting a critical apparatus.
  To illustrate the purpose and use of the software, I will describe the
  scholarly domain it applies to.</p>
  <p>Scholarly disciplines that use texts as their primary source of
  data are confronted with the challenge of textual editing. This
  applies to virtually all studies within the arts and humanities and
  certainly some that lie beyond; a few examples would be literary
  studies, philosophy, history, and linguistics. Textual, or scholarly,
  editing is the activity of providing texts that will be the basis for
  any subsequent work, be it analysis by a researcher, translation, or
  leisurely reading. This activity thus provides the raw material for
  any kind of research within these disciplines.</p>
  <p>Establishing such texts is a highly specialized activity
  presupposing research skills in all the relevant subject areas of a
  text, such as the linguistic disciplines, the study of the content,
  but also the whole discipline of stemmatics, codicology, palaeography
  (it very often involves reading medieval or early modern material in
  manuscript form), and text history. The result of this work is the
  critical text, a text which presents the closest an editor is able to
  get to the ideal text defined by the use case and purpose of the
  edition.</p>
  <p>The critical apparatus is an essential part of a critical text.
  This gives any expert reader information about the choices that the
  editor has made in establishing the text. Examples of such information
  could be the differences between the text of different witnesses (for
  example manuscripts or printings), details of the history of the text,
  and particular difficulties in the interpretation of the
  witnesses.</p>
  <p>A common problem for the editor, and later a reader, of a critical
  text edition is the handling of ambiguous references in the critical
  apparatus. Let us take this paragraph as an example:</p>
  <preformat>Here is a chunk of text, what a nice place for a critical note.

----
1 a] om. M</preformat>
  <p>Unless the “a” is disambiguated, it is impossible to determine
  which instance the reference points to. This will often be done by a
  numbering scheme such as this:</p>
  <preformat>Here is a chunk of text, what a nice place for a critical note.

----
1 a²] om. M</preformat>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ctan.org/pkg/reledmac"><italic>Reledmac</italic></ext-link>
  (<xref alt="Rouquette &amp; Wilson, 2018" rid="ref-reledmac" ref-type="bibr">Rouquette
  &amp; Wilson, 2018</xref>) is the standard LaTeX package used for
  typesetting critical scholarly editions of the highest standard. It
  already provides facilities for disambiguating identical words, but it
  requires the editor of the critical text to mark all potential
  instances of ambiguous references manually. This is a significant
  labour in large text editions, as any recompilation may change the
  presentation of the text, and hence require the editor to check for
  any new conflicts and annotate them accordingly. The annotation of
  ambiguous words can also be very complex, and the manual annotation
  therefore includes a large risk of error.</p>
  <p><italic>Samewords</italic> therefore automates this process. It is
  a Python 3 package that can be installed via
  <monospace>pip</monospace>, but an online interface and API is also
  provided for the users who are not used to installing and running
  software from the command line. It provides full Unicode 10 support,
  and handles single word conflicts by default (with the option to
  annotate multi-word conflicts) as well as apparatus entries with
  custom lemmas. It is possible to indicate custom ellipsis patterns for
  spans in custom lemma references. Further details, such as the number
  of context words to compare, recognized punctuation characters, and
  case sensitivity can be configured in a configuration file.</p>
  <p>The full documentation can be found at
  https://samewords.readthedocs.io/en/latest/.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>I acknowledge valuable contributions from Florian Grammel who has
  reported numerous bugs and performed extensive testing and
  feedback.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-reledmac">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Rouquette</surname><given-names>Maïeul</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Peter R.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Reledmac: Typeset scholarly editions with LaTeX</article-title>
        <publisher-name>CTAN</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-05-21">2018</year><month>05</month><day>21</day>
        <uri>https://www.ctan.org/pkg/reledmac</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
