<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1260</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01260</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>getTBinR: an R package for accessing and summarising the
World Health Organisation Tuberculosis data</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-8057-8037</contrib-id>
<string-name>Sam Abbott</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Bristol Medical School: Population Health Sciences,
University of Bristol, Bristol, UK</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-01-29">
<day>29</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>34</issue>
<fpage>1260</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>rstats</kwd>
<kwd>World Health Organisation</kwd>
<kwd>Open Data</kwd>
<kwd>Visualisation</kwd>
<kwd>Infectious Disease</kwd>
<kwd>Tuberculosis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Developing tools for rapidly accessing and exploring data sets
  benefits the public health research community by enabling multiple
  data sets to be combined in a consistent manner, increasing the
  visibility of key data sets, and providing a framework that can be
  used to explore key questions of interest. Tooling also reduces the
  barriers to entry, allowing non-specialists to explore data sets that
  would otherwise be inaccessible. This widening of access may also lead
  to new insights and wider interest for key public health issues.</p>
  <p><monospace>getTBinR</monospace> is an R package
  (<xref alt="R Core Team, 2019" rid="ref-RCoreTeam2019" ref-type="bibr">R
  Core Team, 2019</xref>) to facilitate working with the data
  (<xref alt="World Health Organisation, 2018" rid="ref-WHOU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">World
  Health Organisation, 2018</xref>) collected by the World Health
  Organisation (WHO) on the country level epidemiology of Tuberculosis
  (TB). All data is freely available from the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/tb/country/data/download/en/">WHO</ext-link>
  and the package code is archived on Zenodo
  (<xref alt="Abbott, 2019" rid="ref-AbbottU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Abbott,
  2019</xref>) and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.samabbott.co.uk/getTBinR/">Github</ext-link>.
  The aim of <monospace>getTBinR</monospace> is to allow researchers,
  and other interested individuals, to quickly and easily gain access to
  a detailed TB data set and to start using it to derive key insights.
  It provides a consistent set of tools that can be used to rapidly
  evaluate hypotheses on a widely used data set before they are explored
  further using more complex methods or more detailed data. The
  functions provided in this package were developed to have sensible
  defaults to allow those new to the field to quickly gain key insights
  but also allow sufficient customisation so that experienced users may
  rapidly prototype new ideas.</p>
  <p>The data sourced by <monospace>getBTinR</monospace> is collected by
  the WHO, via member governments, and used to compile the yearly global
  TB report
  (<xref alt="World Health Organisation, 2018" rid="ref-WHOU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">World
  Health Organisation, 2018</xref>). Data collection encompasses TB
  incidence, TB mortality rates, the age distribution of TB cases, the
  proportion of drug resistant cases, case detection rates, and
  treatment rates. For a complete description of the data and data
  collection process, see
  (<xref alt="World Health Organisation, 2018" rid="ref-WHOU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">World
  Health Organisation, 2018</xref>). These data are used by the WHO,
  governmental organisations and researchers to summarise country level
  TB epidemiology, as well as the wider global and regional picture.</p>
  <p>The <monospace>getTBinR</monospace> package facilitates downloading
  the most up-to-date version of multiple TB relevant data sources from
  the WHO, along with the accompanying data dictionaries. It also
  contains functions to allow easy exploration of the data via searching
  data dictionaries, summarising key metrics on a regional and global
  level, and visualising the data in a variety of highly customisable
  ways. In addition, it provides both a dashboard and an automated
  country level report that enables the global, regional, and country
  level picture to be quickly summarised. An example of a potential use
  of the package is to explore estimates of the TB case fatality ratio
  (<xref alt="Abbott, 2018" rid="ref-AbbottU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">Abbott,
  2018</xref>). In a few lines of code, using only built in package
  tooling, large regional differences can be discovered. Further
  insights can then be found by linking to other publicly available data
  sets or using a model based analysis. See
  https://www.samabbott.co.uk/getTBinR/ for documentation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>Thanks to the staff at the World Health Organisation for compiling
  the data sets used in this package. SA is funded by the National
  Institute for Health Research Health Protection Research Unit (NIHR
  HPRU) in Evaluation of Interventions at University of Bristol in
  partnership with Public Health England (PHE). The views expressed are
  those of the author and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR,
  the Department of Health or Public Health England.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-RCoreTeam2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>R Core Team</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</article-title>
        <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <uri>https://www.R-project.org/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-AbbottU003A2019">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Seabbs/getTBinR 0.5.8</article-title>
        <source>Zenodo</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-01">2019</year><month>01</month>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2547405</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.2547405</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-WHOU003A2018">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>World Health Organisation</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Global tuberculosis report</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-10">2018</year><month>10</month>
        <uri>https://www.who.int/tb/country/data/download/en/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-AbbottU003A2018">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Exploring estimates of the tuberculosis case fatality ratio - with getTBinR</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-02">2018</year><month>02</month>
        <uri>https://www.samabbott.co.uk/getTBinR/articles/case_fatality_rate.html</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
