<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1990</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01990</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>NCBImeta: efficient and comprehensive metadata retrieval
from NCBI databases</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-6862-7756</contrib-id>
<string-name>Katherine Eaton</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>McMaster Ancient DNA Centre, McMaster
University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Anthropology, McMaster
University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-11-29">
<day>29</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>46</issue>
<fpage>1990</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>bioinformatics</kwd>
<kwd>genomics</kwd>
<kwd>metadata</kwd>
<kwd>NCBI</kwd>
<kwd>SRA</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p><monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> is a command-line application that
  downloads and organizes biological metadata from the National Centre
  for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). While the NCBI web portal
  provides an interface for searching and filtering molecular data, the
  output offers limited options for record retrieval and comparison on a
  much larger and broader scale. <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> tackles
  this problem by creating a reformatted local database of NCBI metadata
  based on user search queries and customizable fields. The output of
  <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace>, optionally a SQLite database or text
  file(s), can then be used by computational biologists for applications
  such as record filtering, project discovery, sample interpretation,
  and meta-analyses of published work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="background">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Recent technological advances in DNA sequencing have propelled
  biological research into the realm of big data. Due to the tremendous
  output of Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) platforms, numerous fields
  have transformed to explore this novel high-throughput data. Projects
  that quickly adapted to incorporate these innovative techniques
  included monitoring the emergence of antibiotic resistance genes
  (<xref alt="Zankari et al., 2012" rid="ref-zankari_identification_2012" ref-type="bibr">Zankari
  et al., 2012</xref>), epidemic source tracking in human rights cases
  (<xref alt="Eppinger et al., 2014" rid="ref-eppinger_genomic_2014" ref-type="bibr">Eppinger
  et al., 2014</xref>), and global surveillance of uncharacterized
  organisms
  (<xref alt="Connor et al., 2015" rid="ref-connor_species-wide_2015" ref-type="bibr">Connor
  et al., 2015</xref>). However, the startling rate at which sequence
  data are being deposited online have presented significant hurdles to
  the efficient reuse of published data. In response, there is growing
  recognition within the computational community that effective data
  mining techniques are a dire necessity
  (<xref alt="Mackenzie et al., 2016" rid="ref-mackenzie_post-archival_2016" ref-type="bibr">Mackenzie
  et al., 2016</xref>;
  <xref alt="Nakazato et al., 2013" rid="ref-nakazato_experimental_2013" ref-type="bibr">Nakazato
  et al., 2013</xref>).</p>
  <p>An essential step in the data mining process is the efficient
  retrieval of comprehensive metadata. These metadata fields are diverse
  in nature, but often include the characteristics of the biological
  source material, the composition of the raw data, the objectives of
  the research initiative, and the structure of the post-processed data.
  Several software applications have been developed to facilitate bulk
  metadata retrieval from online repositories. Of the available tools,
  <monospace>SRAdb</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Zhu et al., 2013" rid="ref-zhu_sradbU003A_2013" ref-type="bibr">Zhu
  et al., 2013</xref>), the Pathogen Metadata Platform
  (<xref alt="Chang et al., 2016" rid="ref-chang_pathogen_2016" ref-type="bibr">Chang
  et al., 2016</xref>), <monospace>MetaSRA</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Bernstein et al., 2017" rid="ref-bernstein_metasraU003A_2017" ref-type="bibr">Bernstein
  et al., 2017</xref>), and <monospace>pysradb</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Choudhary, 2019" rid="ref-choudhary_pysradbU003A_2019" ref-type="bibr">Choudhary,
  2019</xref>) are among the most widely utilised and actively
  maintained. While these software extensions offer substantial
  improvements over the NCBI web browser experience, there remain
  several outstanding issues.</p>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <p>Existing tools assume external programming language proficiency
      (ex. R, Python, SQL), thus reducing tool accessibility.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Available software focuses on implementing access to singular
      NCBI databases in isolation, for example, the raw data repository
      the Sequence Read Archive (SRA). This does not empower researchers
      to incorporate evidence from multiple databases, as it fails to
      fully leverage the power of interconnected information within the
      relational database scheme of NCBI.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Existing software provides only intermittent database updates,
      where users are dependent on developers releasing new snapshots to
      gain access to the latest information. This gives researchers less
      autonomy over what data they may incorporate as newer records are
      inaccessible, and may even introduce sampling bias depending on
      when the snapshots are generated.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>In response, <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> aims to provide a more
  user-inclusive experience to metadata retrieval, that emphasizes
  real-time access and provides generalized frameworks for a wide
  variety of NCBI’s databases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ncbimeta">
  <title>NCBImeta</title>
  <p><monospace>NBCImeta</monospace> is a command-line application that
  executes user queries and metadata retrieval from the NCBI suite of
  databases. The software is written in Python 3, using the
  <monospace>BioPython</monospace> module
  (<xref alt="Cock et al., 2009" rid="ref-cock_biopythonU003A_2009" ref-type="bibr">Cock
  et al., 2009</xref>) to connect to, search, and download XML records
  with NCBI’s E-Utilities
  (<xref alt="Kans, 2019" rid="ref-kans_entrez_2019" ref-type="bibr">Kans,
  2019</xref>). The <monospace>lxml</monospace> package is utilised to
  perform XPath queries to retrieve nodes containing biological metadata
  of interest. <monospace>SQLite</monospace> is employed as the database
  management system for storing fetched records, as implemented with the
  <monospace>sqlite3</monospace> python module. Accessory scripts are
  provided to supply external annotation files, to join tables within
  the local database so as to re-create the relational database
  structure, and finally to export the database as tabular text for
  downstream analyses. <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> currently
  interfaces with the molecular and literature databases described in
  Table <xref alt="1" rid="NCBI_databases">1</xref>
  (<xref alt="Entrez Help, 2016" rid="ref-noauthor_entrez_2016" ref-type="bibr"><italic>Entrez
  Help</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p>
  <table-wrap>
    <caption>
      <p>NCBI databases supported in NCBImeta.
      <styled-content id="NCBI_databases"></styled-content></p>
    </caption>
    <table>
      <colgroup>
        <col width="22%" />
        <col width="78%" />
      </colgroup>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th><bold>Database</bold></th>
          <th><bold>Description</bold></th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Assembly</td>
          <td>Descriptions of the names and structure of genomic
          assemblies, statistical reports, and sequence data links.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>BioSample</td>
          <td>Characteristics of the biological source materials used in
          experiments.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>BioProject</td>
          <td>Goals and progress of the experimental initiatives,
          originating from an individual organization or a
          consortium.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Nucleotide</td>
          <td>Sequences collected from a variety of sources, including
          GenBank, RefSeq, TPA and PDB.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>PubMed</td>
          <td>Bibliographic information and citations for biomedical
          literature from MEDLINE, life science journals, and other
          online publications.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>SRA</td>
          <td>Composition of raw sequencing data and post-processed
          alignments generated via high-throughput sequencing
          platforms.</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </table-wrap>
  <p>The typical workflow of <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> follows
  four major steps as outlined in Figure
  <xref alt="1" rid="NCBImeta_Workflow">1</xref>. Users first configure
  the program with their desired search terms.
  <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> is then executed on the command-line
  to fetch relevant records and organize them into a local database.
  Next, the user optionally edits the database to, for example, add
  their own custom metadata. Finally, the resulting database, kept in
  SQLite format or exported to text, delivers 100+ biologically-relevant
  metadata fields to researcher’s fingertips. This process not only
  saves significant time compared to manual record retrieval through the
  NCBI web portal, but additionally unlocks attributes for comparison
  that were not easily accessible via the web-browser interface.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>NCBImeta user workflow.
    <styled-content id="NCBImeta_Workflow"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="figures/NCBImeta_Workflow.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p><monospace>NCBImeta</monospace>’s implementation offers a novel
  approach to metadata management and presentation that improves upon
  the prevously described limitations of existing software in a number
  of ways. First, <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> is run on the
  command-line, and the final database can be exported to a text file,
  thus no knowledge of an external programming language is required to
  generate or explore the output. Second, a general parsing framework
  for tables and metadata fields was developed which can be extended to
  work with diverse database types contained within NCBI’s
  infrastructure. Finally, a query system was implemented for record
  retrieval that allows users to access records in real-time, as opposed
  to working with intermittent or out-dated database snapshots.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="use-case">
  <title>Use Case</title>
  <p>The following section demonstrates how
  <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> can be used to obtain current and
  comprehensive metadata for a pathogenic bacteria, <italic>Pseudomonas
  aeruginosa</italic>, from various sequencing projects across the
  globe. <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> is an opportunistic pathogen
  associated with the disease cystic fibrosis (CF) and is highly
  adaptable to diverse ecological niches
  (<xref alt="Stewart et al., 2014" rid="ref-stewart_draft_2014" ref-type="bibr">Stewart
  et al., 2014</xref>). As such, it is a target of great interest for
  comparative genomics and there are currently over 15,000 genomic
  sequence records available which are spread across two or more
  databases. In cases such as this, it is critical to leverage the
  tremendous power of these existing datasets while being conscious of
  the labor typically required to retrieve and contextualize this
  information. <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> renders the problem of
  acquiring and sifting through this metadata trivial and facilitates
  the integration of information from multiple sources.</p>
  <p>To identify publicly available <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>
  genomes, <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> is configured to search
  through the tables <italic>Assembly</italic> (assembled genomes) and
  <italic>SRA</italic> (raw data). For additional context,
  <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> is used to retrieve metadata from the
  <italic>Nucleotide</italic> table for descriptive statistics of the
  genomic content, from the <italic>BioProject</italic> table to examine
  the research methodology of the initiative, from
  <italic>Pubmed</italic> to identify existing publications, and finally
  from the <italic>Biosample</italic> table to explore characteristics
  of the biological material. A small subset of the 100+ retrieved
  columns is shown in Figure
  <xref alt="2" rid="NCBImeta_aeruginos_db_subset">2</xref>, to provide
  a visual example of the output format and the metadata that is
  retrieved.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>A subset of the 100+ metadata columns retrieved for
    <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> sequencing projects. Viewed with DB
    Browser for SQLite (https://sqlitebrowser.org/)
    <styled-content id="NCBImeta_aeruginos_db_subset"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="figures/NCBImeta_aeruginosa_db_subset.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>Subsequently, the output of NCBImeta can be used for exploratory
  data visualization and analysis. The text file export function of
  NCBImeta ensures downstream compatibility with both user-friendly
  online tools (ex. Google Sheets Charts) as well as more advanced
  visualization packages
  (<xref alt="Wickham, 2016" rid="ref-wickham_ggplot2U003A_2016" ref-type="bibr">Wickham,
  2016</xref>). In Figure
  <xref alt="3" rid="NCBImeta_aeruginosa_geogene">3</xref>, the
  geospatial distribution of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates are
  plotted alongside key aspects of genomic composition (ex. number of
  genes).</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Metadata visualization of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>
    sequencing projects. A) The geographic distribution of samples in
    this region highlights a large number originating in Japan.
    Visualized with Palladio (https://hdlab.stanford.edu/palladio/). B)
    The number of genes per organism reveals a multi-modal distribution
    within the species.
    <styled-content id="NCBImeta_aeruginosa_geogene"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="figures/NCBImeta_aeruginosa_geogene.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>Finally, NCBImeta can be used to streamline the process of primary
  data acquisition following careful filtration. FTP links are provided
  as metadata fields for databases attached to an FTP server (ex.
  Assembly, SRA) which can be used to download biological data for
  downstream analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="future-work">
  <title>Future Work</title>
  <p>The development of <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> has primarily
  focused on a target audience of researchers whose analytical focus is
  prokaryotic genomics and the samples of interest are the organisms
  themselves. Chief among those include individuals pursuing questions
  concerning epidemiology, phylogeography, and comparative genomics.
  Future releases of <monospace>NCBImeta</monospace> will seek to
  broaden database representation to include gene-centric and
  transcriptomics research (ex. NCBI’s Gene and GEO databases).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="availability">
  <title>Availability</title>
  <p>NCBImeta is a command-line application written in Python 3 that is
  supported on Linux and macOS systems. It is distributed for use under
  the OSD-compliant MIT license (https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT).
  Source code, documentation, and example files are available on the
  GitHub repository (https://github.com/ktmeaton/NCBImeta).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>I would like to thank Dr. Hendrik Poinar and Dr. Brian Golding for
  their guidance and support on this project, as well as for insightful
  conversations regarding biological metadata, the architecture of NCBI,
  and software deployment. Thank you to Dr. Andrea Zeffiro, Dr. John
  Fink, Dr. Matthew Davis, and Dr. Amanda Montague for valuable
  discussions regarding APIs, digital project management, and software
  publishing. Thank you to all past and present members of the McMaster
  Ancient DNA Centre and the Golding Lab. This work was supported by the
  MacDATA Institute (McMaster University, Canada) and the Social
  Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada (#20008499).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-zhu_sradbU003A_2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Yuelin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>Robert M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>Paul S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Sean R</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SRAdb: Query and use public next-generation sequencing data from within R</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-09-05">2019</year><month>09</month><day>05</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>14</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>1471-2105</issn>
        <uri>http://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2105-14-19</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-14-19</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-bernstein_metasraU003A_2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>Matthew N</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Doan</surname><given-names>AnHai</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>Colin N</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MetaSRA: Normalized human sample-specific metadata for the Sequence Read Archive</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-09">2017</year><month>09</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-09-05">2019</year><month>09</month><day>05</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <issue>18</issue>
        <issn>1367-4803, 1460-2059</issn>
        <uri>https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article/33/18/2914/3848915</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btx334</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-chang_pathogen_2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Wenling E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>Matthew W.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Garay</surname><given-names>Christopher D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Korves</surname><given-names>Tonia</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pathogen metadata platform: Software for accessing and analyzing pathogen strain information</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-12">2016</year><month>12</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-09-05">2019</year><month>09</month><day>05</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>1471-2105</issn>
        <uri>http://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-016-1231-2</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-016-1231-2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-choudhary_pysradbU003A_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>Saket</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Pysradb: A Python package to query next-generation sequencing metadata and data from NCBI Sequence Read Archive</article-title>
        <source>F1000Research</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.18676.1</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.18676.1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-connor_species-wide_2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>Thomas R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>Clare R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>Kate S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weill</surname><given-names>François-Xavier</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Talukder</surname><given-names>Kaisar Ali</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Anthony M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gouali</surname><given-names>Malika</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pham Thanh</surname><given-names>Duy</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jahan Azmi</surname><given-names>Ishrat</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dias da Silveira</surname><given-names>Wanderley</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Semmler</surname><given-names>Torsten</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wieler</surname><given-names>Lothar H</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>Claire</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cravioto</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Faruque</surname><given-names>Shah M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wook Kim</surname><given-names>Dong</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Keddy</surname><given-names>Karen H</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>Nicholas R</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Species-wide whole genome sequencing reveals historical global spread and recent local persistence in Shigella flexneri</article-title>
        <source>eLife</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015-08">2015</year><month>08</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-16">2019</year><month>10</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issn>2050-084X</issn>
        <uri>https://elifesciences.org/articles/07335</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.07335</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-nakazato_experimental_2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Nakazato</surname><given-names>Takeru</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>Tazro</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bono</surname><given-names>Hidemasa</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Experimental design-based functional mining and characterization of high-throughput sequencing data in the Sequence Read Archive</article-title>
        <source>PLoS ONE</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013-10">2013</year><month>10</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-16">2019</year><month>10</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <issn>1932-6203</issn>
        <uri>https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0077910</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077910</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-mackenzie_post-archival_2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>Adrian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>Ruth</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sharples</surname><given-names>Stuart</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Post-archival genomics and the bulk logistics of DNA sequences</article-title>
        <source>BioSocieties</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-03">2016</year><month>03</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-16">2019</year><month>10</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>11</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>1745-8552, 1745-8560</issn>
        <uri>http://link.springer.com/10.1057/biosoc.2015.22</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1057/biosoc.2015.22</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-cock_biopythonU003A_2009">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Cock</surname><given-names>P. J. A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Antao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dalke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Friedberg</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hamelryck</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kauff</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilczynski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hoon</surname><given-names>M. J. L. de</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Biopython: Freely available Python tools for computational molecular biology and bioinformatics</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2009-06">2009</year><month>06</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-16">2019</year><month>10</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>25</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <issn>1367-4803, 1460-2059</issn>
        <uri>https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp163</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp163</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-stewart_draft_2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>Lewis</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sangal</surname><given-names>Vartul</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jeukens</surname><given-names>Julie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kukavica-Ibrulj</surname><given-names>Iréna</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Caim</surname><given-names>Shabhonam</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Crossman</surname><given-names>Lisa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hoskisson</surname><given-names>Paul A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>Roger</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>Nicholas P.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Draft genomes of 12 host-adapted and environmental isolates of Pseudomonas aeruginosa and their positions in the core genome phylogeny</article-title>
        <source>Pathogens and Disease</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014-06">2014</year><month>06</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-16">2019</year><month>10</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>71</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>2049632X</issn>
        <uri>https://academic.oup.com/femspd/article-lookup/doi/10.1111/2049-632X.12107</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2049-632X.12107</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-noauthor_entrez_2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <source>Entrez Help</source>
        <publisher-name>National Center for Biotechnology Information</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-17">2019</year><month>10</month><day>17</day></date-in-citation>
        <uri>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK3837/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-kans_entrez_2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kans</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Entrez Direct: E-utilities on the UNIX Command Line</article-title>
        <source>Entrez Programming Utilities Help</source>
        <publisher-name>National Center for Biotechnology Information</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-17">2019</year><month>10</month><day>17</day></date-in-citation>
        <uri>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK179288/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-zankari_identification_2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Zankari</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hasman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cosentino</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vestergaard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Aarestrup</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identification of acquired antimicrobial resistance genes</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012-11">2012</year><month>11</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-16">2019</year><month>10</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>67</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
        <issn>0305-7453, 1460-2091</issn>
        <uri>https://academic.oup.com/jac/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/jac/dks261</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dks261</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-eppinger_genomic_2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Eppinger</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>Talima</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>Sara S. K.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>Ofori</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>Nathan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>Sonia</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sanjar</surname><given-names>Fatemeh</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Galens</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>Sean</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hendriksen</surname><given-names>Rene S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>Lance B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>Bishnu P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shakya</surname><given-names>Geeta</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>Claire M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ravel</surname><given-names>Jacques</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>Paul S.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genomic epidemiology of the Haitian cholera outbreak: A single introduction followed by rapid, extensive, and continued spread characterized the onset of the epidemic</article-title>
        <source>mBio</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014-11">2014</year><month>11</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-10-16">2019</year><month>10</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <issn>2150-7511</issn>
        <uri>https://mbio.asm.org/lookup/doi/10.1128/mBio.01721-14</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01721-14</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-wickham_ggplot2U003A_2016">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <isbn>987-3-319-24277-4</isbn>
        <uri>http://ggplot2.org</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
