<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2643</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02643</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Moran Pycess: a Python package to simulate Moran
processes driven by game theory</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1361-7301</contrib-id>
<string-name>Maciej Bak</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5195-4299</contrib-id>
<string-name>Anna M. Rozlach</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Biozentrum, University of Basel</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Faculty of Biochemistry, Biophysics and Biotechnology,
Jagiellonian University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-08-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>54</issue>
<fpage>2643</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Moran Process</kwd>
<kwd>evolutionary stable strategy</kwd>
<kwd>evolutionary game theory</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Moran Pycess is a bioinformatics Python package created to simulate
  population’s growth based on evolutionary game theory and the Moran
  Process model. Growth dynamics is controlled solely by the
  interactions of individuals with each other. Our software is primarily
  targeted to evolutionary and computational biologists, however
  students who learn basic concepts behind evolution may find it equally
  practical.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>A population consists of individuals of the same species living
  simultaneously on a shared area and related to each other by a complex
  system of mutual dependencies. Population characteristics (e.g.,
  reproduction, mortality, abundance or life strategy) change over time
  as a result of evolutionary mechanisms. A complicated network of
  interactions with several degrees of freedom is very challenging for
  evolutionary biologists to decode. A simple mathematical model
  proposed by Patrick Moran is often used to describe probabilistic
  dynamics of a finite population of constant size
  (<xref alt="Moran, 1958" rid="ref-MoranU003A1958" ref-type="bibr">Moran,
  1958</xref>). Within this framework, each individual might be assigned
  with a fitness score calculated solely based on the scored
  interactions with all the other members of the group. Fitness drives
  the probability of an individual to reproduce while mutual interaction
  scores are calculated according to a common ‘payoff matrix’, treating
  the whole system as a game. In many populations the emergence of
  evolutionary stable strategy (ESS) is observed. ESS complements Nash’s
  equilibrium with an additional stability condition. A strategy is
  considered evolutionarily stable if it is resistant to an invasion of
  a small group with a different phenotype and cannot be supplanted
  (<xref alt="Maynard Smith, 1982" rid="ref-SmithU003A1982" ref-type="bibr">Maynard
  Smith, 1982</xref>). Evolutionary game theory set grounds for a solid
  framework for quantitative population biology, allowing researchers to
  simulate dynamics and estimate trajectories of biological systems.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>We have developed Moran Pycess - a Python package with a general
  game-theoretical framework for scientific simulations according to the
  Moran model. Such an approach allows the stochastic nature of
  evolution to be preserved. This is not the case for cellular automata,
  which are completely deterministic systems and where evolution of each
  cell follows some strictly defined local rules. We chose Python
  because of its availability and popularity in the fields of
  bioinformatics and data analysis. It is worth emphasizing that Moran
  Pycess is capable of carrying out simulations over 2D and 3D grid
  where individuals interact with their direct neighbours.
  Three-dimensional space is particularly important for modeling
  dynamics of population growth in cell biology
  (<xref alt="Macnamara et al., 2020" rid="ref-MacnamaraU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Macnamara
  et al., 2020</xref>). Another strength of Moran Pycess lies in its
  simplicity which turns it into a useful research aid for evolutionary
  and computational biologists. An open source license as well as its
  accessibility recommend Moran Pycess as a practical tool for biology,
  economics and math students to learn about population evolution based
  on game theory or for computer science students aiming to properly
  package their research software. A remarkable advantage of our module
  is that any possible model of an antagonistic game may be considered.
  In terms of quality assurance: our repository incorporates Travis CI
  mechanism alongside Coveralls code coverage measurement (currently:
  100%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="state-of-the-field">
  <title>State of the field</title>
  <p>In principle, such computations could be recreated within DEAP - a
  framework dedicated to genetic and evolutionary algorithms
  (<xref alt="Fortin et al., 2012" rid="ref-FortinU003A2012" ref-type="bibr">Fortin
  et al., 2012</xref>). However, these simulations would not be as
  straightforward to implement in DEAP as in Moran Pycess. Due to its
  complexity, DEAP is more suitable for users with more sophisticated
  software engineering skills. Notably, another powerful Python package
  - Axelrod - is limited to Prisoners’ Dilemma, while Moran Pycess
  allows to model evolution of cooperation in various strategies
  (<xref alt="The Axelrod project developers, 2016" rid="ref-axelrodproject" ref-type="bibr">The
  Axelrod project developers, 2016</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="example-results">
  <title>Example results</title>
  <p>We have designed four distinct systems based on well-known
  interaction examples which have been well-described in the literature
  (<xref alt="Tadelis, 2012" rid="ref-TadelisU003A2012" ref-type="bibr">Tadelis,
  2012</xref>).</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Simulations of population evolution based on: (A) Stag
    Hunt (B) Chicken game, (C) Prisoners’ Dilemma, (D) Rock Paper
    Scissors.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/figure.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <list list-type="alpha-upper">
    <list-item>
      <label>(A)</label>
      <p>The Stag Hunt game model describes a conflict between safety
      and social cooperation: the hare hunt represents small but certain
      profit, the stag hunt, great benefit but at great risk. Failure in
      cooperation leads to a player’s loss. There is no dominant
      strategy in this game as it is most beneficial for individuals to
      agree on the same strategy. Both stag hunt and hare hunt are
      evolutionarily stable strategies. A perfect example of this type
      of interaction is the “carousel feeding” behavior, a cooperative
      hunting method used by Norwegian orcas which forces a school of
      fish to form a tight ball; the orcas then stun fish with their
      tails
      (<xref alt="Fort, 2007" rid="ref-FortU003A2007" ref-type="bibr">Fort,
      2007</xref>).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>(B)</label>
      <p>In the game of Chicken a confrontational strategy brings a
      greater profit. However, if chosen by both individuals it yields
      the worst outcome. A peaceful strategy, while protecting against
      the greatest possible loss brings no reward when challenged by an
      aggressor. No player has a dominant strategy and there are no ESS
      in pure strategies in this game. Consider an example of two
      strains of the yeasts S. cerevisiae: wildtype and a mutant lacking
      the invertase gene. In a monosaccharide-poor environment yeasts
      may utilise invertase to produce an energy source from more
      complex molecules. Most monosaccharides are excreted to the
      extracellular environment from where they can also be taken up by
      other cells. Mutant strains (“cheaters”) follow a confrontational
      strategy: they consume glucose created by wildtype cells without
      bearing the metabolic cost of invertase production and secretion.
      Therefore, in a population, a confrontational strategy has a good
      advantage over the peaceful one, given the number of wildtype
      yeasts exceeds the number of mutants vastly. In case this
      condition is not met cheaters would fail to live off the others,
      leading to starvation - the worst possible scenario for them.
      Moreover, the analogy holds while inspecting the behaviour of
      wildtype yeasts. Trying to avoid that worst scenario, in the
      presence of mutants, wildtype cells cooperate in invertase
      expression over a wide range of conditions. However, when
      competing against other wildtype strains, invertase expression is
      repressed, causing them to exhibit the confrontational strategy -
      cheat.
      (<xref alt="Gore et al., 2009" rid="ref-GoreU003A2009" ref-type="bibr">Gore
      et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>(C)</label>
      <p>Prisoners’ dilemma, often analyzed in game theory due to its
      multiple applications, presents a case where two completely
      rational individuals within incomplete knowledge might not
      cooperate, even if it appears that it is in their best interests
      to do so. The most rational strategy yields the worst collective
      outcome. Every participant has a dominant strategy. The only ESS
      is to always cooperate. In biological context the prisoner’s
      dilemma successfully captures the essential features of cancer
      growth and provides a framework for testing hypotheses and
      formulating claims in a quantitative manner
      (<xref alt="West et al., 2016" rid="ref-WestU003A2016" ref-type="bibr">West
      et al., 2016</xref>). In the case of malignant tumors, we observe
      the possibility of infiltration of adjacent tissues by cancer
      cells. Their characteristic uncontrolled proliferation leads to
      the growth of another tumor in this place and the destruction of
      healthy tissue.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <label>(D)</label>
      <p>Rock-Paper-Scissors is a game with cyclic dominance resulting
      in oscillating populations of individuals among types. There is no
      ESS in this game. As an example, consider male side-blotched
      lizards, which come in three color morphs: orange, yellow, and
      blue. The orange males defend large territories. The yellow males
      can invade orange males’ territories. The blue male, in turn,
      effectively expels yellow males from their territory but are
      outcompeted by aggressive orange males.
      (<xref alt="Sinervo &amp; Lively, 1996" rid="ref-SinevroU003A1996" ref-type="bibr">Sinervo
      &amp; Lively, 1996</xref>). As a result: yellow beats orange,
      which bests blue which beats yellow.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="supplementary-data-stochastic-nature-of-the-simulations">
  <title>Supplementary data: Stochastic nature of the
  simulations</title>
  <p>To demonstrate the stochastic nature of the simulations let us
  consider a Hawk-Dove model where the resources value is only slightly
  higher than the confrontational cost. A small group of hawks, having
  an ESS, try to invade a larger community of doves. However, if the
  initial number of predators is too low their advantage might not be
  sufficient for them to overtake the whole population.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Replicated simulations of evolution according to the
    Hawk-Dove model: (A) 5 hawks invade a group of 95 doves: 5/10 times
    the population is overtaken by the invaders, (B) 15 hawks invade a
    group of 85 doves: 10/10 times the population is overtaken by the
    invaders.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/supplementary_figureA1.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-MoranU003A1958">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>P. A. P.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Random processes in genetics</article-title>
        <source>Mathematical Proceedings of the Cambridge Philosophical Society</source>
        <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1958">1958</year>
        <volume>54</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0305004100033193</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SmithU003A1982">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Maynard Smith</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Evolution and the theory of games</source>
        <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1982">1982</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/CBO9780511806292</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-FortinU003A2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>Félix-Antoine</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>De Rainville</surname><given-names>François-Michel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Parizeau</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gagné</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>DEAP: Evolutionary algorithms made easy</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Machine Learning Research, Machine Learning Open Source Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012-07">2012</year><month>07</month>
        <volume>13</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"></pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-MacnamaraU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Macnamara</surname><given-names>Cicely</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Caiazzo</surname><given-names>Alfonso</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ramis-Conde</surname><given-names>Ignacio</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chaplain</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Computational modelling and simulation of cancer growth and migration within a 3D heterogeneous tissue: The effects of fibre and vascular structure</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Computational Science</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-12">2020</year><month>12</month>
        <volume>40</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocs.2019.101067</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-axelrodproject">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>The Axelrod project developers</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Axelrod-python/axelrod: v4.10.0</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-04">2016</year><month>04</month>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3980654</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.3980654</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-TadelisU003A2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Tadelis</surname><given-names>Steaven</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Game theory: An introduction</source>
        <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi"></pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-FortU003A2007">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>Hugo</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Evolving ecological social dilemmas: A spatial individual-based model for the evolution of cooperation with a minimal number of parameters</article-title>
        <source>Research Letters in Ecology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007-11">2007</year><month>11</month>
        <volume>2007</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2007/18636</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-GoreU003A2009">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>Jeff</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Youk</surname><given-names>Hyun</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oudenaarden</surname><given-names>Alexander van</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Snowdrift game dynamics and facultative cheating in yeast</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2009-04">2009</year><month>04</month>
        <volume>459</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07921</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-WestU003A2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>West</surname><given-names>Jeffrey</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hasnain</surname><given-names>Zaki</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Macklin</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>Paul K.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An evolutionary model of tumor cell kinetics and the emergence of molecular heterogeneity driving gompertzian growth</article-title>
        <source>Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-11">2016</year><month>11</month>
        <volume>58,4</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/15M1044825</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SinevroU003A1996">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Sinervo</surname><given-names>Barry</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lively</surname><given-names>Curtis</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The rock-paper-scissors game and the evolution of alternative male strategies</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1996-03">1996</year><month>03</month>
        <volume>380</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/380240a0</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
