<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1201</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01201</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>TraitDB: Web application database of phenotypic trait
data.</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3221-9579</contrib-id>
<string-name>Dan Leehr</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Mercedes Gosby</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>National Evolutionary Synthesis Center</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-07-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>36</issue>
<fpage>1201</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>trait</kwd>
<kwd>rails</kwd>
<kwd>csv</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>TraitDB is a web application that synthesizes phenotypic trait
  datasets from varying structures and formats. It organizes data into a
  consistent format and taxonomy, facilitating querying, subsetting, and
  sharing over a range of user criteria. While many other software
  packages exist to store structured and unstructured relational data,
  TraitDB is designed to meet the needs of research teams by fitting
  into their data gathering practices. Commonly-used packages like
  spreadsheets and SQL databases may excel at direct ingest, storage,
  and management of homogeneous datasets, but fall short dealing with
  real-world heterogenous data structures and formats. They require
  dedicated effort to build and adapt complex processes in order to
  maintain data integrity.</p>
  <p>Through work with multiple
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nescent.org/">NESCent</ext-link>
  working groups, we observed and supported real-world efforts to build
  a database of traits by collecting and organizing thousands of trait
  data observations. We evaluated software including
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://openrefine.org/">OpenRefine</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/sqlite-manager-webext/">SQLite
  Manager</ext-link>, and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mx3/mx">mx</ext-link>
  that aim to address many of these challenges.</p>
  <p>While these software are capable of enforcing complex data models,
  we found that individual researchers were most productive tabulating
  data from specimens or literature into local spreadsheets rather than
  an online application. At this level, they needed frictionless data
  entry of the records they had available, rather than tedious
  interactions. After collecting their data, they needed a robust
  process to validate, reconcile, and ingest records into the larger
  body.</p>
  <p>Through collaboration, and iteration, we designed and built TraitDB
  to serve the use cases of these researchers. Primarily, TraitDB aids
  ingest of datasets from different researchers working to synthesize a
  single, uniform dataset. Data ingest is driven by a flexible YAML
  template system, managed by the group of researchers. The process
  provides validation and observation-level feedback on input CSV
  datasets. It indicates which fields are required, warns of duplicate
  records, and performs validation on categorical and continuous
  variables. Prior to ingesting the data, TraitDB provides a structured
  report of warnings and requires that any errors are corrected.</p>
  <p>Once ingested, TraitDB provides several mechanisms for querying,
  browsing, subsetting, and fetching data via its web interface. It
  implements simple summary calculations of trait data over taxonomic
  levels, and provides CSV download of synthesized datasets for further
  analysis.</p>
  <p>TraitDB has been used to gather and produce datasets hosted by the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bbrowse.biol.berkeley.edu/treeV2/styled/index.html">Tree
  of Sex</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>TraitDB is a project of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nescent.org/">National
  Evolutionary Synthesis Center</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
