<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1473</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01473</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>cde - R package to retrieve data from the Environment
Agency Catchment Data Explorer site</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0341-1203</contrib-id>
<string-name>Robert A Briers</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>School of Applied Sciences, Edinburgh Napier
University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-05-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>39</issue>
<fpage>1473</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>water quality</kwd>
<kwd>Water Framework Directive</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Globally, issues around water quality and quantity are expected to
  increase in coming decades, set against a background of already
  widespread degradation
  (<xref alt="WWAP - United Nations World Water Assessment Programme/UN-Water, 2018" rid="ref-WWAPUnitedNationsWorldWaterAssessmentProgramme2018" ref-type="bibr">WWAP
  - United Nations World Water Assessment Programme/UN-Water,
  2018</xref>). Within Europe, the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/water/water-framework/">Water
  Framework Directive</ext-link> (WFD) set EU-wide standards for how the
  quality of surface waters and groundwater across Europe is assessed
  and classified
  (<xref alt="European Commission, 2000" rid="ref-Communities2000" ref-type="bibr">European
  Commission, 2000</xref>). Assessment of quality under the WFD is based
  on a range of elements that vary depending on the type of water being
  assessed. The elements cover biological, chemical and
  hydromorphological/quantitative components with a hierarchical
  structure. These are combined to give an overall classification of
  waterbodies into five classes (High, Good, Moderate, Poor and Bad) for
  surface waters and two classes (Good or Poor) for groundwaters. The
  overall aim of the WFD is that all European surface waters and
  groundwater will reach at least Good status by 2027, although there
  have been a number of issues with implementation
  (<xref alt="Voulvoulis et al., 2017" rid="ref-Voulvoulis2017" ref-type="bibr">Voulvoulis
  et al., 2017</xref>).</p>
  <p>In the UK, the Environment Agency (EA) is the competent authority
  responsible for monitoring and assessment of water quality within
  England. The EA have made all of the reporting data relating to the
  requirements of the WFD available via the Catchment Data Explorer
  (CDE) website
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://environment.data.gov.uk/catchment-planning/">https://environment.data.gov.uk/catchment-planning/</ext-link>.
  The <monospace>cde</monospace> package for R
  (<xref alt="R Core Team, 2019" rid="ref-RCoreTeam2019" ref-type="bibr">R
  Core Team, 2019</xref>) provides functions that facilitate the
  querying, download and plotting of the data available on the CDE site.
  The ability to access these data from within the R environment allows
  for efficient collation and interrogation of data and reproducible
  analysis of trends or patterns in water quality and pressures on
  waterbodies across England. There are also some inconsistencies in the
  way in which the data are structured within the original CDE website;
  <monospace>cde</monospace> provides consistently named and structured
  output which facilitates further analysis.</p>
  <p>The package allows users to search for waterbodies, catchments or
  River Basin Districts that match given search strings. Having
  identified the relevant sites, the following types of data can be
  downloaded:</p>
  <p><italic>Status classification</italic>: either for overall
  waterbody classification or at a range of more detailed levels
  relating to specific quality elements (e.g., ecological, chemical or
  priority substances). These can be downloaded for specified year
  ranges and for specific waterbody types (such as lakes).</p>
  <p><italic>Reasons for Not Achieving Good status</italic>: for
  catchments or River Basin Districts where there are waterbodies that
  have not achieved Good status, the package provides the functionality
  to download a summary of the Reasons for Not Achieving Good (RNAG)
  data. This gives a range of information regarding the relevant
  pressures identified as contributing to the current status, classified
  according to a standard hierarchy given on the CDE website.</p>
  <p><italic>Objectives for waterbodies</italic>: where less than Good
  status has been achieved, data on the objectives that have been set in
  terms of status aimed for in the longer term can be downloaded, for
  specific target years and for specified levels of classification.</p>
  <p><italic>Measures to achieve objectives</italic>: details of actions
  that have been put in place or are proposed to achieve the objectives
  set (currently in relation to the target objective set for 2021). Only
  data linked to the achievement of a specific outcome in terms of
  status are included.</p>
  <p><italic>Protected areas</italic>: a summary of associated protected
  areas (such as Special Areas of Conservation or Nitrate Vulnerable
  Zones), again at a range of levels from individual waterbodies to
  whole River Basin Districts.</p>
  <p>For each of the types of data that can be downloaded, summary plots
  can also be produced. These differ depending on the type of data, but
  an example showing the percentage of water bodies in each status class
  (derived from the <monospace>get_status</monospace> function) is shown
  in Figure 1.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>A plot of status classification data for the Lark
    Operational Catchment between 2013 and 2015</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="lark%20plot-1.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>Thanks to Matt Starr of the EA and Dave Reynolds of Epimorphics Ltd
  for useful discussions about the CDE API and providing a full site
  listing to help development.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Communities2000">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>European Commission</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Directive 2000/60/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council establishing a framework for the Community action in the field of water policy</article-title>
        <source>Official Journal of the European Communities</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year>
        <volume>L 327</volume>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-WWAPUnitedNationsWorldWaterAssessmentProgramme2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="report">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>WWAP - United Nations World Water Assessment Programme/UN-Water</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The United Nations World Water Development Report 2018: Nature-Based Solutions for Water</article-title>
        <publisher-name>UNSECO</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <isbn>9789231002649</isbn>
        <uri>https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000261424</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Voulvoulis2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Voulvoulis</surname><given-names>Nikolaos</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Arpon</surname><given-names>Karl Dominic</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Giakoumis</surname><given-names>Theodoros</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The EU Water Framework Directive: From great expectations to problems with implementation</article-title>
        <source>Science of The Total Environment</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017-01">2017</year><month>01</month>
        <volume>575</volume>
        <issn>0048-9697</issn>
        <uri>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S004896971632157X</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.SCITOTENV.2016.09.228</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-RCoreTeam2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>R Core Team</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</article-title>
        <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <uri>https://www.R-project.org/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
