<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2674</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02674</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>pd-parser: A tool for Matching Photodiode Deflection
Events to Time-Stamped Events</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3868-7453</contrib-id>
<string-name>Alexander P. Rockhill,</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8421-7105</contrib-id>
<string-name>Ahmed M. Raslan</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2463-5134</contrib-id>
<string-name>Nicole C. Swann</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Oregon, Department of Human Physiology,
Eugene, Oregon.</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Neurological Surgery, Oregon Health &amp;
Science University, Portland, Oregon.</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>54</issue>
<fpage>2674</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>neuroscience</kwd>
<kwd>electrophysiology</kwd>
<kwd>psychology</kwd>
<kwd>behavior</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Precise synchronization of events displayed on a monitor to
  recordings of time series data is critical for applications such as
  vision or psychophysics research. To achieve this, researchers often
  use a photodiode to convert the luminance on a monitor over time into
  a voltage time course, which is what is recorded.
  <monospace>pd-parser</monospace> matches photodiode deflection events
  to time-stamped events; it is particularly useful when the photodiode
  signal is corrupted or there is drift between the clock of the
  computer controlling the monitor and the data acquisition computer
  clock.</p>
  <p>To do this, <monospace>pd-parser</monospace> first extracts
  photodiode time series data from an electrophysiology data file.
  <monospace>pd-parser</monospace> uses
  <monospace>mne-python</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Gramfort et al., 2013" rid="ref-Agramfort2013" ref-type="bibr">Gramfort
  et al., 2013</xref>) for input/output. The photodiode data can be on a
  single channel or two channels that are then bipolar re-referenced.
  Candidate photodiode events from this photodiode time series are
  identified based on matching a square-wave template.</p>
  <p>Time-stamped events from the computer that triggers changes to the
  luminance of the photodiode are read from a tab-separated value (tsv)
  file, and the best alignment of these events relative to photodiode
  deflection events is then found while accounting for any drift between
  computer clocks of separate recording devices like in
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="figU003Atrend">Figure 1</xref>. The success
  of the alignment can be determined from a plot of event differences;
  <xref alt="Figure 3" rid="figU003Aexclude">Figure 3</xref>. When
  almost all of the events match within around 30 ms, the alignment is
  assumed to be correct as this is extremely unlikely to happen by
  chance. This discrepancy in timing can occur when a monitor doesn’t
  update the display for one or more frames; this is most often because
  the computer paused execution of the program controlling luminance to
  do background tasks.</p>
  <p>After the photodiode events are found, additional events can be
  added using the time of each event relative to the corresponding
  photodiode-synchronized event. Adding relative events may be needed
  for any number of reasons. For instance, events may occur too rapidly
  in series relative to the monitor refresh rate to have a photodiode
  deflection for each event, or the photodiode deflection may affect
  neighboring channels on the amplifier. In the latter case, an event
  that is not analyzed, such as a fixation stimulus, can be chosen to
  synchronize the photodiode so that other, more important events will
  not be contaminated by a photodiode deflection.</p>
  <p>Finally, the raw data and events data can be saved in brain imaging
  data structure (BIDS) format, which allows the behavioral events to be
  stored in a standardized format without modifying the underlying raw
  electrophysiology file.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p><italic>An Example of Computer Clock Drift</italic>. The
    difference between each time-stamped event and the nearest
    photodiode event with the first time-stamped and photodiode events
    correctly aligned. There is a positive linear trend due to the
    difference in timekeeping of the photodiode recording computer
    compared to the time-stamp-generating computer. Note that although
    the general linear trend is most apparent, the smaller trends are
    still large enough to also cause misalignment and so need to be
    accounted for.
    <styled-content id="figU003Atrend"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="docsrc/figs/pd_trend.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p><italic>An Example of Event Differences</italic>. An
    example of the differences between the photodiode deflection event
    and the time-stamped event aligned to it, excluding events that were
    not matched or that were matched but the difference was too much, as
    shown in <xref alt="Figure 3" rid="figU003Aexclude">Figure 3</xref>.
    As can be observed in the figure, the alignments are much closer
    than would likely happen by chance, giving confidence that the fit
    of the events was correct.
    <styled-content id="figU003Adiffs"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="docsrc/figs/event_diffs.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p><italic>An Example of Excluded Events</italic>. An
    example of the excluded events from 300 time-stamped events
    synchronized to photodiode deflection events is shown. The threshold
    of exclusion can be set to include all the events except those where
    no event was found, but from inspecting
    <xref alt="Figure 2" rid="figU003Adiffs">Figure 2</xref>, the
    difference plot, these event differences are subjectively outliers.
    Trials where no event was found can be recovered manually when the
    pre-event baseline, plateau, or post-event baseline was corrupted
    but photodiode onset or offset was not.
    <styled-content id="figU003Aexclude"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="docsrc/figs/excluded_events.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>To our knowledge, there are no software packages that extract
  photodiode events and align them with event time-stamps, despite the
  widespread use of photodiodes for task timing. By sensing luminance,
  photodiodes can synchronize recording systems with high temporal
  precision. For example, the timing of events in behavioral tasks
  displayed on a laptop can be synchronized to electrophysiological
  recordings. While many research systems are specially designed to
  record triggers that link recordings from separate machines directly,
  other recording systems, especially clinical systems, lack this
  capability. In these cases, use of a photodiode offers a robust and
  reliable method for synchronization.</p>
  <p>We developed this software package to address our need to
  synchronize task events with intracranial recordings acquired in the
  epilepsy monitoring unit. Here electrophysiology was acquired using a
  clinical system and a behavioral task was performed using a laptop
  brought to the patient’s bedside. A photodiode, placed on the monitor
  of the laptop, was used to detect task-related luminance changes. The
  photodiode recording was gain adjusted before its signal was passed to
  the amplifier using two channels that were later bipolar referenced.
  In this setup, the photodiode was digitized by the same clinical
  recording system which was used for the electrophysiology
  recordings.</p>
  <p>Due to variability in refresh rates for monitors, the use of
  photodiodes is especially helpful for research where precision timing
  of the display is critical, for example vision or psychophysics
  research. This software package addresses photodiode synchronization
  in a comprehensive way so that photodiode parsing can be done by
  flexibly changing key parameters, which avoids writing entirely new
  scripts. This reduces the inefficiency caused by needing to make an
  algorithm for each particular situation, and reduces the potential for
  errors by testing a broad array of situations thoroughly.</p>
  <p><monospace>pd_parser</monospace> handles complex photodiode parsing
  for all setups, making it a one-size-fits-all tool for research using
  photodiode synchronization. Ideal photodiode signals (with minimal
  noise or drift and clear deflections) would not require a complex
  algorithm, but in actual experimental setups, photodiode signals are
  often unideal. This is especially true in clinical settings where
  elements of the environment may be outside of experimenter control.
  Often the baseline value of photodiode changes over time, the plateaus
  of photodiode events trend back toward baseline and overshoot after
  deflection cessation and artifacts contaminate the photodiode signal.
  These artifacts can be caused by movement of the photodiode device,
  changes in the room lighting, hospital equipment or any number of
  other contaminants. This package has robust photodiode
  event-determination and photodiode to time-stamp alignment algorithms
  that are validated with both real and simulated photodiode data.</p>
  <p>The parameters to parse a photodiode channel can be unique to the
  particular setup (how long the photodiode is on, what the inter-event
  interval is and what the amplitude of the on period compared to the
  baseline is), which can be found with an interactive graphical user
  interface (GUI) if the default parameters do not work.
  <monospace>pd-parser</monospace> can accommodate synchronizing a
  multi-event task based on one photodiode event channel, with all other
  events relative to that event, or multiple photodiodes corresponding
  to separate events, or one photodiode used to synchronize multiple
  events on the same channel so long as they do not overlap.</p>
  <p>Existing (unpublished) algorithms are generally written for
  specific projects and lack flexibility, leading to the creation of
  redundant algorithms. These algorithms tend to lack broad and thorough
  testing and are vulnerable to coding errors because of the
  inefficiency of making the algorithm anew for each project. Not only
  does <monospace>pd-parser</monospace> offer this flexibility but it
  also serves as a forum where new issues can be identified and
  addressed by the <monospace>pd-parser</monospace> community so that
  they can be fixed once for all groups.</p>
  <p>Finally, <monospace>pd-parser</monospace> integrates with BIDS
  (<xref alt="Gorgolewski et al., 2016" rid="ref-Gorgolewski2016" ref-type="bibr">Gorgolewski
  et al., 2016</xref>;
  <xref alt="Holdgraf et al., 2019" rid="ref-Holdgraf2019" ref-type="bibr">Holdgraf
  et al., 2019</xref>;
  <xref alt="Niso et al., 2018" rid="ref-Niso2018" ref-type="bibr">Niso
  et al., 2018</xref>;
  <xref alt="Pernet et al., 2019" rid="ref-Pernet2019" ref-type="bibr">Pernet
  et al., 2019</xref>) using <monospace>mne-bids</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Appelhoff et al., 2019" rid="ref-Appelhoff2019" ref-type="bibr">Appelhoff
  et al., 2019</xref>) to store the extracted event data in a
  standardized data structure improving the reproducibility of the
  project using photodiode data. The well-tested instructions,
  Application Programming Interface (API) and Command Line Interface
  (CLI) make <monospace>pd-parser</monospace> easy to use and encourage
  both careful photodiode synchronization and adoption of the BIDS
  community standard.</p>
  <p>Without careful consideration of the early, low-level steps, such
  as photodiode synchronization, potential errors could be carried
  forward in subsequent, more complex analyses, potentially resulting in
  incorrect conclusions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We acknowledge support from the Renée James Seed grant to
  Accelerate Scientific Research from University of Oregon and NIH/NIMH
  R21: 1RF1MH117155-01 (Site PI, subcontract) 9/1/19 – 8/31/22 “From ion
  channel dynamics to human EEG and MEG: multiscale neuronal models
  validated by human data”.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Gorgolewski2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gorgolewski</surname><given-names>Krzysztof J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Auer</surname><given-names>Tibor</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>Vince D</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Craddock</surname><given-names>R Cameron</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>Samir</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>Eugene P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Flandin</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>Satrajit S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Glatard</surname><given-names>Tristan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Halchenko</surname><given-names>Yaroslav O</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Handwerker</surname><given-names>Daniel A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hanke</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Keator</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xiangrui</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>Zachary</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Maumet</surname><given-names>Camille</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>B Nolan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>Thomas E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pellman</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Poline</surname><given-names>Jean-Baptiste</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rokem</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>Gunnar</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sochat</surname><given-names>Vanessa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Triplett</surname><given-names>William</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>Jessica A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Varoquaux</surname><given-names>Gaël</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Poldrack</surname><given-names>Russell A</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The brain imaging data structure, a format for organizing and describing outputs of neuroimaging experiments</article-title>
        <source>Scientific Data</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-06">2016</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>3</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sdata.2016.44</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Agramfort2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gramfort</surname><given-names>Alexandre</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Luessi</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Engemann</surname><given-names>Denis A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Strohmeier</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brodbeck</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Goj</surname><given-names>Roman</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jas</surname><given-names>Mainak</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>Teon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Parkkonen</surname><given-names>Lauri</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hämäläinen</surname><given-names>Matti</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MEG and EEG data analysis with MNE-python</article-title>
        <source>Frontiers in Neuroscience</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013-12">2013</year><month>12</month>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2013.00267</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Niso2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Niso</surname><given-names>Guiomar</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gorgolewski</surname><given-names>Krzysztof J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>Teon L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Flandin</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gramfort</surname><given-names>Alexandre</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>Richard N</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jas</surname><given-names>Mainak</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Litvak</surname><given-names>Vladimir</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>Jeremy T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oostenveld</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schoffelen</surname><given-names>Jan-Mathijs</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tadel</surname><given-names>Francois</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wexler</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baillet</surname><given-names>Sylvain</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MEG-BIDS, the brain imaging data structure extended to magnetoencephalography</article-title>
        <source>Scientific Data</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-06">2018</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sdata.2018.110</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Pernet2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Pernet</surname><given-names>Cyril R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Appelhoff</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gorgolewski</surname><given-names>Krzysztof J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Flandin</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>Christophe</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>Arnaud</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oostenveld</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>EEG-BIDS, an extension to the brain imaging data structure for electroencephalography</article-title>
        <source>Scientific Data</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-06">2019</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-019-0104-8</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Holdgraf2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Holdgraf</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Appelhoff</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bickel</surname><given-names>Stephan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bouchard</surname><given-names>Kristofer</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>D’Ambrosio</surname><given-names>Sasha</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>David</surname><given-names>Oliver</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Devinsky</surname><given-names>Orrin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dichter</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Flinker</surname><given-names>Adeen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>Brett L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gorgolewski</surname><given-names>Krzysztof J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>Iris</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Groppe</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gunduz</surname><given-names>Aysegul</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Liberty</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Honey</surname><given-names>Christpher J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jas</surname><given-names>Mainak</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lachaux</surname><given-names>Jean-Philippe</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>Jonathan C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lee-Messer</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lundstrom</surname><given-names>Brian N</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Kai J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ojemann</surname><given-names>Jeffrey G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oostenveld</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Petridou</surname><given-names>Natalia</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Piantoni</surname><given-names>Gio</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pigorini</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pouratian</surname><given-names>Nader</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>Nick F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stolk</surname><given-names>Arjen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Swann</surname><given-names>Nicole C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tadel</surname><given-names>Francois</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Voytek</surname><given-names>Bradley</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wandell</surname><given-names>Brian A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Winawer</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>Kristie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zehl</surname><given-names>Lyuba</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hermes</surname><given-names>Dora</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>iEEG-BIDS, extending the brain imaging data structure to human intracranial electrophysiology</article-title>
        <source>Scientific Data</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-06">2019</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-019-0105-7</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Appelhoff2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Appelhoff</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>Teon L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vliet</surname><given-names>Marijn van</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Quentin</surname><given-names>Romain</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Holdgraf</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chaumon</surname><given-names>Maximilien</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mikulan</surname><given-names>Ezequiel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tavabi</surname><given-names>Kambiz</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Höchenberger</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Welke</surname><given-names>Dominik</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>Clemens</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rockhill</surname><given-names>Alexander P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gramfort</surname><given-names>Alexandre</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jas</surname><given-names>Mainak</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MNE-BIDS: Organizing electrophysiological data into the BIDS format and facilitating their analysis</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
        <publisher-name>The Open Journal</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>4</volume>
        <issue>44</issue>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01896</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01896</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
