<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2436</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02436</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>CancerSim: A Cancer Simulation Package for Python
3</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-7595-1722</contrib-id>
<string-name>Luka Opasic</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2971-7673</contrib-id>
<string-name>Jacob G. Scott</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-0669-5267</contrib-id>
<string-name>Arne Traulsen</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-2579-5546</contrib-id>
<string-name>Carsten Fortmann-Grote</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Max-Planck-Institute for Evolutionary Biology, Plön,
Germany</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH, US</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-03-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>53</issue>
<fpage>2436</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>stochastic simulation</kwd>
<kwd>tumour growth</kwd>
<kwd>tumour sampling</kwd>
<kwd>cancer biology</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Cancer is a group of complex diseases characterized by excessive
  cell proliferation, invasion, and destruction of the surrounding
  tissue
  (<xref alt="Vinay Kumar, 2017" rid="ref-Kumar2017" ref-type="bibr">Vinay
  Kumar, 2017</xref>). Its high division and mutation rates lead to
  excessive genetic diversity among tumour cells (intra tumour genetic
  heterogeneity). As a consequence, tumours can adapt very efficiently
  to environmental pressures, in particular to cancer therapy
  (<xref alt="Turajlic et al., 2019" rid="ref-Turajlic2019" ref-type="bibr">Turajlic
  et al., 2019</xref>). This process is known as somatic evolution of
  cancer.</p>
  <p>Throughout most of its existence a tumour is inaccessible to direct
  observation and experimental evaluation through genetic sequencing of
  tumour samples. Therefore, computational modelling can be useful to
  study many aspects of cancer. Examples where theoretical models can be
  of great use include (i) early carcinogenesis, as lesions are
  clinically observable when they already contain millions of cells,
  (ii) seeding of metastases, and (iii) cancer cell dormancy
  (<xref alt="Altrock et al., 2015" rid="ref-Altrock2015" ref-type="bibr">Altrock
  et al., 2015</xref>).</p>
  <sec id="statement-of-need">
    <title>Statement of Need</title>
    <p>Advanced cancer simulation software
    (<xref alt="Waclaw et al., 2015" rid="ref-waclaw2015" ref-type="bibr">Waclaw
    et al., 2015</xref>) often exhibit a prohibitively steep learning
    curve especially for new students in the field of somatic evolution
    of cancer. A software package that is accessible, simple to use, and
    yet covers the essential biological processes of cancer growth is
    needed to provide an entry point for students and newcomers to
    mathematical oncology.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="cancer-growth-model">
    <title>Cancer growth model</title>
    <p>Here we present <monospace>CancerSim</monospace>, a software that
    simulates somatic evolution of tumours. The software produces
    virtual spatial tumours with variable extent of intra tumour genetic
    heterogeneity and realistic mutational profiles (i.e., the order of
    appearance of mutations and their distribution among tumour cells).
    Simulated tumours can be virtually sampled at random or in specified
    positions. By binning the frequency of mutations in each sample and
    convolving the resulting histogram with a beta-binomial distribution
    to add realistic sequencing noise
    (<xref alt="Williams et al., 2016" rid="ref-Williams2016" ref-type="bibr">Williams
    et al., 2016</xref>), the simulation produces mutation profiles from
    different tumour regions. This makes the software useful for
    studying various sampling strategies in clinical cancer diagnostics
    such as needle biopsy sampling or liquid biopsy sampling. An early
    version of this cancer evolution model was used to simulate tumours
    subjected to sampling for classification of mutations based on their
    abundance
    (<xref alt="Opasic et al., 2019" rid="ref-Opasic2019" ref-type="bibr">Opasic
    et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
    <p>Our model is abstract, not specific to any neoplasm type, and
    does not consider a variety of biological features commonly found in
    the neoplasm, such as blood vessels, immune cells, nutrient
    availability, and architecture of the tumour surroundings. It
    resembles the most superficially spreading tumours like carcinoma
    <italic>in-situ</italic>, skin cancers, or gastric cancers, but it
    can be used to model any tumour on this abstract level.</p>
    <p>The tumour is simulated using a two-dimensional, on-lattice,
    agent-based model. The tumour lattice structure is established by a
    sparse matrix whose non-zero elements correspond to the individual
    cells. Each cell is surrounded by eight neighbouring cells (Moore
    neighbourhood). The value of the matrix element is an index pointing
    to the last mutation the cell acquired in the list of mutations
    which is updated in each simulation step.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="simulation-parameters">
    <title>Simulation parameters</title>
    <p>The simulation advances in discrete time-steps. In each
    simulation step, every tumour cell on the lattice that has an
    unoccupied neighbour can divide with a certain probability
    (controlled through the parameter
    <monospace>division_probability</monospace>). The daughter cell
    resulting from a cell division inherits all mutations from the
    parent cell and acquires a new mutation with a given probability
    (<monospace>mutation_probability</monospace>). A new mutation that
    changes death and/or birth probabilities can be introduced into a
    random cell at a specific time step defined by
    <monospace>adv_mutation_wait_time</monospace>. By changing the
    fitness parameters of a mutant cell
    <monospace>adv_mutant_division_probability</monospace> and
    <monospace>adv_mutant_death_probability</monospace> one can model
    various evolutionary processes like emergence of a faster dividing
    sub-clone or selective effects of drug treatment.</p>
    <p>The simulation allows the acquisition of more than one mutational
    event per cell
    (<monospace>number_of_mutations_per_division</monospace>). In that
    case, variable amounts of sequencing noise
    (<xref alt="Williams et al., 2016" rid="ref-Williams2016" ref-type="bibr">Williams
    et al., 2016</xref>) can be added to make the output data
    biologically more realistic. The key parameters
    <monospace>number_of_generations</monospace>,
    <monospace>division_probability</monospace> and
    <monospace>death_probability</monospace> determine the final size of
    the tumour, while the degree of intra tumour heterogeneity can be
    varied by changing the <monospace>mutation_probability</monospace>
    parameter. For neutral tumour evolution, parameter
    <monospace>adv_mutant_division_probability</monospace> and
    <monospace>adv_mutant_death_probability</monospace> must be the same
    as <monospace>division_probability</monospace> and
    <monospace>death_probability</monospace>.</p>
    <p>Throughout the cancer growth phase,
    <monospace>CancerSim</monospace> stores information about the parent
    cell and a designation of newly acquired mutations for every cell.
    Complete mutational profiles of cells are reconstructed a posteriori
    based on the stored lineage information.</p>
    <p>The division rules which allow only cells with empty neighbouring
    nodes to divide, cause exclusively peripheral growth and complete
    absence of dynamics in the tumour centre. To allow for variable
    degrees of growth inside the tumour, we introduced a death process.
    At every time step, after all cells attempt their division, a number
    of random cells die according to
    <monospace>death_probability</monospace> and
    <monospace>adv_mutant_death_probability</monospace> and yield their
    position to host a new cancer cell in a subsequent time step.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="simulation-results">
    <title>Simulation results</title>
    <p>After the simulation, the tumour matrix, and the lists of
    lineages and frequencies of each mutation in the tumour are exported
    to files. Furthermore, the virtual tumour can be sampled and a
    histogram over the frequency of mutations will be visualised.
    Alternatively, a saved tumour can be loaded from file and then
    subjected to the sampling process.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="outlook">
    <title>Outlook</title>
    <p>Future investigations and expansions of
    <monospace>CancerSim</monospace> will focus on sampling of tumour
    specimens in a specific spatial pattern. Additionally, the effects
    of chemotherapy can be modelled by the introduction of different
    modes of cell death. Our model only considers sequencing noise for
    mutated cells. Future improvements of our model will also consider
    other sources of sequencing noise, e.g., read errors from
    non-mutated sites which would lead to false-positive cancer
    detections.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="download-and-installation">
  <title>Download and Installation</title>
  <p><monospace>CancerSim</monospace> is written in Python (version
  &gt;3.5). We recommend to install it directly from the source code
  hosted at github
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mpievolbio-scicomp/cancer_sim">https://github.com/mpievolbio-scicomp/cancer_sim</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Detailed instructions including creation of a
  <monospace>conda</monospace> environment are given in the online
  documentation at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cancer-sim.readthedocs.io/en/master/include/README.html#installation">https://cancer-sim.readthedocs.io/en/master/include/README.html#installation</ext-link>.
  After installation, the software is available as a python module
  <monospace>casim</monospace>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="high-level-functionality">
  <title>High-level functionality</title>
  <sec id="setting-up-the-cancer-simulation-parameters">
    <title>Setting up the cancer simulation parameters</title>
    <p>The parameters of the cancer simulation are specified in a python
    module or programmatically via the
    <monospace>CancerSimulationParameters</monospace> class. The table
    below lists all parameters, their function and acceptable values.
    [.,.] denotes a range of permissive parameter values.</p>
    <table-wrap>
      <table>
        <colgroup>
          <col width="38%" />
          <col width="26%" />
          <col width="36%" />
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Parameter name</th>
            <th>function</th>
            <th>valid options</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>matrix_size</monospace></td>
            <td>Number of mesh points in each dimension</td>
            <td>&gt;0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>number_of_generations</monospace></td>
            <td>Number of generations to simulate</td>
            <td>&gt;0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>division_probability</monospace></td>
            <td>Probability of cell division per generation</td>
            <td>[0,1]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>adv_mutant_division_probability</monospace></td>
            <td>Probability of division for cells with advantageous
            mutation</td>
            <td>[0,1]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>death_probability</monospace></td>
            <td>Fraction of cells that die per generation</td>
            <td>[0,1]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>adv_mutant_death_probability</monospace></td>
            <td>Fraction of cells with advantageous mutation that die
            per generation</td>
            <td>[0,1]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>mutation_probability</monospace></td>
            <td>Probability of mutations</td>
            <td>[0,1]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>adv_mutant_mutation_probability</monospace></td>
            <td>Mutation probability for the adv. cells</td>
            <td>[0,1]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>number_of_mutations_per_division</monospace></td>
            <td>Number of mutations per cell division</td>
            <td>&gt;=0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>adv_mutation_wait_time</monospace></td>
            <td>Number of generations after which adv. mutation
            occurs</td>
            <td>&gt;0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>number_of_initial_mutations</monospace></td>
            <td>Number of mutations present in first cancer cell</td>
            <td>&gt;=0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>tumour_multiplicity</monospace></td>
            <td>Tumour multiplicity</td>
            <td>“single”, “double”</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>read_depth</monospace></td>
            <td>Sequencing read depth</td>
            <td>read length * number of reads / genome length</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>sampling_fraction</monospace></td>
            <td>Fraction of cells to be sampled</td>
            <td>[0,1]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>sampling_positions</monospace></td>
            <td>A list of [(x,y)] coordinates specifying the grid points
            where to take samples from the tumour. If unset or None, a
            single random position is chosen.</td>
            <td>[0, matrix_size-1]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>plot_tumour_growth</monospace></td>
            <td>Plot the tumour growth curve</td>
            <td>True, False</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><monospace>export_tumour</monospace></td>
            <td>Export the tumour growth data to file</td>
            <td>True, False</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <p>The file
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mpievolbio-scicomp/cancer_sim/blob/master/params.py"><monospace>params.py</monospace></ext-link>
    can serve as a template to setup a simulation with all above
    parameters. Users should start with the template and adjust the
    parameters as needed for their application by setting experimentally
    or theoretically known values or by calibrating the simulation
    output against experiments or other models.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="run-the-simulation">
    <title>Run the simulation</title>
    <p>The simulation is started either from the command line, through a
    python script or from within an interactive python session. The
    command line interface accepts as arguments a random seed, a path
    for the output directory and a log level. More detailed instructions
    are given in the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cancer-sim.readthedocs.io/en/latest/include/README.html#high-level-functionality">online
    documentation</ext-link> and in the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cancer-sim.readthedocs.io/en/latest/refman.html#casim.casim.CancerSimulator.run">reference
    manual</ext-link>.</p>
    <p>For the impatient, we also provide a jupyter notebook with a more
    condensed version of the above example (grid size 20x20) at
    <monospace>docs/source/include/notebooks/quickstart_example.ipynb</monospace>.
    An interactive version can be launched on the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/mpievolbio-scicomp/cancer_sim.git/master?filepath=docs%2Fsource%2Finclude%2Fnotebooks%2Fquickstart_example.ipynb">Binder
    service</ext-link>.</p>
    <p>A further notebook demonstrates the possibility to dump a
    simulation to disk, reload it and continue the simulation with
    optionally changed parameters
    (<monospace>docs/source/include/notebooks/run_dump_reload_continue.ipynb</monospace>).
    This feature could be exploited to simulate cancer dormancy with
    <monospace>CancerSim</monospace>.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="output">
    <title>Output</title>
    <p>After the run has finished, all output is found in the specified
    output directory. Simulation output consists of the mutation list
    and a sample file representing the sampled portion of the tumour.
    Two pdf files are generated showing the mutation histograms of the
    whole tumour and the sampled portion, respectively. If requested by
    the parameter <monospace>plot_tumour_growth</monospace>, a third pdf
    is generated showing the tumour growth curve (number of tumour cells
    over time). Furthermore, the output contains serialized versions
    (“pickles”) of the tumour geometry as a 2D matrix, the death list,
    and the mutation list. Another directory contains all logged
    information from the run. The amount of logged information depends
    on the chosen log level.</p>
    <p>As an example and possible starting point for further
    investigations beyond the produced plots, the quick start example
    notebook demonstrates how to load the tumour matrix into memory and
    how to visualize the mutational profile as a heat map as shown in
    Figure 1.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption><p>Tumour matrix as a 2D grid with colored cells
      indicating the order in which mutations appear.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="img/mutation_profile.png" xlink:title="" />
    </fig>
    <p>The figure shows the central part of the tumour matrix that
    results from the template parameter file
    <monospace>params.py</monospace> on the X-Y grid with colors
    indicating the order in which mutations appear. 0 (deep purple)
    indicates no mutation in this cell.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="documentation-and-support">
  <title>Documentation and support</title>
  <p>The API reference manual and community guidelines including
  directions for contributors and bug reports are given in the online
  documentation at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cancer-sim.readthedocs.io">https://cancer-sim.readthedocs.io</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="testing-and-continuous-integration">
  <title>Testing and continuous integration</title>
  <p>Each commit to the code base triggers a build and test run on
  https://travis-ci.org. The build and test status can be observed at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://travis-ci.org/mpievolbio-scicomp/cancer_sim">https://travis-ci.org/mpievolbio-scicomp/cancer_sim</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Turajlic2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Turajlic</surname><given-names>Samra</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sottoriva</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>Trevor</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Swanton</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Resolving genetic heterogeneity in cancer</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-03">2019</year><month>03</month>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41576-019-0114-6</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Williams2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Marc J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>Chris P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>Trevor A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sottoriva</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Identification of neutral tumor evolution across cancer types</article-title>
        <source>Nature Genetics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>48</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3489</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Kumar2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Vinay Kumar</surname><given-names>Jon C. Aster</given-names><suffix>Abul K. Abbas</suffix></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Robbins basic pathology</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <isbn>978-0-323-48054-3</isbn>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Altrock2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Altrock</surname><given-names>Philipp M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Lin L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Michor</surname><given-names>Franziska</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The mathematics of cancer: Integrating quantitative models</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015-12">2015</year><month>12</month>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc4029</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Opasic2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Opasic</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dingli</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Traulsen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>How many samples are needed to infer truly clonal mutations from heterogenous tumours?</article-title>
        <source>BMC Cancer</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-019-5597-1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-waclaw2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Waclaw</surname><given-names>Bartlomiej</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bozic</surname><given-names>Ivana</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pittman</surname><given-names>Meredith E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hruban</surname><given-names>Ralph H</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vogelstein</surname><given-names>Bert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>Martin A</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A spatial model predicts that dispersal and cell turnover limit intratumour heterogeneity</article-title>
        <source>Nature</source>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>525</volume>
        <issue>7568</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14971</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
