<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2029</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02029</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>WEPPCLIFF: A command-line tool to process climate inputs
for soil loss models</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0464-9774</contrib-id>
<string-name>Ryan P. McGehee</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Dennis C. Flanagan</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Puneet Srivastava</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Purdue University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>USDA ARS National Soil Erosion Research
Laboratory</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Auburn University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-12-02">
<day>2</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>49</issue>
<fpage>2029</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>WEPP</kwd>
<kwd>CLIGEN</kwd>
<kwd>RIST</kwd>
<kwd>USLE</kwd>
<kwd>erosivity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>A key driver of erosion, and arguably the most labor-intensive
  input to erosion models, especially the Water Erosion Prediction
  Project model (WEPP,
  <xref alt="Flanagan &amp; Nearing, 1995" rid="ref-USDAU003A1995" ref-type="bibr">Flanagan
  &amp; Nearing, 1995</xref>), is climate. Even the simplest erosion
  models require climate inputs which are not always straightforward in
  their calculation. The complexity of these inputs dissuades potential
  users from creating their own inputs from observed data, which are
  almost always better than their simulated counterparts, especially
  when used to force erosion models for historical periods. For example,
  the Revised Universal Soil Loss Equation version 2 (RUSLE2,
  <xref alt="User’s Reference Guide, 2013" rid="ref-USDAU003A2013" ref-type="bibr"><italic>User’s
  Reference Guide</italic>, 2013</xref>) and WEPP are two of the leading
  soil erosion prediction models in the world today, but both still rely
  on climate inputs that are generated from outdated data, tools, or
  both.</p>
  <p>It appears that the lack of sufficient software in this field has
  resulted in models being used with suboptimal climate data inputs,
  which can, if left unaddressed, stifle scientific discovery and
  advancement. RUSLE2, as currently applied commonly within the United
  States, relies on climate data from 1960-1999. This data is not only
  20 years out of date, but the years utilized had fewer observation
  stations and the stations themselves used a mix of older technologies,
  some of which have documented quality issues that impact usability and
  reliability
  (<xref alt="Hollinger et al., 2002" rid="ref-HollingerU003A2002" ref-type="bibr">Hollinger
  et al., 2002</xref>;
  <xref alt="McGehee &amp; Srivastava, 2018" rid="ref-McGeheeU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">McGehee
  &amp; Srivastava, 2018</xref>;
  <xref alt="User’s Reference Guide, 2013" rid="ref-USDAU003A2013" ref-type="bibr"><italic>User’s
  Reference Guide</italic>, 2013</xref>). WEPP on the other hand, just
  had its climate database updated to the years 1974-2013
  (<xref alt="Srivastava et al., 2019" rid="ref-SrivastavaU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Srivastava
  et al., 2019</xref>), but those observed values are only used to
  create parameter files for CLImate GENerator (CLIGEN,
  <xref alt="Nicks et al., 1995" rid="ref-NicksU003A1995" ref-type="bibr">Nicks
  et al., 1995</xref>) which is then used to create simulated climate
  files for WEPP. Some internal investigations at the National Soil
  Erosion Research Laboratory (NSERL) have identified the climate inputs
  to both models as a significant reason for differences in their
  predictions of soil loss under otherwise identical simulations.</p>
  <p>In short, the erosion modeling community is in need of software
  that can at least shoulder most of the burden when preparing climate
  inputs for soil loss models. Therefore, we are proposing a WEPP
  CLImate File Formatter (WEPPCLIFF) program to begin addressing this
  need.</p>
  <p><monospace>WEPPCLIFF</monospace> is an R-based command line tool
  which was originally designed to prepare ‘breakpoint format’ climate
  file inputs for WEPP (Figure 1) that has been extended to perform
  other general functions such as storm separation, quality checking,
  gap filling, and erosion index (EI) calculations (climate inputs for
  the USLE family of models). The program is also provided with
  extensive accompanying documentation which covers a range of topics
  including most notably: installation, syntax, input, output, and
  examples.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>An example ‘breakpoint format’ climate input file for
    WEPP, which was prepared by WEPPCLIFF. More information on the
    format of WEPP climate inputs can be obtained from its documentation
    at:
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ars.usda.gov/ARSUserFiles/50201000/WEPP/usersum.pdf">https://www.ars.usda.gov/ARSUserFiles/50201000/WEPP/usersum.pdf</ext-link></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="KMQE_CLI_FILE_COLOR.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="advanced-functionality">
  <title>Advanced Functionality</title>
  <p>After the initial core functions of WEPPCLIFF had been developed,
  several more advanced functions were added to increase the utility of
  WEPPCLIFF (and to enhance its ability to deliver high quality climate
  inputs to WEPP and potentially other models as well). Each of the more
  impactful features are discussed below with figures when applicable.
  All of the following figures were produced with WEPPCLIFF standard
  plots.</p>
  <p>Two of these features are more general and are used to refine the
  time series inputs for all variables supported in WEPPCLIFF
  (i.e. quality checking and gap-filling). WEPPCLIFF quality checking
  uses a combination of a) hard physical limits, b) adaptive physical
  rate change limits, and c) adaptive ‘spiking’, ‘streaking’,
  ‘sticking’, and frequency (return period) analyses to determine
  potentially faulty or erroneneous data. These analyses are performed
  for precipitation and non-precipitation variables separately. An
  example quality checked input using default parameters is provided in
  Figure 2. At the time of publication, a new frequency analysis method
  based on a generalized extreme value model (climextRemes,
  <xref alt="Paciorek, 2019" rid="ref-PaciorekU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Paciorek,
  2019</xref>) was being incorporated in WEPPCLIFF source code;
  therefore, that functionality was not active for WEPPCLIFF at
  publication.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>An example quality checked input timeseries (daily
    resolution) of maximum temperature data for a typical midwest
    climate station using default quality checking
    parameters.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="11419800_MAXIMUM_TEMPERATURE_INPUT_TS.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>Gap-filling in WEPPCLIFF is based on a multiple imputation model
  (MICE,
  <xref alt="van Buuren &amp; Groothuis-Oudshoorn, 2011" rid="ref-vanBuurenU003A2011" ref-type="bibr">van
  Buuren &amp; Groothuis-Oudshoorn, 2011</xref>) which was configured to
  utilize all available data (within the same time series and from
  correlated multivariate relationships to other variables) to inform
  gap-filling of the missing time series. Figure 3 shows the same
  quality checked weather station from Figure 2 before and after
  gap-filling (using default parameters for the ‘quick impute’ option).
  At the time of publication, there was still some need to tweak each of
  these functions so that they would work seamlessly with the many
  different data types (temporal resolutions and formats) and diverse
  climate conditions (severe weather, droughts, nonstationarity, etc.).
  These functions will be refined as new information becomes available
  about how to improve them. Figures 4 and 5 show examples of how varied
  data missingness, seasonality, magnitude, variability, etc. can be for
  any two given stations. All other quality checking and gap-filling
  features were the original work of the WEPPCLIFF lead-developer.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>An example quality checked output timeseries (daily
    resolution) of maximum temperature data for the same station using
    default gap filling parameters for the ‘quick impute’
    option.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="11419800_MAXIMUM_TEMPERATURE_DAILY_TS.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>An example gap-filled precipitation time series with
    heavier, more seasonal rainfall from a longer time period with
    limited missingness.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="KUIL_PRECIPITATION_DAILY_TS.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>An example gap-filled precipitation time series with
    lighter, more variable rainfall from a shorter time period with
    rampant missingness.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="KYIP_PRECIPITATION_DAILY_TS.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>The other two advanced features are specific to soil loss modeling:
  storm separation and erosion index (EI) calculation. These features
  provide a critical service from WEPPCLIFF enabling the production of
  empirical erosivity (more commonly known as R, R-factor, or EI) model
  inputs from the same time series inputs to physical models. Therefore,
  the results from WEPPCLIFF can be used to prepare identical climate
  inputs for empirical and physical models (e.g. WEPP and RUSLE2) so
  that their various outputs can be compared. The definition of a storm
  was based on soil loss modeling literature, which utilizes a time and
  depth threshhold to determine breaks between storms. These are
  directly specifiable in WEPPCLIFF, and they essentially control how
  many different storms (with the same I30) should be used to calculate
  EI. The EI calculation in WEPPCLIFF follows all the rules for various
  methods in erosion modeling literature, but most importantly,
  WEPPCLIFF allows the user to specify their own energy equation (a
  valid R expression based on breakpoint intensity input) for the
  exploration of new kinetic energy calculation methods and their impact
  on EI.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="existing-software">
  <title>Existing Software</title>
  <p>Historically, when providing climate inputs to WEPP, there were
  essentially two options. One must either a) use CLIGEN to prepare a
  daily ‘tp-ip’ format input file or b) manually prepare a ‘breakpoint’
  format input file. The first option was the preferred method for
  providing climate inputs to WEPP, and it was originally the only way
  to prepare inputs for simulation with WEPP. The second option was
  added later in WEPP’s development as a way to provide the highest
  resolution and best quality precipitation data for WEPP simulations.
  This enabled higher quality results primarily for single-storm
  simulation, but it was impractical for continous simulation for even a
  small period of time. <monospace>WEPPCLIFF</monospace> pushes this
  capability to the extreme by providing the capability to prepare
  relatively vast (format-intensive) climate inputs to force WEPP for
  extended continuous simulation while still preserving the most
  valuable components of breakpoint data (discussed in more detail
  later). Details on these two input formats can be found in either
  CLIGEN, WEPP, or WEPPCLIFF documentation.</p>
  <p>The only other related software for providing climate inputs to
  soil loss models, of which we are aware, is a publicly distributed
  executable program called Rainfall Intensity Summarization Tool (RIST,
  <xref alt="Dabney &amp; Justice, 2019" rid="ref-USDAU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Dabney
  &amp; Justice, 2019</xref>). RIST is currently maintained by the USDA
  ARS National Sedimentation Laboratory (NSL) where it can be used as a
  tool to prepare climate inputs for RUSLE, WEPP, SWAT, and AnnAGNPS.
  However, the WEPP inputs for example, are only provided in the ‘tp-ip’
  file format rather than the ‘breakpoint’ file format which means that
  only the intensity-at-peak factor, time-to-peak factor, and daily
  precipitation amount and duration are actually provided to WEPP to fit
  a double exponential storm distribution and finally generate
  breakpoints for erosion calculations. Therefore, much of the observed
  data is being discarded when providing ‘observed climate inputs’ to
  WEPP using RIST. WEPPCLIFF, on the other hand, maintains the original
  precipitation breakpoints in its climate file output thereby providing
  more valuable climate inputs to WEPP.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="validation">
  <title>Validation</title>
  <p>WEPPCLIFF was developed from and validated by comparing to several
  different works including: three Agriculture Handbooks (AH282
  (<xref alt="Wischmeier &amp; Smith, 1965" rid="ref-WischmeierU003A1965" ref-type="bibr">Wischmeier
  &amp; Smith, 1965</xref>), AH537
  (<xref alt="Wischmeier &amp; Smith, 1978" rid="ref-WischmeierU003A1978" ref-type="bibr">Wischmeier
  &amp; Smith, 1978</xref>), and AH703
  (<xref alt="Renard et al., 1997" rid="ref-RenardU003A1997" ref-type="bibr">Renard
  et al., 1997</xref>)), two peer-reviewed articles
  (<xref alt="McGehee &amp; Srivastava, 2018" rid="ref-McGeheeU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">McGehee
  &amp; Srivastava, 2018</xref>;
  <xref alt="McGregor &amp; Mutchler, 1995" rid="ref-McGregorU003A1995" ref-type="bibr">McGregor
  &amp; Mutchler, 1995</xref>), and RIST
  (<xref alt="Dabney &amp; Justice, 2019" rid="ref-USDAU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Dabney
  &amp; Justice, 2019</xref>). The comparison with RIST is of particular
  interest since this was completed as part of a massive WEPP-RUSLE2
  model comparison project between the NSERL and NSL ARS laboratories.
  This project resulted in several important findings related to climate
  representations in both models (WEPP and RUSLE2), their accompanying
  input generation softwares (CLIGEN, RIST, and now WEPPCLIFF), and the
  impacts on erosion predictions. An example comparison related to
  WEPPCLIFF found that RIST (April 2019 release version) erroneously
  calculated kinetic energy and RUSLE2 erosion indices to be 26% and 21%
  too low, respectively. RIST was updated with more correct calculations
  in May 2019 (there were still differences of about 3% for the stations
  compared at the time of this writing), but RIST has been actively used
  since at least 2011 with several scientific works, and this error may
  have impacted several or all of those works. More comprehensive
  summaries of findings from this comparison project are expected to be
  published in scientific literature in the near future.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-PaciorekU003A2019">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Paciorek</surname><given-names>Christopher J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>climextRemes: Tools for analyzing climate extremes</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <uri>https://cran.r-project.org/package=climextRemes</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-vanBuurenU003A2011">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>van Buuren</surname><given-names>Stef</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Groothuis-Oudshoorn</surname><given-names>Karin</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>mice: Multivariate imputation by chained equations in r</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Statistical Software</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <volume>45</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <uri>https://www.jstatsoft.org/v45/i03/</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v045.i03</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-USDAU003A2019">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Dabney</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Rainfall intensity summarization tool (RIST) v3.99</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <uri>https://www.ars.usda.gov/southeast-area/oxford-ms/national-sedimentation-laboratory/watershed-physical-processes-research/research/rist/rist-rainfall-intensity-summarization-tool/</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-NicksU003A1995">
      <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Nicks</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gander</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Chapter 2: Weather generator</article-title>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nearing</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <publisher-name>USDA ARS</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>West Lafayette, IN</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
        <volume>USDA Water Erosion Prediction Project: Hillslope Profile and Watershed Model Documentation, NSERL Report No. 10</volume>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-HollingerU003A2002">
      <element-citation publication-type="report">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hollinger</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Angel</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Palecki</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Spatial distribution, variation, and trends in storm precipitation characteristics associated with soil erosion in the united states</article-title>
        <publisher-name>Illinois State Water Survery</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Champaign, IL</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SrivastavaU003A2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>J. R. Frankenberger</surname></name>
          <name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Updated climate database and impacts on WEPP model predictions</article-title>
        <source>Soil and Water Conservation</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>74</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2489/jswc.74.4.334</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-USDAU003A1995">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <source>USDA water erosion prediction project hillslope and watershed model documentation.</source>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nearing</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <publisher-name>USDA ARS</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>West Lafayette, IN</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-USDAU003A2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <source>User’s reference guide: Revised universal soil loss equation, version 2</source>
        <publisher-name>USDA ARS</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-McGregorU003A1995">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mutchler</surname><given-names>C. K</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Erosivity index values for northern mississippi</article-title>
        <source>Transactions of the American Society of Agricultural Engineers</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
        <volume>38</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13031/2013.27921</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-McGeheeU003A2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>McGehee</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Benchmarking reliable erosion indices from quarter-hour station data for climate studies in the southeastern united states</article-title>
        <source>Soil and Water Conservation</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>73</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2489/jswc.73.4.363</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-WischmeierU003A1965">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wischmeier</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Predicting rainfall erosion losses from cropland east of the rocky mountains</source>
        <publisher-name>USDA ARS</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="1965">1965</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-RenardU003A1997">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Renard</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weesies</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McCool</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Predicting soil erosion by water: A guide to conservation planning with the revised universal soil loss equation (RUSLE)</source>
        <publisher-name>USDA ARS</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-WischmeierU003A1978">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wischmeier</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Predicting rainfall erosion losses</source>
        <publisher-name>USDA ARS</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="1978">1978</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
