<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2425</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02425</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>argopy: A Python library for Argo ocean data
analysis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-7231-2095</contrib-id>
<string-name>Guillaume Maze</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4956-8698</contrib-id>
<string-name>Kevin Balem</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Univ Brest, Ifremer, CNRS, IRD, LOPS, F‐29280 Plouzané,
France</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-06-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>53</issue>
<fpage>2425</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>ocean</kwd>
<kwd>oceanography</kwd>
<kwd>observation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Argo is a real-time global ocean <italic>in situ</italic> observing
  system. It provides thousands of highly accurate ocean measurements
  every day. The Argo dataset has now accumulated more than 2.3 million
  vertical ocean profiles and accessing it for scientific analysis
  remains a challenge.</p>
  <p>The Argo expert community, focused on delivering a curated dataset
  of the best scientific quality possible, has never provided its user
  base with a Python software package to easily access and manipulate
  Argo measurements: the <bold>argopy</bold> software aims to fill this
  gap. The <bold>argopy</bold> software can be used to easily fetch and
  manipulate measurements from Argo floats. It is dedicated to
  scientists without knowledge of the Argo data management system but is
  also designed to accommodate expert requirements.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>The ocean is a key component of the Earth’s climate system. It
  therefore needs continuous real-time monitoring to help scientists
  better understand its dynamics and to predict its evolution. All
  around the world, oceanographers have managed to join their efforts
  and set up a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.goosocean.org/">Global
  Ocean Observing System</ext-link> among which <italic>Argo</italic> is
  a key component.</p>
  <p>Argo is a global network of nearly 4000 autonomous probes measuring
  pressure, temperature and salinity from the surface to 2000m depth
  every 10 days. The localisation of these probes is nearly random
  between the <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[60^o]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msup><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  parallels
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://map.argo-france.fr">see
  live coverage here</ext-link>). Data from the probes are collected by
  satellite in real-time, processed by several data centers, merged in a
  single dataset (comprising of more than 2.3 million vertical profiles
  as of June 2020) and made freely available to anyone through an
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ifremer.fr/ifremer/argo">ftp
  server</ext-link> or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.17882/42182">monthly
  zip snapshots</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>The Argo international observation array was initiated in 1999 and
  soon revolutionised our perspective on the large scale structure and
  variability of the ocean by providing seasonally and regionally
  unbiased in situ temperature/salinity measurements of the ocean
  interior, key information that satellites can’t provide
  (<xref alt="Riser et al., 2016" rid="ref-riser-2016" ref-type="bibr">Riser
  et al., 2016</xref>). The Argo array reached its full global coverage
  (of 1 profile per month and per 3x3 degree horizontal area) in 2007,
  and pursues its evolution to fulfil new scientific requirements
  (<xref alt="Roemmich et al., 2019" rid="ref-roemmich-2019" ref-type="bibr">Roemmich
  et al., 2019</xref>). Argo data have been used in more than 4000
  scientific publications.</p>
  <p>This
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://map.argo-france.fr">online
  figure</ext-link> shows the current coverage of the network. It now
  extends to higher latitudes than the original
  <inline-formula><alternatives>
  <tex-math><![CDATA[\pm60^o]]></tex-math>
  <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
  and some of the floats are able to profile down to 4000m and 6000m.
  New floats are also equipped with biogeochemical sensors, measuring
  oxygen and chlorophyll for instance. All these evolutions of the
  network increase the total number of floats to nearly 4000. Argo is
  thus providing a deluge of in situ data: more than 400 profiles per
  day.</p>
  <p>Each Argo probe is an autonomous, free drifting, profiling float,
  i.e. a probe that can’t control its trajectory but is able to control
  its buoyancy and thus to move up and down the water column as it
  wishes. Argo floats continuously operate the same program, or cycle,
  illustrated
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="figU003Aargofloat">Figure 1</xref>. After 9
  to 10 days of free drift at a parking depth of about 1000m, a typical
  Argo float dives down to 2000m and then rises back to the surface
  while profiling - measuring pressure, temperature and salinity. Once
  it reaches the surface, the float sends by satellite its measurements
  to a data center, where they are processed in real time and made
  freely available on the web in less than 24 hours.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Typical 10 days program, cycle, of an Argo
    float.<styled-content id="figU003Aargofloat"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="_static/argofloats_cycle.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="why-argopy">
  <title>Why <bold>argopy</bold> ?</title>
  <p>For non-expert users of the Argo dataset, it is rather complicated
  to get access to Argo measurements. Even though data are made freely
  available on the web, the Argo dataset consists of thousands of files
  organised using jargon, tens of different variables and many reference
  tables. The exhaustive Argo
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.13155/29825">user
  manual</ext-link> is more than 100 pages long, which can be rather
  intimidating to go through for new users.</p>
  <p>This complexity arises from the fact that Argo operates many
  different models of floats and sensors, quality control of <italic>in
  situ</italic> measurements from autonomous platforms requires a lot of
  complementary information (meta-data), and the Argo data management
  workflow is distributed between more than 10 Data Assembly Centers all
  around the world. The Argo data management is a model for other ocean
  observing systems and constantly ensures the highest quality of
  scientific measurements for the community
  (<xref alt="Wong &amp; coauthors, 2020" rid="ref-wong-2020" ref-type="bibr">Wong
  &amp; coauthors, 2020</xref>).</p>
  <p>The result of this tremendous success in data management – in
  developing good practices and well calibrated procedures
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.argodatamgt.org/Documentation">see
  all the Argo Data Management Team documentation here</ext-link>) – is
  a very complex Argo dataset: the <bold>argopy</bold> software aims to
  help users navigate this complex realm.</p>
  <p>Since the Argo community focuses on delivering a curated dataset
  for science, software packages exist for Argo data operators to decode
  and quality control the data (e.g.
  <xref alt="Detoc et al., 2017" rid="ref-scoop" ref-type="bibr">Detoc
  et al., 2017</xref>). However, no open source softwares are available
  for scientists, who therefore must develop their own machinery to
  download and manipulate the data.</p>
  <p>Python is becoming widely used by the scientific community and
  beyond: worldwide, and is the most popular and fastest growing
  language in the last 5 years (20%, source:
  http://pypl.github.io/PYPL.html). It offers a modern, powerful and
  open source framework to work with. Since, up to this point, no Python
  based software has been dedicated to the Argo dataset, it made sense
  to develop <bold>argopy</bold>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="key-features-of-argopy">
  <title>Key features of <bold>argopy</bold></title>
  <p><bold>argopy</bold> is a python software package that simplifies
  the process of accessing and manipulating Argo data. The two key
  features of <bold>argopy</bold> are its trivial fetching API of Argo
  data and its ability to provide data formatted for both beginner and
  expert users of Argo.</p>
  <sec id="data-fetching">
    <title>Data fetching</title>
    <p><bold>argopy</bold> provides a trivial fetching API of Argo data
    through a simple call to one of the 3 different ways to look at Argo
    data: over a space/time domain (with the <italic>region</italic>
    access point), for one or a list of specific floats (given their
    unique
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.wmo.int/pages/prog/amp/mmop/wmo-number-rules.html">WMO
    number</ext-link> with the <italic>float</italic> access point) or
    for one or a list of float profiles (with the
    <italic>profile</italic> access point). This is as simple as:</p>
    <code language="python">from argopy import DataFetcher as ArgoDataFetcher
fetcher = ArgoDataFetcher().region([-75, -45, 20, 30, 0, 100, '2011', '2012'])
ds = fetcher.to_xarray()</code>
    <p>Here we used <bold>argopy</bold> to fetch data between 75/45W,
    20/30N, from 0 to 100db and for the entire year 2011. Once the user
    has defined what they need (the <monospace>fetcher</monospace> class
    instance in the example above), <bold>argopy</bold> will fetch data
    online and manage internally all the complicated processing of
    formatting the web request and creating a workable in memory data
    structure (the <monospace>to_xarray()</monospace> call above). By
    default, <bold>argopy</bold> uses the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://xarray.pydata.org">xarray
    data model</ext-link>; <italic>xarray</italic> is an open source
    Python package to easily work with labelled multi-dimensional
    arrays.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="data-formatting">
    <title>Data formatting</title>
    <p><bold>argopy</bold> aims to thrive in providing Argo data to
    non-experts. One key feature of <bold>argopy</bold> is the option
    for selecting a <italic>user mode</italic> that is either
    <monospace>standard</monospace> or <monospace>expert</monospace>.
    Standard users are those who want to focus on the measurements for
    scientific analysis; those who do not know, or don’t want to be
    bothered with all the Argo jargon and multitude of variables and
    parameters.</p>
    <p>For standard users (the default mode), <bold>argopy</bold>
    internally runs a series of processes that curate the raw data and
    provide a simplified and science focused dataset. For expert users,
    <bold>argopy</bold> will apply its data model to raw fetched data
    and return Argo variables that experts users are already used
    to.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="and-more">
    <title>And more</title>
    <p><bold>argopy</bold> has features to manipulate Argo data, for
    instance:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>the possibility to transform data from a collection of
        measurements to a collection of vertical profiles, and
        vice-versa;</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>the possibility to interpolate irregularly sampled
        measurements onto standard pressure levels.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p>Another feature is the ability to cache fetched data, so that
    requests provide users with data much more rapidly, saving bandwidth
    and time.</p>
    <p>Two last important features of <bold>argopy</bold> to mention
    here are:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>the possibility to fetch data locally, from a user copy of
        the entire or subset of the Argo database,</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>the possibility to fetch only meta data (organised in
        <italic>index</italic> lookup tables), which allows the user to
        determine the regional Argo sampling, for instance. These more
        advanced features may be more of interest for
        <monospace>expert</monospace> users, since they require more
        knowledge of the Argo dataset.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusion">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p><bold>argopy</bold> is filling an important gap in the ocean
  science community by providing an easy way to access a large and
  complex dataset that has proved to be very important in oceanographic
  studies. For information on all the features available with
  <bold>argopy</bold>, the reader is referred to the complete software
  documentation at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://argopy.readthedocs.io">https://argopy.readthedocs.io</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We acknowledge support from the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.euro-argo.eu/">Euro-Argo
  ERIC community</ext-link> during the genesis of this project. This
  software was created with support from the EARISE project, a European
  Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under grant
  agreement no 824131. Call INFRADEV-03-2018-2019: Individual support to
  ESFRI and other world-class research infrastructures.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-roemmich-2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Roemmich</surname><given-names>Dean</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>Matthew H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Claustre</surname><given-names>Hervé</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Kenneth</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Moum</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oke</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>W. Brechner</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pouliquen</surname><given-names>Sylvie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Purkey</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Scanderbeg</surname><given-names>Megan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Suga</surname><given-names>Toshio</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wijffels</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zilberman</surname><given-names>Nathalie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>Dorothee</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baringer</surname><given-names>Molly</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Belbeoch</surname><given-names>Mathieu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bittig</surname><given-names>Henry C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>Emmanuel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Calil</surname><given-names>Paulo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Carse</surname><given-names>Fiona</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Carval</surname><given-names>Thierry</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Conchubhair</surname><given-names>Diarmuid Ó.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>d’Ortenzio</surname><given-names>Fabrizio</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dall’Olmo</surname><given-names>Giorgio</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Desbruyeres</surname><given-names>Damien</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fennel</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fer</surname><given-names>Ilker</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>Raffaele</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Forget</surname><given-names>Gael</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Freeland</surname><given-names>Howard</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fujiki</surname><given-names>Tetsuichi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gehlen</surname><given-names>Marion</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Greenan</surname><given-names>Blair</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hallberg</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hibiya</surname><given-names>Toshiyuki</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hosoda</surname><given-names>Shigeki</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jayne</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jochum</surname><given-names>Markus</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Gregory C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>KiRyong</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kolodziejczyk</surname><given-names>Nicolas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Körtzinger</surname><given-names>Arne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Traon</surname><given-names>Pierre-Yves Le</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lenn</surname><given-names>Yueng-Djern</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Maze</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mork</surname><given-names>Kjell Arne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>Tamaryn</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>Takeyoshi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Garabato</surname><given-names>Alberto Naveira</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>Are</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pattabhi</surname><given-names>Rama Rao</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>Satya</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Riser</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schmechtig</surname><given-names>Catherine</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>Claudia</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shroyer</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sterl</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Talley</surname><given-names>Lynne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Tanhua</surname><given-names>Toste</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thierry</surname><given-names>Virginie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thomalla</surname><given-names>Sandy</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Toole</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Troisi</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Trull</surname><given-names>Thomas W.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Turton</surname><given-names>Jon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Velez-Belchi</surname><given-names>Pedro Joaquin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Walczowski</surname><given-names>Waldemar</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Haili</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wanninkhof</surname><given-names>Rik</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>Amy F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>Stephanie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Cara</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Annie P. S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jianping</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>Ichiro</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>On the Future of Argo: A Global, Full-Depth, Multi-Disciplinary Array</article-title>
        <source>Frontiers in Marine Science</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <uri>https://www.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmars.2019.00439</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmars.2019.00439</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-riser-2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Riser</surname><given-names>Stephen C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Freeland</surname><given-names>Howard J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Roemmich</surname><given-names>Dean</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wijffels</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Troisi</surname><given-names>Ariel</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Belbeoch</surname><given-names>Mathieu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>Denis</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jianping</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pouliquen</surname><given-names>Sylvie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thresher</surname><given-names>Ann</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Le Traon</surname><given-names>Pierre-Yves</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Maze</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>Birgit</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ravichandran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>Fiona</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Poulain</surname><given-names>Pierre-Marie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Suga</surname><given-names>Toshio</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Byunghwan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sterl</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mork</surname><given-names>Kjell-Arne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Velez-Belchi</surname><given-names>Pedro Joaquin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ansorge</surname><given-names>Isabelle</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Turton</surname><given-names>Jon</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baringer</surname><given-names>Molly</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jayne</surname><given-names>Steven R.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fifteen years of ocean observations with the global Argo array</article-title>
        <source>Nature Clim. Change</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016-02">2016</year><month>02</month>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nclimate2872</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate2872</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-wong-2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>Annie</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>coauthors</surname></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Argo 1999-2019: Two million temperature-salinity profiles and subsurface velocity observations from a global array of profiling floats</article-title>
        <source>Frontiers in Marine Science, section Ocean Observation</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>in press</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmars.2020.00700</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-scoop">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Detoc</surname><given-names>Jerome</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thepault</surname><given-names>Baptiste</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Carval</surname><given-names>Thierry</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mahoudo</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Garo</surname><given-names>Mickael</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Scoop-Argo : Visual quality control for Argo NetCDF data files</article-title>
        <source></source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume></volume>
        <uri></uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17882/48531</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
