<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1018</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01018</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>\| SWEpy: A Python Library for Quick and Easy Access and
Manipulation of MEaSUREs CETB Files for SWE Analysis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-6772-9600</contrib-id>
<string-name>William M. Norris</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1643-5976</contrib-id>
<string-name>Carson J.Q. Farmer</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Earth Lab, University of Colorado Boulder</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-09-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>32</issue>
<fpage>1018</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>snow</kwd>
<kwd>swe</kwd>
<kwd>data after_success</kwd>
<kwd>data processing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Modern analysis of earth’s systems requires significant volumes of
  increasingly fine resolution spatial and temporal information. For
  example, the <italic>MEaSUREs Calibrated Enhanced Passive Microwave
  Daily-Grid 2.0 Brightness Temperature</italic> data set, released by
  the National Snow and Ice Data Center (NSIDC), is no exception
  (<xref alt="Brodzik &amp; Armstrong, 2018" rid="ref-measures" ref-type="bibr">Brodzik
  &amp; Armstrong, 2018</xref>). The MEaSUREs dataset contains twice
  daily passive microwave imagery from 1978 through 2017, which can be
  particularly useful for spatial-temporal analysis of snow water
  equivalent (SWE). In addition to high temporal resolution, the
  MEaSUREs CETB dataset contains imagery that has been resampled from
  25km down to 6.25km wide pixels, allowing for analysis to be done at a
  finer spatial scale than previously available versions of the data
  source. While this data is exceedingly useful, it can take
  considerable time to set up scripts for web access, geographic
  subsetting, and merging sequential images into useful time cubes. The
  MEaSUREs data set is also large: accessing a full time series of
  Northern Hemisphere imagery would require easily two terabytes of disc
  space, which most researchers do not have available on their local
  computer. SWEpy was developed in part to deal with these issues, while
  also providing basic data manipulation tools to facilitate SWE-based
  research. SWEpy is a Python library that allows for quick and easy
  web-access, geographic subsetting, and concatenation of MEaSUREs CETB
  files. The primary goal of SWEpy is to reduce the time needed for
  researchers to access and begin making use of MEaSUREs CETB data. A
  user with very little knowledge of Python can use SWEpy to access this
  data within minutes, and those more familiar with the scientific
  Python ecosystem can benefit from the wealth of tools available for
  subsequent analysis of CETB data.</p>
  <p>Ease of use is a primary goal for SWEpy. Users can enter as little
  information as a date range, bounding coordinates, and their Earthdata
  login credentials, and SWEpy will return two single time cube files
  with only the data for the user’s study area included. SWEpy has
  intelligent defaults pre-defined for various CETB files used in SWE
  analysis, such as which sensor is the most stable for a given year, as
  well as more specific web-access functionality. When using the default
  settings, in order to avoid running out of disk space, SWEpy will
  optimize long running data access sessions by automating the whole
  process, stopping to subset and concatenate files incrementally when
  the entire dataset will be too large to store on disk. Additionally,
  if a user has more specific file needs, they can work directly with
  SWEpy’s flexible web access tool, and still make use of the built in
  geographic subsetting and merging features if desired.</p>
  <sec id="example-use-of-auto-workflow">
    <title>Example Use of Auto Workflow</title>
    <preformat>from swepy.swepy import swepy
import datetime
import os

# enter Earthdata login credentials
username = &quot;username&quot;
password = &quot;password&quot;

# enter bounding coordinates
lon_lat_ul = [66,-145]
lon_lat_lr = [73,-166]

# set date range (Y,M,D)
start = datetime.date(2010,1,1)
end = datetime.date(2010,2,1)

# instantiate the class
swe = swepy(os.getcwd(), start=start, end=end,
            ul=lon_lat_ul, lr=lon_lat_lr, username=username,
            password=password)

# Get a time cube for your study area
swe.scrape_all()</preformat>
  </sec>
  <sec id="example-use-of-web-scraper-alone">
    <title>Example Use of Web Scraper Alone</title>
    <preformat>from swepy.nsidcDownloader import nsidcDownloader
nD = nsidcDownloader.nsidcDownloader(username=username,password=password,folder=os.getcwd())
file = {
    &quot;resolution&quot;: &quot;3.125km&quot;,
    &quot;platform&quot;: &quot;F17&quot;,
    &quot;sensor&quot;: &quot;SSMIS&quot;,
    &quot;grid&quot;: &quot;N&quot;,
    &quot;pass&quot;: &quot;M&quot;,
    &quot;date1&quot;: datetime.date(2015,10,10),
    &quot;date2&quot;: datetime.date(2015,10,10),
    &quot;channel&quot;: &quot;37H&quot;,
    &quot;algorithm&quot;: &quot;SIR&quot;,
    &quot;input&quot;: &quot;CSU&quot;
}

nD.download_file(**file)</preformat>
  </sec>
  <sec id="accessing-swepy">
    <title>Accessing SWEpy</title>
    <p>SWEpy is available from GitHub
    (https://github.com/wino6687/SWEpy) and anaconda
    (https://anaconda.org/wino6687/swepy). Full documentation can be
    found in the GitHub repository wiki
    (https://github.com/wino6687/SWEpy/wiki). Any issues or bugs can be
    reported to the issues page on the GitHub repository:
    https://github.com/wino6687/SWEpy/issues.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements:</title>
  <p>SWEpy was developed with funding from Earth Lab at the University
  of Colorado Boulder under the supervision of Carson Farmer.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-measures">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Brodzik</surname><given-names>D. G. Long</given-names><suffix>M. J.</suffix></name>
          <name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MEaSUREs calibrated enhanced-resolution passive microwave daily EASE-grid 2.0 brightness temperature ESDR, version 1.3</article-title>
        <publisher-name>https://doi.org/10.5067/MEASURES/CRYOSPHERE/NSIDC-0630.001</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
