<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">494</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00494</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>PyTransport: A Python package for the calculation of
inflationary correlation functions</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>David J. Mulryne</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-6464-6466</contrib-id>
<string-name>John W. Ronayne</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Astronomy Unit, Queen Mary University of London, E3 4NS,
UK</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2017-11-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>23</issue>
<fpage>494</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Inflation</kwd>
<kwd>Cosmology</kwd>
<kwd>Early Universe</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="PyTransLogo-1.png" />
  PyTransport constitutes a straightforward code written in C++ together
  with Python scripts which automatically edit, compile and run the C++
  code as a Python module. It has been written for Unix-like systems (OS
  X and Linux). The transport method we utilise means only coupled
  differential equations need to be solved, and the implementation
  presented here combines the speed of C++ with the functionality and
  convenience of Python.</p>
  <p>The code is intended to be a reusable resource for inflationary
  cosmology. It enables users to quickly create a complied Python
  module(s) for any given model(s) of multi-field inflation. Primarily
  the module employs the transport approach to inflationary cosmology to
  calculate the tree-level power-spectrum and bispectrum of user
  specified models of multi-field inflation, accounting for all sub and
  super-horizon effects. To this end, the module contains a number
  functions that can be called from Python and that perform tasks such
  as calculating the background evolution of the cosmology, as well as
  the evolution of the two and three point functions. We also provide a
  number of further functions written in Python that perform common
  tasks such as calculating the power spectrum or bispectrum over a
  range of scales by utilising the compiled module. The true power of
  the approach, however, is that users can rapidly write their own
  scripts, or adapt ours, to suit their own needs.</p>
  <p>The transport approach to inflationary perturbation theory that the
  code employs can be seen as the differential version of the integral
  expressions of the In-In formalism. It is helpful numerically because
  it provides a set of ordinary differential equations for the
  correlation functions of inflationary perturbations. The code solves
  these equations from deep inside the horizon until some desired time
  after horizon crossing using a standard variable step size ordinary
  differential equation (ODE) routine with error control. Such off the
  shelf routines are extremely well tested, and provide an easy way to
  change the required accuracy. This is helpful in order to check
  convergence of the numerical solutions, or to respond to needs of
  models with very fine features. Details of the transport method itself
  that the code is based on can be found in the recent paper
  (<xref alt="Dias et al., 2016" rid="ref-Dias" ref-type="bibr">Dias et
  al., 2016</xref>)
  (<xref alt="Ronayne &amp; Mulryne, 2017" rid="ref-Ronayne" ref-type="bibr">Ronayne
  &amp; Mulryne, 2017</xref>). We highly recommend reading this guide in
  combination with that paper.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Dias">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>Mafalda</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mulryne</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Seery</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Numerical evaluation of the bispectrum in multiple field inflation - the transport approach with code</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Ronayne">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Ronayne</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mulryne</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Numerically evaluating the bispectrum in curved field-space – with PyTransport 2.0</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
