<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2582</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02582</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>21cmFAST v3: A Python-integrated C code for generating 3D
realizations of the cosmic 21cm signal.</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3059-3823</contrib-id>
<string-name>Steven G. Murray</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4085-2094</contrib-id>
<string-name>Bradley Greig</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3374-1772</contrib-id>
<string-name>Andrei Mesinger</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8984-0465</contrib-id>
<string-name>Julian B. Muñoz</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-5"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4314-1810</contrib-id>
<string-name>Yuxiang Qin</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-3095-6137</contrib-id>
<string-name>Jaehong Park</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-7"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1443-3483</contrib-id>
<string-name>Catherine A. Watkinson</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-6"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>School of Earth and Space Exploration, Arizona State
University, Phoenix, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>ARC Centre of Excellence for All-Sky Astrophysics in 3
Dimensions (ASTRO 3D)</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>School of Physics, University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC
3010, Australia</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-4">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Scuola Normale Superiore, Piazza dei Cavalieri 7, 56126
Pisa, Italy</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-5">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Physics, Harvard University, 17 Oxford St.,
Cambridge, MA, 02138, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-6">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>School of Physics and Astronomy, Queen Mary University of
London, G O Jones Building, 327 Mile End Road, London, E1 4NS,
UK</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-7">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>School of Physics, Korea Institute for Advanced Study, 85
Hoegiro, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul, 02455, Republic of Korea</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-09-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>54</issue>
<fpage>2582</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>astronomy</kwd>
<kwd>cosmology</kwd>
<kwd>simulation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The field of 21-cm cosmology – in which the hyperfine spectral line
  of neutral hydrogen (appearing at the rest-frame wavelength of 21 cm)
  is mapped over large swathes of the Universe’s history – has developed
  radically over the last decade. The promise of the field is to
  revolutionize our knowledge of the first stars, galaxies, and black
  holes through the timing and patterns they imprint on the cosmic 21-cm
  signal. In order to interpret the eventual observational data, a range
  of physical models have been developed – from simple analytic models
  of the global history of hydrogen reionization, through to fully
  hydrodynamical simulations of the 3D evolution of the brightness
  temperature of the spectral line. Between these extremes lies an
  especially versatile middle-ground: fast semi-numerical models that
  approximate the full 3D evolution of the relevant fields: density,
  velocity, temperature, ionization, and radiation (Lyman-alpha, neutral
  hydrogen 21-cm, etc.). These have the advantage of being comparable to
  the full first-principles hydrodynamic simulations, but significantly
  quicker to run; so much so that they can be used to produce thousands
  of realizations on scales comparable to those observable by upcoming
  low-frequency radio telescopes, in order to explore the very wide
  parameter space that still remains consistent with the data.</p>
  <p>Amongst practitioners in the field of 21-cm cosmology, the
  <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> program has become the <italic>de
  facto</italic> standard for such semi-numerical simulators.
  <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Mesinger et al., 2011" rid="ref-mesinger2010" ref-type="bibr">Mesinger
  et al., 2011</xref>;
  <xref alt="Mesinger &amp; Furlanetto, 2007" rid="ref-mesinger2007" ref-type="bibr">Mesinger
  &amp; Furlanetto, 2007</xref>) is a high-performance C code that uses
  the excursion set formalism
  (<xref alt="Furlanetto et al., 2004" rid="ref-furlanetto2004" ref-type="bibr">Furlanetto
  et al., 2004</xref>) to identify regions of ionized hydrogen atop a
  cosmological density field evolved using first- or second-order
  Lagrangian perturbation theory
  (<xref alt="Scoccimarro &amp; Sheth, 2002" rid="ref-scoccimarro2002" ref-type="bibr">Scoccimarro
  &amp; Sheth, 2002</xref>;
  <xref alt="Zel’Dovich, 1970" rid="ref-zeldovich1970" ref-type="bibr">Zel’Dovich,
  1970</xref>), tracking the thermal and ionization state of the
  intergalactic medium, and computing X-ray, soft UV and ionizing UV
  cosmic radiation fields based on parametrized galaxy models. For
  example, the following figure contains slices of lightcones (3D fields
  in which one axis corresponds to both spatial <italic>and</italic>
  temporal evolution) for the various component fields produced by
  <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace>.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Sample of Component Fields output by 21cmFAST. Cosmic
    evolution occurs from bottom to top. From left to right, quantities
    shown are: (i) dark matter overdensity field; (ii) Lyman-alpha flux;
    (iii) Lyman-Werner flux; (iv) X-ray heating rate; (v)
    locally-averaged UVB; (vi) critical halo mass for star formation in
    Atomically Cooled Galaxies; (vii) critical halo mass for star
    formation in Molecularly Cooled Galaxies; (viii) cumulative number
    of recombinations per baryon; (ix) neutral hydrogen fraction; and
    (x) the 21cm brightness temperature. A high-resolution version of
    this figure is available at
    http://homepage.sns.it/mesinger/Media/lightcones_minihalo.png</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="yuxiangs-plot-small.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>However, <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> is a highly specialized
  code, and its implementation has been quite specific and relatively
  inflexible. This inflexibility makes it difficult to modify the
  behaviour of the code without detailed knowledge of the full system,
  or disrupting its workings. This lack of modularity within the code
  has led to widespread code “branching” as researchers hack new
  physical features of interest into the C code; the lack of a
  streamlined API has led derivative codes which run multiple
  realizations of <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> simulations (such as
  the Monte Carlo simulator, <monospace>21CMMC</monospace>,
  <xref alt="Greig &amp; Mesinger, 2015" rid="ref-greig2015" ref-type="bibr">Greig
  &amp; Mesinger, 2015</xref>) to re-write large portions of the code in
  order to serve their purpose. It is thus of critical importance, as
  the field moves forward in its understanding – and the range and scale
  of physical models of interest continues to increase – to reformulate
  the <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> code in order to provide a fast,
  modular, well-documented, well-tested, stable simulator for the
  community.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="features-of-21cmfast-v3">
  <title>Features of 21cmFAST v3</title>
  <p>This paper presents <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> v3+, which is
  formulated to follow these essential guiding principles. While keeping
  the same core functionality of previous versions of
  <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace>, it has been fully integrated into a
  Python package, with a simple and intuitive interface, and a great
  deal more flexibility. At a higher level, in order to maintain best
  practices, a community of users and developers has coalesced into a
  formal collaboration which maintains the project via a Github
  organization. This allows the code to be consistently monitored for
  quality, maintaining high test coverage, stylistic integrity,
  dependable release strategies and versioning, and peer code review. It
  also provides a single point-of-reference for the community to obtain
  the code, report bugs and request new features (or get involved in
  development).</p>
  <p>A significant part of the work of moving to a Python interface has
  been the development of a robust series of underlying Python
  structures which handle the passing of data between Python and C via
  the <monospace>CFFI</monospace> library. This foundational work
  provides a platform for future versions to extend the scientific
  capabilities of the underlying simulation code. The primary
  <italic>new</italic> usability features of
  <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> v3+ are:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Convenient (Python) data objects which simplify access to and
      processing of the various fields that form the brightness
      temperature.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Enhancement of modularity: the underlying C functions for each
      step of the simulation have been de-coupled, so that arbitrary
      functionality can be injected into the process.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Conversion of most global parameters to local structs to enable
      this modularity, and also to obviate the requirement to re-compile
      in order to change parameters.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Simple <monospace>pip</monospace>-based installation.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Robust on-disk caching/writing of data, both for efficiency and
      simplified reading of previously processed data (using HDF5).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Simple high-level API to generate either coeval cubes (purely
      spatial 3D fields defined at a particular time) or full lightcone
      data (i.e. those coeval cubes interpolated over cosmic time,
      mimicking actual observations).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Improved exception handling and debugging.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Convenient plotting routines.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Simple configuration management, and also more intuitive
      management for the remaining C global variables.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Comprehensive API documentation and tutorials.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Comprehensive test suite (and continuous integration).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Strict semantic
      versioning<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>While in v3 we have focused on the establishment of a stable and
  extendable infrastructure, we have also incorporated several new
  scientific features, appearing in separate papers:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Generate transfer functions using the
      <monospace>CLASS</monospace> Boltzmann code
      (<xref alt="Lesgourgues, 2011" rid="ref-Lesgourgues2011" ref-type="bibr">Lesgourgues,
      2011</xref>).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Simulate the effects of relative velocities between dark matter
      and Baryons
      (<xref alt="Muñoz, 2019b" rid="ref-munoz2019a" ref-type="bibr">Muñoz,
      2019b</xref>,
      <xref alt="2019a" rid="ref-munoz2019b" ref-type="bibr">2019a</xref>).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Correction for non-conservation of ionizing photons (Park,
      Greig et al., <italic>in prep</italic>).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Include molecularly cooled galaxies with distinct properties
      (<xref alt="Qin, Mesinger, et al., 2020" rid="ref-qin2020" ref-type="bibr">Qin,
      Mesinger, et al., 2020</xref>)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Calculate rest-frame UV luminosity functions based on
      parametrized galaxy models.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p><monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> is still in very active
  development. Amongst further usability and performance improvements,
  future versions will see several new physical models implemented,
  including milli-charged dark matter models
  (<xref alt="Muñoz et al., 2018" rid="ref-Munoz2018" ref-type="bibr">Muñoz
  et al., 2018</xref>) and forward-modelled CMB auxiliary data
  (<xref alt="Qin, Poulin, et al., 2020" rid="ref-qin2020a" ref-type="bibr">Qin,
  Poulin, et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
  <p>In addition, <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> will be incorporated
  into large-scale inference codes, such as
  <monospace>21CMMC</monospace>, and is being used to create large
  data-sets for inference via machine learning. We hope that with this
  new framework, <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> will remain an
  important component of 21-cm cosmology for years to come.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="examples">
  <title>Examples</title>
  <p><monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> supports installation using
  <monospace>conda</monospace>, which means installation is as simple as
  typing <monospace>conda install -c conda-forge 21cmFAST</monospace>.
  The following example can then be run in a Python interpreter.</p>
  <p>In-depth examples can be found in the official documentation. As an
  example of the simplicity with which a full lightcone may be produced
  with the new <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> v3, the following may be
  run in a Python interpreter (or Jupyter notebook):</p>
  <code language="python">import py21cmfast as p21c

lightcone = p21c.run_lightcone(
    redshift=6.0,              # Minimum redshift of lightcone
    max_redshift=30.0,
    user_params={
        &quot;HII_DIM&quot;: 150,        # N cells along side in output cube
        &quot;DIM&quot;: 400,            # Original high-res cell number
        &quot;BOX_LEN&quot;: 300,        # Size of the simulation in Mpc
    },
    flag_options={
        &quot;USE_TS_FLUCT&quot;: True,  # Don't assume saturated spin temp
        &quot;INHOMO_RECO&quot;: True,   # Use inhomogeneous recombinations
    },
    lightcone_quantities=(     # Components to store as lightcones
        &quot;brightness_temp&quot;,
        &quot;xH_box&quot;,
        &quot;density&quot;
    ),
    global_quantities=(        # Components to store as mean
        &quot;xH_box&quot;,              # values per redshift
        &quot;brightness_temp&quot;
    ),
)

# Save to a unique filename hashing all input parameters
lightcone.save()

# Make a lightcone sliceplot
p21c.plotting.lightcone_sliceplot(lightcone, &quot;brightness_temp&quot;)</code>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Brightness temperature lightcone produced by the example
    code in this paper.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="lightcone.pdf" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <code language="python"># Plot a global quantity
p21c.plotting.plot_global_history(lightcone, &quot;xH&quot;)</code>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Globally volume-averaged hydrogen neutral fraction
    produced by the example code in this paper.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="xH_history.pdf" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="performance">
  <title>Performance</title>
  <p>Despite being a Python code, <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> v3
  does not diminish the performance of previous pure-C versions. It
  utilises <monospace>CFFI</monospace> to provide the interface to the
  C-code through Python, which is managed by some custom Python classes
  that oversee the construction and memory allocation of each C
  <monospace>struct</monospace>.</p>
  <p>OpenMP parallelization is enabled within the C-code, providing
  excellent speed-up for large simulations when performed on
  high-performance machines.</p>
  <p>A simple performance comparison between v3 and v2.1 (the last
  pure-C version), running a light-cone simulation over a redshift range
  between 35 and 5 (92 snapshots) with spin temperature fluctuations
  (<monospace>USE_TS_FLUCT</monospace>), inhomogeneous recombinations
  (<monospace>INHOMO_RECO</monospace>), FFTW Wisdoms
  (<monospace>USE_FFTW_WISDOM</monospace>) and interpolation tables
  (<monospace>USE_INTERPOLATION_TABLES</monospace>), with a resolution
  of <monospace>HII_DIM=250</monospace> cells, and
  <monospace>DIM=1000</monospace> cells for the initial conditions, on
  an Intel(R) Xeon(R) CPU (E5-4657L v2 @ 2.40GHz) with 16 shared-memory
  cores, reveals that a clock time of 7.63(12.63) hours and a maximum
  RAM of 224(105) gigabytes are needed for v3(v2.1).</p>
  <p>Note that while a full light-cone simulation can be expensive to
  perform, it only takes 2-3min to calculate a Coeval box (excluding the
  initial conditions). For instance, the aforementioned timing for v3
  includes 80 minutes to generate the initial condition, which also
  dominates the maximum RAM required, with an additional ~4 minutes per
  snapshot to calculate all required fields of perturbation, ionization,
  spin temperature and brightness temperature.</p>
  <p>To guide the user, we list some performance benchmarks for
  variations on this simulation, run with
  <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> v3.0.2. Note that these benchmarks are
  subject to change as new minor versions are delivered; in particular,
  operational modes that reduce maximum memory consumption are planned
  for the near future.</p>
  <table-wrap>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Variation</th>
          <th>Time (hr)</th>
          <th>Memory (GB)</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Reference</td>
          <td>7.63</td>
          <td>224</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Single Core</td>
          <td>14.77</td>
          <td>224</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>4 Shared-memory Cores</td>
          <td>7.42</td>
          <td>224</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>64 Shared-memory Cores</td>
          <td>9.60</td>
          <td>224</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Higher Resolution (HII_DIM=500, DIM=2000)</td>
          <td>68.37</td>
          <td>1790</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Lower Resolution (HII_DIM=125, DIM=500)</td>
          <td>0.68</td>
          <td>28</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>No Spin Temperature</td>
          <td>4.50</td>
          <td>224</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Use Mini-Halos</td>
          <td>11.57</td>
          <td>233</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>No FFTW Wisdoms</td>
          <td>7.33</td>
          <td>224</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </table-wrap>
  <p>At this time, the <monospace>21cmFAST</monospace> team suggests
  using 4 or fewer shared-memory cores. However, it is worth noting that
  as performance does vary on different machines, users are recommended
  to calculate their own scalability.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This work was supported in part by the European Research Council
  (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation
  programme (AIDA – #638809). The results presented here reflect the
  authors’ views; the ERC is not responsible for their use. JBM was
  partially supported by NSF grant AST-1813694. Parts of this research
  were supported by the European Research Council under ERC grant number
  638743-FIRSTDAWN. Parts of this research were supported by the
  Australian Research Council Centre of Excellence for All Sky
  Astrophysics in 3 Dimensions (ASTRO 3D), through project number
  CE170100013. JP was supported in part by a KIAS individual Grant
  (PG078701) at Korea Institute for Advanced Study.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-mesinger2007">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mesinger</surname><given-names>Andrei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Furlanetto</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Efficient Simulations of Early Structure Formation and Reionization</article-title>
        <source>The Astrophysical Journal</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2007-11">2007</year><month>11</month>
        <volume>669</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/0704.0946</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/521806</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-mesinger2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Mesinger</surname><given-names>Andrei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Furlanetto</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cen</surname><given-names>Renyue</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>21CMFAST: a fast, seminumerical simulation of the high-redshift 21-cm signal</article-title>
        <source>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011-02">2011</year><month>02</month>
        <volume>411</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1003.3878</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2966.2010.17731.x</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-furlanetto2004">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Furlanetto</surname><given-names>Steven R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zaldarriaga</surname><given-names>Matias</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hernquist</surname><given-names>Lars</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Growth of H II Regions During Reionization</article-title>
        <source>The Astrophysical Journal</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2004-09">2004</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>613</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0403697</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/423025</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-zeldovich1970">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Zel’Dovich</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Gravitational instability: an approximate theory for large density perturbations.</article-title>
        <source>Astronomy and Astrophysics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1970-03">1970</year><month>03</month>
        <volume>500</volume>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-scoccimarro2002">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Scoccimarro</surname><given-names>Román</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>Ravi K.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>PTHALOS: a fast method for generating mock galaxy distributions</article-title>
        <source>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2002-01">2002</year><month>01</month>
        <volume>329</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0106120</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-8711.2002.04999.x</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-munoz2019a">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>Julian B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Standard Ruler at Cosmic Dawn</article-title>
        <source>Physics Review Letters</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-09">2019</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>123</volume>
        <issue>13</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.07868</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.123.131301</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-munoz2019b">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>Julian B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Robust velocity-induced acoustic oscillations at cosmic dawn</article-title>
        <source>Physics Review D</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-09">2019</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>100</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.07881</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevD.100.063538</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-qin2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Yuxiang</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mesinger</surname><given-names>Andrei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Jaehong</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Greig</surname><given-names>Bradley</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>Julian B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A tale of two sites - I. Inferring the properties of minihalo-hosted galaxies from current observations</article-title>
        <source>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-04">2020</year><month>04</month>
        <volume>495</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04442</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mnras/staa1131</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Lesgourgues2011">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Lesgourgues</surname><given-names>Julien</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Cosmic Linear Anisotropy Solving System (CLASS) I: Overview</article-title>
        <source>arXiv e-prints</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011-04">2011</year><month>04</month>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1104.2932</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Munoz2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>Julian B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dvorkin</surname><given-names>Cora</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>Abraham</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>21-cm Fluctuations from Charged Dark Matter</article-title>
        <source>Physics Review Letters</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-09">2018</year><month>09</month>
        <volume>121</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.01092</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.121.121301</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-qin2020a">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Yuxiang</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>Vivian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mesinger</surname><given-names>Andrei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Greig</surname><given-names>Bradley</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Jaehong</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Reionization inference from the CMB optical depth and E-mode polarization power spectra</article-title>
        <source>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020-07">2020</year><month>07</month>
        <volume>499</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.16828</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mnras/staa2797</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-greig2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Greig</surname><given-names>Bradley</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mesinger</surname><given-names>Andrei</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>21CMMC: an MCMC analysis tool enabling astrophysical parameter studies of the cosmic 21 cm signal</article-title>
        <source>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015-06">2015</year><month>06</month>
        <volume>449</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.06576</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mnras/stv571</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
<fn-group>
  <fn id="fn1">
    <label>1</label><p>https://semver.org</p>
  </fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
