<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3607</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03607</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>TraViA: a Traffic data Visualization and Annotation tool
in Python</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5614-1262</contrib-id>
<string-name>Olger Siebinga</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Human-Robot Interaction group, Department of Cognitive
Robotics, Faculty 3mE, Delft University of Technology, Mekelweg 2, 2628
CD Delft, the Netherlands</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-06-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>65</issue>
<fpage>3607</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>naturalistic traffic data</kwd>
<kwd>visualization</kwd>
<kwd>annotation</kwd>
<kwd>HighD</kwd>
<kwd>NGSim</kwd>
<kwd>pNEUMA</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>In recent years, multiple datasets containing traffic recorded in
  the real world and containing human-driven trajectories have been made
  available to researchers. Among these datasets are the HighD, pNEUMA,
  and NGSIM datasets. TraViA, an open-source Traffic data Visualization
  and Annotation tool was created to provide a single environment for
  working with data from these three datasets. Combining the data in a
  single visualization tool enables researchers to easily study data
  from all sources. TraViA was designed in such a way that it can easily
  be extended to visualize data from other datasets and that specific
  needs for research projects are easily implemented.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>The combination of drones, cameras, and image recognition
  techniques might sound like a recipe for a spy movie. But actually,
  this combination allows for the collection of rich traffic datasets.
  The recipe is straightforward: hover a drone above a location with
  traffic, record a video, and use image recognition to generate
  bounding boxes for all vehicles. The result is a dataset containing
  human-driven trajectories at the location of interest that can be used
  for many scientific purposes, e.g., to study traffic flow, model human
  behavior, or design autonomous vehicle controllers.</p>
  <p>Because the required ingredients are easily accessed all over the
  world, multiple such datasets have been published in recent years. In
  Germany, the highD project
  (<xref alt="Krajewski et al., 2018" rid="ref-Krajewski2018" ref-type="bibr">Krajewski
  et al., 2018</xref>) recorded all traffic at 6 different high-way
  locations; in Athens, Greece, all traffic in the city’s business
  district was recorded using 10 drones for 5 days in the pNEUMA project
  (<xref alt="Barmpounakis &amp; Geroliminis, 2020" rid="ref-Barmpounakis2020" ref-type="bibr">Barmpounakis
  &amp; Geroliminis, 2020</xref>); and American highway traffic was
  recorded using fixed base cameras in the NGSIM project
  (<xref alt="U.S. Department of Transportation Federal Highway Administration, 2016" rid="ref-NGSIM2016" ref-type="bibr">U.S.
  Department of Transportation Federal Highway Administration,
  2016</xref>). Combined, these datasets span different countries, types
  of vehicles, and environments, a combination valuable for researchers
  with different backgrounds. Example usages of these datasets are
  validating human behavior models (e.g., by Talebpour et al.
  (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-Talebpour2015a" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>)
  and Treiber et al.
  (<xref alt="2008" rid="ref-Treiber2008" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>))
  or testing autonomous vehicle controllers (e.g., by Schwarting et al.
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-Schwarting2019" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)).</p>
  <p>Currently, it is difficult to leverage the powerful combination of
  multiple datasets because all the datasets come in different formats,
  and it is often difficult to get a good and real-time visualization of
  the data. Some visualization tools exist (one is provided with the
  highD data
  (<xref alt="Krajewski et al., 2018" rid="ref-Krajewski2018" ref-type="bibr">Krajewski
  et al., 2018</xref>) and another example for NGSIM data can be found
  in Sazara
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-Sazara2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>))
  but they are specifically made for only one of these datasets and are
  very basic in the sense that they provide little control over
  simulation time and no insight in raw values per vehicle per frame. In
  addition to difficulties with visualization, finding, and annotating
  situations of interest in these massive datasets is a time-consuming
  task and keeping track of the annotations for the different datasets
  requires some bookkeeping skills.</p>
  <p>TraViA was developed to provide a solution for these problems.
  TraViA can be used to visualize and annotate data from highD, pNEUMA,
  and NGSIM and uses generic vehicle objects to store the state of
  vehicles at a specific time. This makes it possible to validate and
  test models or controllers on multiple datasets in parallel, without
  having to cope with the different dataset formats.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="software-functionality">
  <title>Software Functionality</title>
  <p>TraViA is written in Python 3 and has a graphical user interface
  developed in PyQt5. A screenshot of TraViA is provided in
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="figU003Ascreenshot">Figure 1</xref>. This
  screenshot shows the capabilities of TraViA in a single image. The
  main features of TraViA are:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Advanced information display based on raw data for every
      vehicle in every dataset by leveraging generic vehicle objects</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Dynamic visualization of the traffic scene with possibilities
      to zoom, pan, and rotate for an optimal view</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Exporting the visualization to a video or single image</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>An interactive timeline that shows dataset annotations, which
      are saved as python objects for easy manipulation</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>A screenshot of the TraViA software visualizing a frame
    of the highD dataset. The main features of TraViA are highlighted in
    this image.
    <styled-content id="figU003Ascreenshot"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/screenshot.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>TraViA was designed for use as a stand-alone program. It uses
  abstract classes as a basis for all dataset-specific objects to enable
  easy implementation of new datasets (for a class diagram and more
  information on how to do this, please see the readme file in the
  repository). It was specifically created to serve as a tool for
  generic visualization and annotation such that it can be used by
  researchers from different fields. To show the capabilities of TraViA
  and to provide a starting point for other researchers that want to use
  TraViA for their work, three example implementations of tools for
  specific purposes are included with TraVia. The first example is the
  functionality to automatically detect and annotate specific scenarios
  (e.g., lane changes), the second is functionality to plot specific
  vehicle signals over the course of an annotation, and the third is a
  function to plot a heatmap overlay for use in autonomous vehicle
  reward function development. All of these example tools are only
  implemented for use with the highD dataset.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="usage-of-travia-in-science-and-education">
  <title>Usage of TraViA in Science and Education</title>
  <p>Currently, TraVia is being used by the author for model validation
  of an inverse-reinforcement-learning-based driver model. A publication
  on this validation is currently being prepared for submission. Besides
  that, TraViA is used for educational purposes, allowing students at TU
  Delft to explore big naturalistic datasets by providing them with an
  accessible, GUI-based starting point.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>I thank Nissan Motor Co. Ltd. for funding this work, and I also
  thank my supervisors David Abbink and Arkady Zgonnikov for their
  valuable help and advice. Finally, I thank Joris Giltay for his help
  with testing the instructions in the readme file.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Krajewski2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Krajewski</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kloeker</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Eckstein</surname><given-names>Lutz</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The highD Dataset: A Drone Dataset of Naturalistic Vehicle Trajectories on German Highways for Validation of Highly Automated Driving Systems</article-title>
        <source>IEEE Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems, Proceedings, ITSC</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>2018-Novem</volume>
        <isbn>9781728103235</isbn>
        <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.05642</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ITSC.2018.8569552</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Barmpounakis2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Barmpounakis</surname><given-names>Emmanouil</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Geroliminis</surname><given-names>Nikolas</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>On the new era of urban traffic monitoring with massive drone data: The pNEUMA large-scale field experiment</article-title>
        <source>Transportation Research Part C: Emerging Technologies</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>111</volume>
        <issue>November 2019</issue>
        <issn>0968090X</issn>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trc.2019.11.023</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trc.2019.11.023</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-NGSIM2016">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>U.S. Department of Transportation Federal Highway Administration</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Next Generation Simulation (NGSIM) Vehicle Trajectories and Supporting Data. [Dataset]</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <uri>https://data.transportation.gov/Automobiles/Next-Generation-Simulation-NGSIM-Vehicle-Trajector/8ect-6jqj</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21949/1504477</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Schwarting2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Schwarting</surname><given-names>Wilko</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>Alyssa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Alonso-Mora</surname><given-names>Javier</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Karaman</surname><given-names>Sertac</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rus</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Social behavior for autonomous vehicles</article-title>
        <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-12">2019</year><month>12</month>
        <volume>116</volume>
        <issue>50</issue>
        <issn>0027-8424</issn>
        <uri>http://www.pnas.org/lookup/doi/10.1073/pnas.1820676116</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1820676116</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Talebpour2015a">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Talebpour</surname><given-names>Alireza</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mahmassani</surname><given-names>Hani S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hamdar</surname><given-names>Samer H.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Modeling lane-changing behavior in a connected environment: A game theory approach</article-title>
        <source>Transportation Research Part C: Emerging Technologies</source>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <issn>0968090X</issn>
        <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.trc.2015.07.007</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trc.2015.07.007</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Treiber2008">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Treiber</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kesting</surname><given-names>Arne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thiemann</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>How Much does Traffic Congestion Increase Fuel Consumption and Emissions? Applying a Fuel Consumption Model to the NGSIM Trajectory Data</article-title>
        <source>Transportation Research Board</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
        <issue>August</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Sazara2017">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Sazara</surname><given-names>Cem</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>NGSIM-trajectory-animation</article-title>
        <publisher-name>https://github.com/cemsaz/NGSIM-trajectory-animation</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
