<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">215</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00215</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>OSMnx: A Python package to work with graph-theoretic
OpenStreetMap street networks</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1851-6411</contrib-id>
<string-name>Geoff Boeing</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of California, Berkeley</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2017-03-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>215</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>openstreetmap</kwd>
<kwd>street network</kwd>
<kwd>network analysis</kwd>
<kwd>graph theory</kwd>
<kwd>physics</kwd>
<kwd>GIS</kwd>
<kwd>geospatial</kwd>
<kwd>urban planning</kwd>
<kwd>urban design</kwd>
<kwd>transportation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>OSMnx is a Python package for downloading OpenStreetMap street
  network data and then constructing it into NetworkX graphs. OSMnx can
  simplify and correct the network’s topology automatically to ensure
  that nodes actually exclusively represent intersections and dead-ends.
  Once the network is constructed and corrected, OSMnx can calculate
  shortest paths from one node to another. It can also calculate various
  network measures relevant to urban design and transportation (Ewing
  and Cervero 2010) as well as statistical physics (Newman 2010;
  Barthélemy 2011), including intersection density, average intersection
  degree, edge density, average street segment length, circuity
  (Giacomin and Levinson 2015), clustering coefficients, betweenness
  centrality (Crucitti et al. 2006), closeness centrality, PageRank
  (Brin and Page 1998), and many more. Its built-in visualization
  capabilities leverage matplotlib to easily plot routes (Figure 1),
  one-way streets, dead-ends, high/low connectivity intersections, and
  figure-ground diagrams of street networks and urban form (Figure
  2).</p>
  <p>OpenStreetMap presents an important new source of geospatial
  network data (Jokar Arsanjani 2015; Karduni et al. 2016). This package
  makes it easy to work with OpenStreetMap data for urban planning,
  transportation engineering, and network analysis purposes. Although
  scholars in urban studies and physics have studied street networks in
  numerous ways, the existing software landscape limits researchers’
  capabilities. The labor-intensive challenge of compiling street
  network data sets, especially for multiple countries, tends to limit
  sample sizes and most studies fall back on planar representations of
  the graph for tractibility (e.g., Porta et al. 2006; Strano et
  al. 2013). There is currently no ideal tool that offers a consistent,
  scalable, configurable method for collecting street network data from
  anywhere in the world and assembling it into graph-theoretic objects
  (rather than simple spatial geometries).</p>
  <p>OSMnx facilitates all of these use cases. It automates the
  downloading and algorithmic correction of street network and building
  footprint data for anywhere in the world from OpenStreetMap. It allows
  researchers to save street networks as ESRI shapefiles, GraphML files,
  or scalable vector graphics (SVG) files. Finally, it calculates routes
  and various network statistics, and projects and visualizes networks.
  Unlike expensive commercial software like ArcGIS and its limited
  network analysis capabilities, OSMnx is free, open-source, and
  natively provides rich network analysis abilities. Unlike network
  analysis software like Gephi, OSMnx natively provides geospatial
  abilities and interacts directly with OpenStreetMap’s Nominatim and
  Overpass APIs. OSMnx leverages the geopandas, NetworkX, and matplotlib
  Python packages for geospatial analysis, network analysis, and the
  visualization of network statistics and built environment
  characteristics.</p>
  <p>The latest stable release of the software can be installed via
  <monospace>pip</monospace> and full documentation can be found at
  https://osmnx.readthedocs.io.</p>
  <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="fig01.png" />
  <italic>Figure 1. OSMnx retrieves the street network for Los Angeles,
  California and plots a shortest-path route along it.</italic></p>
  <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="fig02.png" />
  <italic>Figure 2. OSMnx visualizes street networks in various ways to
  facilitate consistent comparison of urban form.</italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
