<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2044</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02044</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>NEEP: null empirically estimated p-values for
high-throughput molecular survival analysis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-1394-1999</contrib-id>
<string-name>Sean West</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Hesham Ali</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-0630-0843</contrib-id>
<string-name>Dario Ghersi</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>School of Interdisciplinary Informatics, University of
Nebraska at Omaha</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-12-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>52</issue>
<fpage>2044</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Python</kwd>
<kwd>bioinformatics</kwd>
<kwd>survival analysis</kwd>
<kwd>RNA-seq</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>When conducting survival analysis for molecular expression, a
  researcher has two main options: a regression test using the
  continuous expression as the independent variable with Cox
  Proportional Hazards (CPH) or a logrank test after separating patients
  into two groups such as low- vs high-expression with the Kaplan-Meier
  (KM) method. Both methods depend on the proportional hazards
  assumption. When this assumption is violated, using a binary variable
  performs better. However, KM survival analysis requires that the
  patients are split into two groups by a molecular expression
  threshold. In many cases, such as molecular survival analysis, a
  single threshold choice cannot be justified based on experimental
  design. The choice of a threshold when splitting up a continuous
  variable has been shown to be sensitive to patient group re-sampling
  (<xref alt="Sehgal et al., 2015" rid="ref-sehgal2015" ref-type="bibr">Sehgal
  et al., 2015</xref>). And in practice, small changes in the chosen
  threshold produce proportionally larger differences in the set of
  significant logrank tests
  (<xref alt="West et al., 2019" rid="ref-west2019" ref-type="bibr">West
  et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
  <p>To circumvent the need for an ad hoc molecular expression
  threshold, the logrank test can be calculated across a range of
  thresholds, producing a range of p-values. Choosing the minimum
  p-value from this range identifies the optimal split of patients into
  two groups, given a single molecular expression vector. However,
  taking the lowest p-value from a range will produce a
  non-Uniform(0,1), right-skewed distribution of p-values. Since
  p-values should be uniform under the null distribution, the skewed
  distribution cannot be used for valid statistical analysis. An
  equation was developed that could predict the correct p-values
  (<xref alt="Lausen &amp; Schumacher, 1992" rid="ref-lausen1992" ref-type="bibr">Lausen
  &amp; Schumacher, 1992</xref>); however, the precision given by the
  original authors is not precise enough for p-value correction
  procedures which are sensitive to very small p-value changes, as in
  the case of molecular analyses having many tens of thousands of
  observations. Thus, we developed NEEP, which overcomes this issue by
  sampling the null distribution using a bootstrapping procedure, which
  is parallelized to improve execution time performance.
  (<xref alt="West et al., 2019" rid="ref-west2019" ref-type="bibr">West
  et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
  <p>The null distribution is constructed by repeatedly permuting the
  patient order. For each permutation, the minimum p-value is calculated
  and added to the null distribution. Separately, the minimum p-value is
  obtained for each molecular expression vector. This null distribution
  is used to empirically determine the true p-values for this list of
  molecular expression vector p-values. In this way, the precision of
  the procedure is dependent on the number of samples (permutations)
  used to generate the null distribution. Since the null distribution is
  generated from the same set of patients, the corrected p-values are
  guaranteed to be Uniform(0,1) under the null if random. In other
  words, the minimum p-values for a set of random molecular expression
  vectors is the same as the null distribution. Because of this, the
  type 1 error and the FDR are guaranteed to be controlled. Finally,
  NEEP conducts False Discovery Rate (FDR) p-value correction
  (<xref alt="Benjamini &amp; Hochberg, 1995" rid="ref-benjamini1995" ref-type="bibr">Benjamini
  &amp; Hochberg, 1995</xref>) and calculates effect sizes, the hazard
  ratio and the 1, 2, and 5 year mortality ratios.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of Need</title>
  <p><bold>Research purpose</bold>: <monospace>NEEP</monospace> offers
  non-parametric, high-throughput, and statistically valid survival
  analysis of molecular expression vectors.</p>
  <p><bold>Problem solved</bold>: In molecular expression, the choice of
  a single threshold to separate patients into low- and high-expression
  cannot be justified and produces variable results.
  <monospace>NEEP</monospace> chooses the threshold which maximizes the
  test statistic relating molecular expression and patient survival for
  each molecular expression vector. Then <monospace>NEEP</monospace>
  corrects the resulting biased p-value distribution using a empirically
  determined null distribution. To generate the null,
  <monospace>NEEP</monospace> permutes different orders of patients and
  calculates their p-values across a range in order to produce a
  <monospace>Null Empirically Estimated P-value</monospace> for each
  molecular expression vector. <monospace>NEEP</monospace> produces
  p-values which are uniform under their null distribution so that their
  precision is dependent on the size of the null generated. By doing so,
  <monospace>NEEP</monospace> circumvents the issue of choosing a single
  threshold while addressing the issue of asymmetric p-value when
  optimizing the relationship between molecular expression and patient
  survival.</p>
  <p><bold>Target audience</bold>: The target audience is anyone
  conducting molecular, high-throughput survival analysis that does not
  have confounding clinical variables and whose expression vectors may
  violate CPH assumptions. Full documentation is available in the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/thecodingdoc/neep">project
  repository</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This project was partly funded by a University of Nebraska
  Collaboration Initiative/ System Science Seed Grant to Sushil Kumar,
  Hesham Ali, and Dario Ghersi and by the NIH AA026428 R21 grant to
  Sushil Kumar. The funder website is
  https://nebraska.edu/collaboration-initiative. The funders had no role
  in project design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish,
  or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-west2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>West</surname><given-names>Sean</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Sushil</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>Surinder K.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Hesham</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ghersi</surname><given-names>Dario</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Uncovering and characterizing splice variants associated with survival in lung cancer patients</article-title>
        <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007469</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-sehgal2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>Vasudha</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Seviour</surname><given-names>Elena G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>Tyler J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>Gordon B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Azencott</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ram</surname><given-names>Prahlad T.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Robust selection algorithm (RSA) for multi-omic biomarker discovery; integration with functional network analysis to identify miRNA regulated pathways in multiple cancers</article-title>
        <source>PloS one</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140072</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-lausen1992">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Lausen</surname><given-names>Berthold</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Maximally selected rank statistics</article-title>
        <source>Biometrics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2532740</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-benjamini1995">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Yoav</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Yosef</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: A practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>
        <source>Journal of the Royal statistical society: series B (Methodological)</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
        <volume>57</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2517-6161.1995.tb02031.x</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
