<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2575</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02575</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>DYCO: A Python package to dynamically detect and
compensate for time lags in ecosystem time series</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5569-0761</contrib-id>
<string-name>Lukas Hörtnagl</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>ETH Zurich, Department of Environmental Systems Science,
ETH Zurich, CH-8092, Switzerland</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-07-31">
<day>31</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>62</issue>
<fpage>2575</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>eddy covariance</kwd>
<kwd>flux</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>In ecosystem research, the eddy covariance (EC) method is widely
  used to quantify the biosphere-atmosphere exchange of greenhouse gases
  (GHGs) and energy
  (<xref alt="Aubinet et al., 2012" rid="ref-Aubinet2012" ref-type="bibr">Aubinet
  et al., 2012</xref>;
  <xref alt="Baldocchi et al., 1988" rid="ref-Baldocchi1988" ref-type="bibr">Baldocchi
  et al., 1988</xref>). The raw ecosystem flux (i.e., net exchange) is
  calculated by the covariance between the turbulent vertical wind
  component measured by a sonic anemometer and the entity of interest,
  e.g., CO<sub>2</sub>, measured by a gas analyzer. Due to the
  application of two different instruments, wind and gas are not
  recorded at exactly the same time, resulting in a time lag between the
  two time series. For the calculation of ecosystem fluxes this time
  delay has to be quantified and corrected for, otherwise fluxes are
  systematically biased. Time lags for each averaging interval can be
  estimated by finding the maximum absolute covariance between the two
  turbulent time series at different time steps in a pre-defined time
  window of physically possible time-lags (e.g.,
  <xref alt="McMillen, 1988" rid="ref-McMillen1988" ref-type="bibr">McMillen,
  1988</xref>;
  <xref alt="Moncrieff et al., 1997" rid="ref-Moncrieff1997" ref-type="bibr">Moncrieff
  et al., 1997</xref>). Lag detection works well when processing fluxes
  for compounds with high signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), which is
  typically the case for e.g. CO<sub>2</sub>. In contrast, for compounds
  with low SNR (e.g., N<sub>2</sub>O, CH<sub>4</sub>) the
  cross-covariance function with the turbulent wind component yields
  noisier results and calculated fluxes are biased towards larger
  absolute flux values
  (<xref alt="Langford et al., 2015" rid="ref-Langford2015" ref-type="bibr">Langford
  et al., 2015</xref>), which in turn renders the accurate calculation
  of yearly ecosystem GHG budgets more difficult and results may be
  inaccurate.</p>
  <p>One method to adequately calculate fluxes for compounds with low
  SNR is to first calculate the time lag for a
  <italic>reference</italic> compound with high SNR (e.g.,
  CO<sub>2</sub>) and then to apply the same time lag to the
  <italic>target</italic> compound of interest (e.g., N<sub>2</sub>O),
  with both compounds being recorded by the same analyzer
  (<xref alt="Nemitz et al., 2018" rid="ref-Nemitz2018" ref-type="bibr">Nemitz
  et al., 2018</xref>). <monospace>DYCO</monospace> uses this method by
  facilitating the dynamic lag-detection between the turbulent wind data
  and a <italic>reference</italic> compound and the subsequent
  application of found <italic>reference</italic> time lags to one or
  more <italic>target</italic> compounds.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>Lag detection between the turbulent departures of measured wind and
  the scalar of interest is a central step in the calculation of EC
  ecosystem fluxes. If the covariance maximization fails to detect a
  clear peak in the covariance function between the wind and the scalar,
  current flux calculation software can apply a constant default
  (nominal) time lag to the respective scalar. However, both the
  detection of clear covariance peaks in a pre-defined time window and
  the definition of a reliable default time lag is challenging for
  compounds that are often characterized by low SNR, such as
  N<sub>2</sub>O. In addition, the application of one static default
  time lag may produce inaccurate results when systematic time shifts
  are present in the raw data.</p>
  <p><monospace>DYCO</monospace> is meant to assist current flux
  processing software in the calculation of fluxes for compounds with
  low SNR. In the context of current flux processing schemes, the unique
  features offered as part of the <monospace>DYCO</monospace> package
  include:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>the dynamic application of progressively smaller time windows
      during lag search for a <italic>reference</italic> compound (e.g.,
      CO<sub>2</sub>),</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>the calculation of default time lags on a daily scale for the
      <italic>reference</italic> compound,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>the application of daily default <italic>reference</italic>
      time lags to one or more <italic>target</italic> compounds (e.g.,
      N<sub>2</sub>O)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>the dynamic normalization of time lags across raw data
      files,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>the automatic correction of systematic time shifts in
      <italic>target</italic> raw data time series, e.g., due to failed
      synchronization of instrument clocks, and</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>the application of instantaneous <italic>reference</italic>
      time lags, calculated from lag-normalized files, to one or more
      <italic>target</italic> compounds.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p><monospace>DYCO</monospace> aims to complement current flux
  processing schemes. <monospace>DYCO</monospace> uses EC raw data files
  as input and produces final lag-removed files that can be directly
  used in current flux calculation software.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="processing-chain">
  <title>Processing chain</title>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="dyco_processing_chain.png" />
  <p><bold>Figure 1.</bold> <italic>The DYCO processing
  chain.</italic></p>
  <p><monospace>DYCO</monospace> uses eddy covariance raw data files as
  input and produces lag-compensated raw data files as output.</p>
  <p>The full <monospace>DYCO</monospace> processing chain comprises
  four phases and several iterations during which
  <italic>reference</italic> lags are iteratively refined in
  progressively smaller search windows (Figure 1). Generally, the
  <italic>reference</italic> lag search is facilitated by prior
  normalization of default (nominal) time lags across files. This is
  achieved by compensating <italic>reference</italic> and
  <italic>target</italic> time series data for daily default
  <italic>reference</italic> lags, calculated from high-quality
  <italic>reference</italic> lags available around the respective date
  (Figure 2). Due to this normalization, <italic>reference</italic> lags
  fall into a specific, pre-defined, and therefore known time range,
  which in turn allows the application of increasingly narrower time
  windows during lag search. This approach has the advantage that
  <italic>reference</italic> lags can be calculated from a
  <italic>reference</italic> signal that shows clear peaks in the
  cross-covariance analysis with the wind data and thus yields
  unambiguous time lags due to its high SNR. In case the lag search
  failed to detect a clear time delay for the <italic>reference</italic>
  variable (e.g., during the night), the respective daily default
  <italic>reference</italic> lag is used instead.
  <italic>Reference</italic> lags can then be used to compensate
  <italic>target</italic> variables with low SNR for detected
  <italic>reference</italic> time delays.</p>
  <p><bold>Phase 1</bold> uses eddy covariance raw data files as input
  and removes the daily default <italic>reference</italic> lag from
  <italic>reference</italic> and <italic>target</italic> variables,
  producing lag-normalized raw data files. This is achieved by first
  calculating the time lag between the turbulent fluctuations of the
  vertical wind and the turbulent measurements of the
  <italic>reference</italic> variable (e.g., atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>)
  by covariance maximization. The time window for this lag search is
  iteratively narrowed down (default 3 iterations). Detected time lags
  are analyzed and daily default <italic>reference</italic> lags are
  calculated from a selection of high-quality covariance peaks found
  around the respective date. The <italic>reference</italic> variable
  and <italic>target</italic> variables are then compensated for found
  daily default <italic>reference</italic> lags by shifting time series
  data accordingly. At the same time <monospace>DYCO</monospace> removes
  systematic shifts from the data, i.e., after normalization all lags
  are found in the same time range (Figure 2). Finally, the shifted data
  are saved to new files.</p>
  <p><bold>Phase 2</bold> comprises the exact same processing steps as
  Phase 1, with the difference that instead of the original eddy
  covariance raw data files the lag-normalized files produced during
  Phase 1 are used as input. In essence, Phase 2 refines
  <italic>reference</italic> results from Phase 1. Since the
  <italic>reference</italic> time series data were already compensated
  for daily default <italic>reference</italic> lags during the previous
  phase, Phase 2 can apply a much narrower time window during
  <italic>reference</italic> lag search.</p>
  <p><bold>Phase 3</bold> detects the final instantaneous lags between
  the turbulent wind and the <italic>reference</italic> variable, using
  the lag-normalized files from Phase 2 as input. Due to the
  compensation for daily default time lags in preceding Phases,
  instantaneous lags for each time period are now found close to zero.
  Therefore, a narrow time window of +/- 100 records is applied for the
  final lag search. Lags found within the acceptance limit of +/- 50
  records are selected as the final instantaneous
  <italic>reference</italic> lag for the respective time period. For
  time periods with lags outside the acceptance limits, the final
  instantaneous <italic>reference</italic> lag is set to zero. Final
  instantaneous <italic>reference</italic> time lags are then applied to
  the <italic>target</italic> variables and final lag-compensated files
  are produced.</p>
  <p><bold>Phase 4</bold> finalizes the processing chain by producing
  additional plots.</p>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="fig_PHASE-1_ITERATION-3_TIMESERIES-PLOT_segment_lag_times_iteration-1612269182193.png" />
  <p><bold>Figure 2</bold>. <italic>Example showing the normalization of
  default reference time lags across raw data files recorded at the
  forest site
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.swissfluxnet.ethz.ch/index.php/sites/ch-dav-davos/site-info-ch-dav/">Davos</ext-link>
  in Switzerland. Shown are found instantaneous time lags (red) between
  turbulent wind data and turbulent CO<sub>2</sub> mixing ratios,
  calculated daily reference default lags (yellow bars), normalization
  correction (blue arrows) and the daily default reference lag after
  normalization (green bar). Negative lag values mean that the
  CO<sub>2</sub> signal was lagged behind the wind data, e.g., -400
  means that the instantaneous CO<sub>2</sub> records arrived 400
  records (corresponds to 20s in this example) later at the analyzer
  than the wind data. Daily default reference lags were calculated as
  the 3-day median time lag from a selection of high-quality time lags,
  i.e., when cross-covariance analyses yielded a clear covariance peak.
  The normalization correction is applied dynamically to shift the
  CO<sub>2</sub> data so that the default time lag is found close to
  zero across files. Note the systematic shift in time lags starting
  after 27 Oct 2016.</italic></p>
</sec>
<sec id="real-world-examples">
  <title>Real-world examples</title>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.icos-cp.eu/">ICOS</ext-link>
  Class 1 site
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.swissfluxnet.ethz.ch/index.php/sites/ch-dav-davos/site-info-ch-dav/">Davos</ext-link>
  (CH-Dav), a subalpine forest ecosystem station in the east of
  Switzerland, provides one of the longest continuous time series (24
  years and running) of ecosystem fluxes globally. Since 2016,
  measurements of the strong GHG N<sub>2</sub>O are recorded by a
  closed-path gas analyzer that also records CO<sub>2</sub>. To
  calculate fluxes using the EC method, wind data from the sonic
  anemometer is combined with instantaneous gas measurements from the
  gas analyzer. However, the air sampled by the gas analyzer needs a
  certain amount of time to travel from the tube inlet to the
  measurement cell in the analyzer and is thus lagged behind the wind
  signal. The lag between the two signals needs to be compensated for by
  detecting and then removing the time lag at which the cross-covariance
  between the turbulent wind and the turbulent gas signal reaches the
  maximum absolute value. This works generally well when using
  CO<sub>2</sub> (high SNR) but is challenging for N<sub>2</sub>O (low
  SNR). Using covariance maximization to search for the lag between wind
  and N<sub>2</sub>O mostly fails to accurately detect time lags between
  the two variables (noisy cross-correlation function), resulting in
  relatively noisy fluxes. However, since N<sub>2</sub>O has similar
  adsorption / desorption characteristics as CO<sub>2</sub>, it is valid
  to assume that both compounds need approximately the same time to
  travel through the tube to the analyzer, i.e., the time lag for both
  compounds in relation to the wind is similar. Therefore,
  <monospace>DYCO</monospace> can be applied (i) to calculate time lags
  across files for CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>reference</italic> compound),
  and then (ii) to remove found CO<sub>2</sub> time delays from the
  N<sub>2</sub>O signal (<italic>target</italic> compound). The
  lag-compensated files produced by <monospace>DYCO</monospace> can then
  be used to calculate N<sub>2</sub>O fluxes. Since
  <monospace>DYCO</monospace> normalizes time lags across files and
  compensates the N<sub>2</sub>O signal for instantaneous CO<sub>2</sub>
  lags, the <italic>true</italic> lag between wind and N<sub>2</sub>O
  can be found close to zero, which in turn facilitates the application
  of a small time window for the final lag search during flux
  calculations.</p>
  <p>Another application example are managed grasslands where the
  biosphere-atmosphere exchange of N<sub>2</sub>O is often characterized
  by sporadic high-emission events (e.g.,
  <xref alt="Hörtnagl et al., 2018" rid="ref-Hoertnagl2018" ref-type="bibr">Hörtnagl
  et al., 2018</xref>;
  <xref alt="Merbold et al., 2014" rid="ref-Merbold2014" ref-type="bibr">Merbold
  et al., 2014</xref>). While high N<sub>2</sub>O quantities can be
  emitted during and after management events such as fertilizer
  application and ploughing, fluxes in between those events typically
  remain low and often below the limit-of-detection of the applied
  analyzer. In this case, calculating N<sub>2</sub>O fluxes works well
  during the high-emission periods (high SNR) but is challenging during
  the rest of the year (low SNR). Here, <monospace>DYCO</monospace> can
  be used to first calculate time lags for a <italic>reference</italic>
  gas measured in the same analyzer (e.g., CO<sub>2</sub>, CO,
  CH<sub>4</sub>) and then remove <italic>reference</italic> time lags
  from the N<sub>2</sub>O data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This work was supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation
  SNF (ICOS CH, grant nos. 20FI21_148992, 20FI20_173691) and the EU
  project Readiness of ICOS for Necessities of integrated Global
  Observations RINGO (grant no. 730944).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Baldocchi1988">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Baldocchi</surname><given-names>Dennis D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hincks</surname><given-names>Bruce B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>Tilden P.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Measuring Biosphere-Atmosphere Exchanges of Biologically Related Gases with Micrometeorological Methods</article-title>
        <source>Ecology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1988-10">1988</year><month>10</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-01-02">2020</year><month>01</month><day>02</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>69</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <issn>00129658</issn>
        <uri>http://doi.wiley.com/10.2307/1941631</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1941631</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Langford2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Langford</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Acton</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ammann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Valach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nemitz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Eddy-covariance data with low signal-to-noise ratio: Time-lag determination, uncertainties and limit of detection</article-title>
        <source>Atmospheric Measurement Techniques</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015-10">2015</year><month>10</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-01-02">2020</year><month>01</month><day>02</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>8</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <issn>1867-8548</issn>
        <uri>https://www.atmos-meas-tech.net/8/4197/2015/</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/amt-8-4197-2015</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Moncrieff1997">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Moncrieff</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Massheder</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bruin</surname><given-names>H. de</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Elbers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Friborg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Heusinkveld</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kabat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Soegaard</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A system to measure surface fluxes of momentum, sensible heat, water vapour and carbon dioxide</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Hydrology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1997-02">1997</year><month>02</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-01-02">2020</year><month>01</month><day>02</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>188-189</volume>
        <issn>00221694</issn>
        <uri>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0022169496031940</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-1694(96)03194-0</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Merbold2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Merbold</surname><given-names>Lutz</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Eugster</surname><given-names>Werner</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stieger</surname><given-names>Jacqueline</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zahniser</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Greenhouse gas budget (CO _{\textrm{2}} , CH _{\textrm{4}} and N _{\textrm{2}} O) of intensively managed grassland following restoration</article-title>
        <source>Global Change Biology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014-06">2014</year><month>06</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-01-02">2020</year><month>01</month><day>02</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>6</issue>
        <issn>13541013</issn>
        <uri>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1111/gcb.12518</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.12518</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-McMillen1988">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>McMillen</surname><given-names>Robert T.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An eddy correlation technique with extended applicability to non-simple terrain</article-title>
        <source>Boundary-Layer Meteorology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1988-05">1988</year><month>05</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-01-02">2020</year><month>01</month><day>02</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>43</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
        <issn>0006-8314, 1573-1472</issn>
        <uri>http://link.springer.com/10.1007/BF00128405</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00128405</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Nemitz2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Nemitz</surname><given-names>Eiko</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mammarella</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ibrom</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Aurela</surname><given-names>Mika</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Burba</surname><given-names>George G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dengel</surname><given-names>Sigrid</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gielen</surname><given-names>Bert</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grelle</surname><given-names>Achim</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Heinesch</surname><given-names>Bernard</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>Mathias</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hörtnagl</surname><given-names>Lukas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Klemedtsson</surname><given-names>Leif</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lindroth</surname><given-names>Anders</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lohila</surname><given-names>Annalea</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McDermitt</surname><given-names>Dayle K.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Merbold</surname><given-names>Lutz</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nicolini</surname><given-names>Giacomo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>Mats B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peltola</surname><given-names>Olli</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rinne</surname><given-names>Janne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zahniser</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Standardisation of eddy-covariance flux measurements of methane and nitrous oxide</article-title>
        <source>International Agrophysics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-12">2018</year><month>12</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-04-16">2020</year><month>04</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <issn>2300-8725</issn>
        <uri>http://archive.sciendo.com/INTAG/intag.2017.32.issue-4/intag-2017-0042/intag-2017-0042.pdf</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/intag-2017-0042</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Hoertnagl2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hörtnagl</surname><given-names>Lukas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Barthel</surname><given-names>Matti</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Buchmann</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Eugster</surname><given-names>Werner</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Butterbach-Bahl</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Díaz-Pinés</surname><given-names>Eugenio</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zeeman</surname><given-names>Matthias</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Klumpp</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kiese</surname><given-names>Ralf</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bahn</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hammerle</surname><given-names>Albin</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Haiyan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ladreiter-Knauss</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Burri</surname><given-names>Susanne</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Merbold</surname><given-names>Lutz</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Greenhouse gas fluxes over managed grasslands in Central Europe</article-title>
        <source>Global Change Biology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-05">2018</year><month>05</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-04-16">2020</year><month>04</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <issue>5</issue>
        <issn>13541013</issn>
        <uri>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1111/gcb.14079</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.14079</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Aubinet2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <source>Eddy Covariance: A Practical Guide to Measurement and Data Analysis</source>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name><surname>Aubinet</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vesala</surname><given-names>Timo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Papale</surname><given-names>Dario</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-07-09">2020</year><month>07</month><day>09</day></date-in-citation>
        <isbn>978-94-007-2350-4 978-94-007-2351-1</isbn>
        <uri>http://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-94-007-2351-1</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-007-2351-1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
