<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">803</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00803</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>ukpopulation: unified national and subnational population
estimates and projections, including variants</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-9951-6642</contrib-id>
<string-name>Andrew P Smith</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-0081-400X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Tom Russell</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>School of Geography and Leeds Institute for Data Analytics,
University of Leeds</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Environmental Change Institute, School of Geography and the
Environment, University of Oxford</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-05-31">
<day>31</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>28</issue>
<fpage>803</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>python</kwd>
<kwd>data science</kwd>
<kwd>population</kwd>
<kwd>projection</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>UK statistics agencies (ONS, StatsWales, NRScotland and NISRA)
  produce mid-year population estimates (MYE), national population
  projections (NPP), and subnational population projections (SNPP), by
  age and gender. Mid-year estimates and subnational population
  projections are at local authority district (or equivalent) geography;
  national projections are produced for England, Wales, Scotland and
  Northern Ireland respectively.</p>
  <p>At the time of writing (June 2018), mid-year estimates are
  available from 1991 to 2016. Subnational population projections
  typically have a 25-year horizon and in most cases cover the period
  2016-2041. National projections have a longer horizon, extending from
  2016 to 2116.</p>
  <p>The datasets are published online in different places and in
  different formats, depending on the originating agency. The data may
  require significant preprocessing/reformatting before it can be used
  programmatically and, crucially, reproducibly.</p>
  <p>Population projection variants (e.g. high fertility) are extremely
  useful for scenario analyses and a number of population projection
  variants are available at national scale. However, the availability of
  variants at subnational scale is patchy at best.</p>
  <p>This python package
  (<xref alt="Smith, 2018" rid="ref-smith_ukpopulationU003A_2018" ref-type="bibr">Smith,
  2018</xref>) aims to unify the retrieval of UK-wide data, providing
  consistent interfaces for each of the three (MYE, SNPP, NPP) datasets.
  For efficiency all data is cached locally.</p>
  <p>The package includes functionality to filter data by geography
  (e.g. for analysis of a single local authority), and/or by age and by
  gender, e.g. for analysis of working-age population.</p>
  <p>It also provides a simple methodology for extrapolating the
  shorter-term SNPP data using the longer-term NPP data. By
  extrapolating the SNPP independently for each age and gender enables
  the age-gender structure of the original population to be captured.
  Aggregation only takes place on the extrapolated age-gender specific
  values. This means that the trends shown by SNPP geographies with
  different age-gender structures, will differ, even though they both
  extrapolate using the same NPP data. (If aggregation was performed
  before the extrapolation it would not be possible to compute different
  extrapolated trends for regions with different initial age-gender
  structures.)</p>
  <p>This functionality enables researchers and policymakers to examine
  population growth trajectories and construct plausible projections,
  both principal and variant, at subnational scale, consistently for
  anywhere in the UK over longer time horizons than the official data
  permit. By automating the process of obtaining and consistently
  formatting the data, the package also makes it much easier to create
  reproducible analyses.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-smith_ukpopulationU003A_2018">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Russell</given-names><suffix>Andrew P</suffix></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>ukpopulation: Unified UK National and Subnational Population Projections</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018-05">2018</year><month>05</month>
        <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2018-05-31">2018</year><month>05</month><day>31</day></date-in-citation>
        <uri>https://github.com/nismod/ukpopulation</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
