<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1532</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01532</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>KinESim: Pre-equilibrium kinetic simulation of
electrochemical reactions</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-1713-1229</contrib-id>
<string-name>Christopher W. John</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-4625-0323</contrib-id>
<string-name>Denis A. Proshlyakov</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Chemistry, Michigan State
University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-07-21">
<day>21</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>40</issue>
<fpage>1532</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Igor Pro</kwd>
<kwd>chemistry</kwd>
<kwd>kinetics</kwd>
<kwd>homogeneous</kwd>
<kwd>heterogeneous</kwd>
<kwd>equilibrium</kwd>
<kwd>electrode</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <sec id="rationale">
    <title>Rationale:</title>
    <p>Electrochemistry studies reduction-oxidation reactions, or
    reactions that involve transfer of an electron, with a particular
    emphasis on the reactions occurring at the interface between the
    electrode and the solution. Multiple electrochemical techniques can
    provide valuable insight into the thermodynamic properties of
    analytes and their chemical mechanisms. Extensive efforts have been
    invested into developing a quantitative description of the dynamics
    of electron transfer and ensuing mass transport where the analyte
    itself can undergo direct reduction/oxidation on the surface of the
    electrode. However, more complex cases where a redox-active analyte
    requires one or more redox-active mediators to transfer an electron
    to/from the electrode received less attention. Additional complexity
    may arise from the kinetic limitations of such multi-step reactions
    and the inherent nature of electrochemistry: it relies on the
    detection of electric currents, which report on the rate of a
    chemical process, while often focusing on the thermodynamic
    properties of the analyte, which represents equilibrium conditions.
    This conundrum requires a balance between detectability (fast
    processes) and accuracy (slow processes). Therefore, in most cases
    electrochemical studies are conducted under pre-equilibrium
    conditions.</p>
    <p>KinESim is a procedure package for Igor Pro that was primarily
    designed to predict pre-equilibrium concentrations and their changes
    in a multi-component, redox-active chemical mixture. In general,
    this includes homogenous electrochemical reactions in the solution
    and heterogenous processes on the solution/electrode boundary.
    Heterogenous electrochemical reactions are controlled by an applied
    electric potential of an arbitrary waveform (continuous or pulsed).
    This allows one to use KinESim to predict pre-equilibrium changes in
    a variety of standard techniques, such as pulse, staircase, or
    cyclic voltammetry, as well as custom potential profiles. KinESim
    supports branching, sequential, and isomerization reactions in
    various stochiometric ratios over both phases. Unlike experimental
    electrochemical methods that report net electric current/charge,
    KinESim provides an insight into changes occurring to the individual
    reagents and their redox sub-population. This is particularly
    significant for spectro-electrochemical and indirect (mediated)
    electrochemical studies where redox changes in the analytes of
    interests may be difficult to detect from the electric current
    alone. Therefore, it can be used to predict experimental data and to
    test proposed reaction mechanisms in most chemical processes
    controlled by a combination of kinetics and thermodynamics. These
    abilities have recently been demonstrated in a study of how
    electrochemical mediators affect the observed electrochemical
    properties of an analyte
    (<xref alt="John et al., 2019" rid="ref-JohnU003A2019b" ref-type="bibr">John
    et al., 2019</xref>;
    <xref alt="John &amp; Proshlyakov, 2019" rid="ref-JohnU003A2019a" ref-type="bibr">John
    &amp; Proshlyakov, 2019</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="concept">
    <title>Concept:</title>
    <p>KinESim is suitable for modeling reactions in a thin solution
    layer over an electrode. It distinguishes two phases, electrode and
    solution, with mass transport between them. The current version
    makes an assumption that diffusion within the solution, in the
    direction perpendicular to the electrode, is fast relative to the
    process being modeled. In other words, the concentration of any
    analyte throughout the solution is uniform. KinESim implements a
    deterministic kinetics model for a continuous-time Markov process
    (<xref alt="Anderson &amp; Kurtz, 2011" rid="ref-AndersonU003A2011" ref-type="bibr">Anderson
    &amp; Kurtz, 2011</xref>;
    <xref alt="Zhang et al., 2019" rid="ref-ZhangU003A2018" ref-type="bibr">Zhang
    et al., 2019</xref>). Reactions in the solution and on the
    electrode, as well as adsorption/desorption processes are described
    by a system of ordinary differential equation (ODEs) derived from
    differential rate laws. Numerical integration of such system of ODEs
    using initial conditions, reaction order, and rate or equilibrium
    constants provided by the user yields time-dependent concentrations
    of all components. In addition, potential applied to the electrode
    controls electrochemical kinetics per the Butler-Volmer
    equation.</p>
    <p>ODEs are integrated using the 4th-order Runge-Kutta method. This
    integration method includes a built-in adaptive timing method to
    minimize both the amount of error in each calculation and the amount
    of time needed to complete the simulation. The adaptive timing
    algorithm is particularly beneficial when KinESim is used with
    nonmonotonic processes. Since the simulation makes no assumption
    about the applied potential waveform, it gives the user full
    flexibility in the experimental design at the expense of
    computational uncertainty in the future progression of the reaction
    (which distinguishes KinESim from traditional simulations of
    chemical kinetics). Balance between computational time and accuracy
    is achieved by establishing boundary conditions for relative
    concentration changes. This allows for dynamic changes in the
    simulation time granularity if the chemical system is rapidly
    shifted off-equilibrium by large changes in the applied
    potential.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgments">
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>
  <p>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health grants
  GM096132 and EY028049.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-JohnU003A2019a">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>John</surname><given-names>Christopher W.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Proshlyakov</surname><given-names>Denis A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fourier transform infrared spectrovoltammetry and quantitative modeling of analytes in kinetically constrained redox mixtures</article-title>
        <source>Analytical Chemistry</source>
        <publisher-name>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>91</volume>
        <issue>15</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.9b00859</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-JohnU003A2019b">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>John</surname><given-names>Christopher W.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>Greg M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hausinger</surname><given-names>Robert P.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Proshlyakov</surname><given-names>Denis A.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Strongly coupled redox-linked conformational switching at the active site of the non-heme iron-dependent dioxygenase, TauD</article-title>
        <source>The Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source>
        <publisher-name>American Chemical Society (ACS)</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-08">2019</year><month>08</month>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpcb.9b05866</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-AndersonU003A2011">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>David F.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>Thomas G.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Continuous Time Markov Chain Models for Chemical Reaction Networks</source>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name><surname>Koeppl</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Setti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>di Bernardo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Densmore</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4419-6766-4_1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ZhangU003A2018">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Chuan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Ziyuan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Zaichen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>You</surname><given-names>Xiaohu</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Molecular computing for Markov chains</article-title>
        <source>Natural Computing</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019-04">2019</year><month>04</month>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11047-019-09736-8</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11047-019-09736-8</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
