<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3175</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03175</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>HyRiver: Hydroclimate Data Retriever</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5430-6000</contrib-id>
<string-name>Taher Chegini</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-9807-3851</contrib-id>
<string-name>Hong-Yi Li</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3221-9467</contrib-id>
<string-name>L. Ruby Leung</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Houston</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-02-26">
<day>26</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>66</issue>
<fpage>3175</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>hydrology</kwd>
<kwd>climate</kwd>
<kwd>web services</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Over the last decade, increasing availability of web services for
  hydrology and climatology data has facilitated publication of
  reproducible scientific research in hydrological and climate studies.
  Such web services allow researchers to subset big databases and
  perform some common data processing operations on the server-side.
  However, implementing such services increases the technical complexity
  of code development as it requires sufficient understanding of their
  underlying protocols to generate valid queries and filters.
  <monospace>HyRiver</monospace> bridges this gap by providing a unified
  and simple Application Programming Interface (API) to web services
  that are based on three of the most commonly used protocols for
  geo-spatial/temporal data publication: REpresentational State Transfer
  (RESTful), Web Feature Services (WFS), and Web Map Services (WMS).
  <monospace>HyRiver</monospace> is a software stack consisting of the
  following seven Python packages:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cheginit/pygeohydro">PyGeoHydro</ext-link>:
      Provides access to NWIS (National Water Information System), NID
      (National Inventory of Dams), HCDN-2009 (Hydro-Climatic Data
      Network), NLCD (National Land Cover Database), and SSEBop
      (operational Simplified Surface Energy Balance) databases.
      Moreover, it can generate an interactive map for exploring NWIS
      stations within a bounding box, compute categorical statistics of
      land use/land cover data, and plot five hydrologic signature
      graphs. There is also a helper function which returns a roughness
      coefficients lookup table for NLCD’s land cover types. These
      coefficients can be useful for overland flow routing among other
      applications.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cheginit/pynhd">PyNHD</ext-link>:
      Provides the ability to navigate and subset National Hydrography
      Database
      (<xref alt="Buto &amp; Anderson, 2020" rid="ref-Buto_2020" ref-type="bibr">Buto
      &amp; Anderson, 2020</xref>), at medium- and high-resolution,
      using NLDI (Hydro Network-Linked Data Index), WaterData, and TNM
      (The National Map) web services. Additionally, it can retrieve
      over 30 catchment-scale attributes from
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5669a79ee4b08895842a1d47">ScienceBase</ext-link>
      and
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hydroshare.org/resource/6092c8a62fac45be97a09bfd0b0bf726">NHDPlus
      Value Added Attributes</ext-link> that are linked to the NHDPlus
      database via Common Identifiers (ComIDs).
      <monospace>PyNHD</monospace> has some additional river network
      tools that use NHDPlus data for routing through a river network.
      This flow routing module is general and accepts any user-defined
      transport equation for computing flow accumulation through a given
      river network. It sorts the river network topologically from
      upstream to downstream, then accumulates a given attribute based
      on the user-defined transport equation.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cheginit/py3dep">Py3DEP</ext-link>:
      Gives access to topographic data through the 3D Elevation Program
      (3DEP) service
      (<xref alt="Thatcher et al., 2020" rid="ref-Thatcher_2020" ref-type="bibr">Thatcher
      et al., 2020</xref>). This package can pull 12 types of
      topographic data from the 3DEP service, such as Digital Elevation
      Model, slope, aspect, and hillshade.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cheginit/pydaymet">PyDaymet</ext-link>:
      Retrieves daily climate data as well as their monthly and annual
      summaries from the Daymet dataset
      (<xref alt="Thornton et al., 2020" rid="ref-Thornton_2020" ref-type="bibr">Thornton
      et al., 2020</xref>). It is possible to request data for a single
      location as well as a grid (any valid geometrical shape) at 1-km
      spatial resolution.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cheginit/pygeoogc">PyGeoOGC</ext-link>:
      Generates valid queries for retrieving data from supported
      RESTful-, WMS-, and WFS-based services. Although these web
      services limit the number of features in a single query,
      under-the-hood, <monospace>PyGeoOGC</monospace> takes care of
      breaking down a large query into smaller queries according to
      specifications of the services. Additionally, this package offers
      several notable utilities, such as data re-projection and
      asynchronous data retrieval for speeding up sending/receiving
      queries.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cheginit/pygeoutils">PyGeoUtils</ext-link>:
      Converts responses from PyGeoOGC’s supported web services to
      geo-dataframes (vector data type) or datasets (raster data type).
      Moreover, for gridded data, it can mask the output dataset based
      on any given geometry.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cheginit/async_retriever">AsyncRetriever</ext-link>:
      <monospace>AsyncRetriever</monospace> has only one purpose;
      asynchronously sending requests and retrieving responses as
      <monospace>text</monospace>, <monospace>binary</monospace>, or
      <monospace>json</monospace> objects. It uses persistent caching to
      speedup the retrieval even further.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>These packages are standalone and users can install and work with
  them independently. Furthermore, <monospace>PyGeoOGC</monospace>,
  <monospace>PyGeoUtils</monospace>, and
  <monospace>AsyncRetriever</monospace> are low-level engines of this
  software stack that the other four packages utilize for providing
  access to some of the most popular databases in the hydrology
  community. These two low-level packages are generic and developers can
  use them for connecting and sending queries to any other web services
  that are based on the protocols that <monospace>HyRiver</monospace>
  supports. Currently, <monospace>HyRiver</monospace> only supports
  hydrology and climatology datasets within the US.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>Preparing input data for conducting studies, is often one of the
  most time-consuming steps. The difficulties of processing such input
  data stem from the diverse data sources and types as well as sizes.
  For example, hydrological modeling of watersheds might require climate
  data such as precipitation and temperature, topology data such as
  Digital Elevation Model, and a river network. Climate and topology
  data are available in raster format, and river network could be from a
  vector data type. Additionally, these datasets often have large sizes
  and subsetting operations can be computationally demanding. Geospatial
  web services can carry out subsetting and some common geographic
  information system (GIS) operations on server-side. However, these
  services usually have different specifications, thus implementing them
  can be technically challanging. Moreover, since the underlying
  protocols of these web services are under active development by
  organizations such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ogc.org">Open
  Geospatial Consortium</ext-link>, keeping track of the latest
  developments adds another level of complexity.
  <monospace>HyRiver</monospace> removes these barriers by providing
  consistent and simple, yet configurable, interfaces to these web
  services. Since these interfaces are web protocol-specific, not web
  service-specific, researchers can utilize
  <monospace>HyRiver</monospace> to access a plethora of databases that
  are offered through RESTFul-, WFS-, and WMS-based services.</p>
  <p>There are several open-source packages that offer similar
  functionalities. For example,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mroberge/hydrofunctions">hydrofunctions</ext-link>
  is a Python package that retrieves streamflow data from NWIS and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ulmo-dev/ulmo">ulmo</ext-link>
  is another Python package that provides access to several public
  hydrology and climatology data.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/sentinel-hub/sentinelhub-py">Sentinelhub-py</ext-link>
  can download and process satellite images from six data sources
  through Python. <monospace>Dataretrieval</monospace> gives access to
  some of the USGS (United States Geological Survey) databases and has
  two versions in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/USGS-R/dataRetrieval">R</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/USGS-python/dataretrieval">Python</ext-link>.
  Another R Package called
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mikejohnson51/HydroData">HydroData</ext-link>,
  provides access to 15 earth system datasets. Although there are
  overlaps between <monospace>HyRiver</monospace> and these packages, to
  the best of our knowledge, none of them offer access to the diverse
  data sources and types that this software stack provides.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>T. Chegini was supported by the University of Houston’s internal
  funds and the US National Science Foundation (EAR #1804560). H.-Y. Li
  and L. R. Leung were supported by the U.S. Department of Energy Office
  of Science Biological and Environmental Research as part of the Earth
  System Model Development and Regional and Global Model Analysis
  program areas through the collaborative, multi-program Integrated
  Coastal Modeling (ICoM) project. PNNL is operated for the Department
  of Energy by Battelle Memorial Institute under contract
  DE-AC05-76RL01830.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-Thornton_2020">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Daymet: Daily Surface Weather Data on a 1-km Grid for North America, Version 4</article-title>
        <publisher-name>ORNL Distributed Active Archive Center</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <uri>https://daac.ornl.gov/cgi-bin/dsviewer.pl?ds_id=1840</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1840</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Thatcher_2020">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Thatcher</surname><given-names>Cindy A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lukas</surname><given-names>Vicki</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>Jason M.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The 3D Elevation Program and energy for the Nation</article-title>
        <publisher-name>US Geological Survey</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.3133%2Ffs20193051</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3133/fs20193051</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Buto_2020">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Buto</surname><given-names>Susan G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Rebecca D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>NHDPlus high resolution (NHDPlus HR) – a hydrography framework for the Nation</article-title>
        <publisher-name>US Geological Survey</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <uri>https://doi.org/10.3133%2Ffs20203033</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3133/fs20203033</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
