<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2957</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02957</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>nf-gwas-pipeline: A Nextflow Genome-Wide Association
Study Pipeline</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Zeyuan Song</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Anastasia Gurinovich</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Anthony Federico</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Stefano Monti</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Paola Sebastiani</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Biostatistics, Boston University School of
Public Health, 801 Massachusetts Avenue 3rd Floor, Boston, MA 02218,
USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Section of Computational Biomedicine, Boston University
School of Medicine, 72 East Concord St., Boston, MA 02218,
USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Institute for Clinical Research and Health Policy Studies,
Tufts Medical Center, 800 Washington Street, Boston, MA 02111,
USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-4">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Bioinformatics Program, Boston University, 24 Cummington
Mall, Boston, MA 02215, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-11-21">
<day>21</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>59</issue>
<fpage>2957</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Nextflow</kwd>
<kwd>GWAS</kwd>
<kwd>gene-based analysis</kwd>
<kwd>longitudianl GWAS</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>A tool for conducting Genome-Wide Association Study (GWAS) in a
  systematic, automated and reproducible manner is overdue. We developed
  an automated GWAS pipeline by combining multiple analysis tools –
  including bcftools, vcftools, the R packages SNPRelate/GENESIS/GMMAT
  and ANNOVAR – through Nextflow, which is a portable, flexible, and
  reproducible reactive workflow framework for developing pipelines. The
  GWAS pipeline integrates the steps of data quality control and
  assessment and genetic association analyses, including analysis of
  cross-sectional and longitudinal studies with either single variants
  or gene-based tests, into a unified analysis workflow. The pipeline is
  implemented in Nextflow, dependencies are distributed through Docker,
  and the code is publicly available on Github.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>Genome-Wide Association Studies (GWAS) have led to the discovery of
  highly reproducible variants associated with human complex traits and
  diseases
  (<xref alt="Tam V et al., 2019" rid="ref-TamU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Tam
  V et al., 2019</xref>). Many software tools are available for
  conducting GWAS using cross-sectional data and standard multivariable
  linear or logistic regression. However, the analysis of longitudinal
  or family-based studies requires the use of advanced statistical
  methods such as mixed effect modeling, or survival analysis. To
  conduct a GWAS with such complex data, often investigators have to
  rely on multiple programs and ad-hoc linking the results generated
  between steps because each program focuses on a specific aspect of the
  analysis
  (<xref alt="Eller RJ et al., 2019" rid="ref-EllerU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Eller
  RJ et al., 2019</xref>). This approach makes it difficult to keep
  track of all the analysis steps and parameters, including data
  cleaning, filtering, and calculation of the genome-wide principal
  components, limiting reproducibility of the analyses. To address these
  problems, we have developed a GWAS pipeline that provides a
  comprehensive computing environment to manage genome-wide genotype
  data, to conduct analyses of continuous and binary traits using mixed
  effect models, and to summarize, annotate, and visualize the
  results.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="materials-and-methods">
  <title>Materials and Methods</title>
  <sec id="features">
    <title>Features</title>
    <p>The pipeline is implemented in Nextflow, a portable, scalable and
    parallelizable reactive workflow framework for data-intensive
    pipelines
    (<xref alt="Di Tommaso P et al., 2017" rid="ref-DiU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Di
    Tommaso P et al., 2017</xref>). Through Nextflow, the GWAS pipeline
    is designed to automatically parallelize workflow steps, denoted as
    processes, and does not require users to manually handle
    intermediate data between steps, thus improving traceability and
    reproducibility. Additionally, the pipeline remains flexible
    allowing users to customize parameters and options in the
    configuration file. Adding processes (i.e., additional analytical
    steps) in Nextflow framework is standardized and simple. Advanced
    Nextflow users can define and incorporate additional processes in
    the pipeline framework, which will then be executed as part of the
    customized pipeline.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="workflow">
    <title>Workflow</title>
    <p>Figure 1 depicts the workflow:</p>
    <list list-type="order">
      <list-item>
        <p>Input. Required files include VCF files for all 22
        chromosomes and a comma-delimited phenotype file including
        sample id, phenotype and covariates. Optionally, users can
        provide a file with a list of Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms
        (SNPs) to compute genome-wide principal components and genetic
        relationship or provide a kinship matrix for known
        relations.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Quality control. The pipeline removes monomorphic SNPs and
        variants with percent of missing values above a provided
        threshold. The cleaned VCF files are then converted into Genome
        Data Structure (GDS) file format for computationally efficient
        data storage
        (<xref alt="Zheng X et al., 2017" rid="ref-ZhengU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Zheng
        X et al., 2017</xref>).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Principal component analysis and genetic relationship
        inference. This is an optional step that uses the PC-AiR and
        PC-Relate algorithms [Conomos MP et al.
        (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-ConomosU003A2015" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>)](<xref alt="Conomos MP et al., 2016" rid="ref-ConomosU003A2016" ref-type="bibr">Conomos
        MP et al., 2016</xref>) to estimate the genetic relationship
        matrix between study subjects (GRM) and genome-wide principal
        components (PCs) to adjust for population structure. Users have
        the option to provide their own PCs as covariates and/or
        GRM.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Association tests. The pipeline can conduct three types of
        analyses of qualitative and quantitative traits: GWAS of
        individual SNPs, gene-based tests, and genome-wide longitudinal
        analyses, by turning on the corresponding logical options in the
        configuration file. All three analyses fit a null model first
        and then iterate over the whole genome by testing one variant or
        gene at a time. The tests for cross-sectional data are based on
        the R package GENESIS
        (<xref alt="Gogarten SM et al., 2019" rid="ref-GogartenU003A2019" ref-type="bibr">Gogarten
        SM et al., 2019</xref>). The test for longitudinal data is based
        on the R package GMMAT, which uses generalized mixed effect
        models
        (<xref alt="Chen H et al., 2016" rid="ref-ChenU003A2016" ref-type="bibr">Chen
        H et al., 2016</xref>).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>Output and Visualization. Manhattan and QQ-plots with the
        value of genomic control are generated for any of the three
        analyses. The output file includes SNP results annotated with
        ANNOVAR and minor allele frequency (MAF) for any subgroup of
        individuals defined by the users. Finally, an html-report of the
        analysis is generated.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
  </sec>
  <sec id="configuration-file">
    <title>Configuration file</title>
    <p>A single configuration file containing all the pipeline options
    and parameters is provided. Users can customize this file to deploy
    specific analysis processes. For example, a user may run a GWAS on a
    cohort of unrelated individuals by turning off the GRM step. To
    reduce the complexity for new users, only essential parameters are
    modifiable in the configuration file. Advanced users can modify any
    parameters by diving into the original code.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="installation-and-execution">
    <title>Installation and Execution</title>
    <p>The pipeline can be cloned from
    https://github.com/montilab/nf-gwas-pipeline. A Docker container was
    built to assist in installing the necessary tools and the pipeline
    and ensuring accessibility to specific versions of tools and
    packages. There are two methods for executing the pipeline. Users
    can execute the pipeline through the command line interface
    specifying parameters and a configuration file. All available
    options can be either obtained by the command ‘–help’ or from the
    configuration file. If a configuration file is specified, users
    should set paths for all input files and specify the analysis with
    corresponding parameters. Once file paths and parameters are set,
    the execution can be either run locally or scaled up to various
    high-performance computing environments.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="output-and-error-handling">
    <title>Output and Error Handling</title>
    <p>Output files are automatically arranged in a nested folder
    structure (Fig. 1). Each lowest-level subfolder holds output and log
    files from executed process. In addition, Nextflow creates its own
    work folder to hold intermediate output files, which serves as a
    record of a run. If errors are encountered in a run, users can fix
    the specific error and re-run the pipeline with the “-resume”
    command. Once resumed, the pipeline automatically uses the cached
    files from the previous run and continues processes that have been
    fixed
    (<xref alt="Di Tommaso P et al., 2017" rid="ref-DiU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Di
    Tommaso P et al., 2017</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusions-and-discussions">
  <title>Conclusions and Discussions</title>
  <p>The GWAS pipeline provides a user-friendly one-step analysis tool.
  The workflow balances flexibility and reproducibility by requiring
  limited options and parameters. To run more study- specific analyses,
  users may need to modify some parameters in the original scripts.
  While three types of analyses are currently available, the
  Nextflow-based pipeline is easy to extend with new tools and methods.
  We plan to include more complex models and analyses, such as survival
  analysis, in the next versions of the pipeline.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="figures">
  <title>Figures</title>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Figure 1</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="nf-gwas-pipeline.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We thank for Harold Bae and Aparna Bhutkar for their help. This
  work was supported with funding from NIH/NIA: U19AG023122 (Longevity
  Consortium), and UH2AG064704 (Omics Profiles in Centenarians).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-TamU003A2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Tam V</string-name>
          <string-name>Patel N</string-name>
          <string-name>Turcotte M</string-name>
          <string-name>Bossé Y</string-name>
          <string-name>Paré G</string-name>
          <string-name>Meyre D</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Benefits and limitations of genome- wide association studies</article-title>
        <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41576-019-0127-1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-EllerU003A2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Eller RJ</string-name>
          <string-name>Janga SC</string-name>
          <string-name>Walsh S</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Odyssey: a semi-automated pipeline for phasing, imputation, and analysis of genome-wide genetic data</article-title>
        <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-019-2964-5</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-DiU003A2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Di Tommaso P</string-name>
          <string-name>Chatzou M</string-name>
          <string-name>Floden EW</string-name>
          <string-name>Barja PP</string-name>
          <string-name>Palumbo E</string-name>
          <string-name>Notredame C</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Nextflow enables reproducible computational workflows</article-title>
        <source>Nat. Biotechnol</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3820</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ZhengU003A2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Zheng X</string-name>
          <string-name>Gogarten SM</string-name>
          <string-name>Lawrence M</string-name>
          <string-name>et al</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SeqArray-a storage-efficient high-performance data format for WGS variant calls</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>33</volume>
        <issue>15</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btx145</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ConomosU003A2015">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Conomos MP</string-name>
          <string-name>Miller MB</string-name>
          <string-name>Thornton TA</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Robust inference of population structure for ancestry prediction and correction of stratification in the presence of relatedness</article-title>
        <source>Genet Epidemiol</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
        <volume>39</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gepi.21896</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ConomosU003A2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Conomos MP</string-name>
          <string-name>Reiner AP</string-name>
          <string-name>Weir BS</string-name>
          <string-name>Thornton TA</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Model-free Estimation of Recent Genetic Relatedness</article-title>
        <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>98</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2015.11.022</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-GogartenU003A2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Gogarten SM</string-name>
          <string-name>Sofer T</string-name>
          <string-name>Chen H</string-name>
          <string-name>et al</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Genetic association testing using the GENESIS R/Bioconductor package</article-title>
        <source>Bioinformatics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>35</volume>
        <issue>24</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz567</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ChenU003A2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <string-name>Chen H</string-name>
          <string-name>Wang C</string-name>
          <string-name>Conomos MP</string-name>
          <string-name>et al</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Control for Population Structure and Relatedness for Binary Traits in Genetic Association Studies via Logistic Mixed Models</article-title>
        <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>98</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2016.02.012</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
