<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1203</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01203</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>BladeX: Python Blade Morphing</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9507-9468</contrib-id>
<string-name>Mahmoud Gadalla</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9747-6328</contrib-id>
<string-name>Marco Tezzele</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4483-0212</contrib-id>
<string-name>Andrea Mola</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-0810-8812</contrib-id>
<string-name>Gianluigi Rozza</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>International School of Advanced Studies, SISSA, Trieste,
Italy</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-01-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>34</issue>
<fpage>1203</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Blade construction</kwd>
<kwd>Blade morphing</kwd>
<kwd>CAD files</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Marine propeller blade shape is constantly studied by engineers to
  obtain designs that allow for enhanced hydrodynamic performance while
  reducing vibrations and noise emissions. In such framework, shape
  parametrization and morphing algorithms are crucial elements of the
  numerical simulation and prototyping environment required for the
  evaluation of new blade geometries. From a practical standpoint, a
  propeller blade is uniquely described by the following parameters: the
  shape of a certain number of sectional profiles, complemented by the
  pitch, skew, rake, and chord length values corresponding to each
  section along the radial direction. Taking such parameters into
  account we are able to construct a blade and, parametrizing the
  aforementioned quantities by spline reconstruction, we are able to
  morph every single section. This results in a morphing tool that
  expands in a non-intrusive way the naval engineering consolidated
  design techniques. In particular, we followed Carlton
  (<xref alt="2012" rid="ref-carlton2012marine" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>)
  for marine propeller blades construction, conventions, and
  terminology.</p>
  <p>In the BladeX Python package, we implemented the bottom-up
  construction of blades given the radial distribution of pitch, skew,
  rake, chord, and camber of the sectional profiles. We also provide
  several tutorials showing how to construct or import sectional
  profiles in 2D and then how to generate the desired 3D representation
  of the blade. It is also possible to export the final design in CAD
  files such as iges and stl. Even if the focus is on marine propeller
  blades, the software is general enough to produce, for instance,
  aircraft wings or wind turbine blades. It is particularly suited for
  simulation-driven design shape optimization.</p>
  <p>The package has already been used within the research project
  PRELICA, “Advanced methodologies for hydro-acoustic design of naval
  propulsion,” with both industrial and academic partners, and some
  results can be found in Tezzele et al.
  (<xref alt="2018" rid="ref-tezzele2018ecmi" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).
  This highlights that the target user of this package is either a
  numerical analyst working in academia or a skilled engineer working in
  the naval construction field.</p>
  <p>As an example, we show below a bottom-up construction of a
  benchmark blade called PPTC, and the resulting iges and stl file
  formats.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Bottom-up construction of the PPTC benchmark blade, and
    the resulting iges and stl file.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="../readme/PPTC.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>Here we have the undeformed reference blade and a couple of
  deformed configurations obtained by moving some control points
  defining the skew and chord length radial distributions.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Undeformed blade, on the left, and two deformed
    configurations.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="../readme/blade_deformations.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This work was partially supported by the project PRELICA, “Advanced
  methodologies for hydro-acoustic design of naval propulsion”,
  supported by Regione FVG, POR-FESR 2014-2020, Piano Operativo
  Regionale Fondo Europeo per lo Sviluppo Regionale, and by European
  Union Funding for Research and Innovation — Horizon 2020 Program — in
  the framework of European Research Council Executive Agency: H2020 ERC
  CoG 2015 AROMA-CFD project 681447 “Advanced Reduced Order Methods with
  Applications in Computational Fluid Dynamics” P.I. Gianluigi
  Rozza.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-carlton2012marine">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Carlton</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Marine propellers and propulsion</source>
        <publisher-name>Butterworth-Heinemann</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-tezzele2018ecmi">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Tezzele</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Demo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mola</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rozza</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An integrated data-driven computational pipeline with model order reduction for industrial and applied mathematics</article-title>
        <source>Submitted, Special Volume ECMI</source>
        <publisher-name>https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.12364</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
