<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1179</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01179</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>CITapp - a response time-based Concealed Information Test
lie detector web application</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9401-4830</contrib-id>
<string-name>Gáspár Lukács</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Vienna, Department of Basic Psychological
Research and Research Methods, Austria</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-01-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>34</issue>
<fpage>1179</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>concealed information test</kwd>
<kwd>deception detection</kwd>
<kwd>lie detection</kwd>
<kwd>response time</kwd>
<kwd>javascript</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Undetected deception may have extremely high costs in certain
  scenarios, such as counterterrorism, pre-employment screening for
  intelligence agencies, or high-stake criminal proceedings. However,
  meta-analyses have repeatedly shown that without special aid, based on
  their own best judgment only, people (including police officers,
  detectives, and professional judges) distinguish lies from truth on a
  level hardly better than mere chance
  (<xref alt="Hartwig &amp; Bond, 2011" rid="ref-hartwig2011" ref-type="bibr">Hartwig
  &amp; Bond, 2011</xref>).</p>
  <p>The response time-based Concealed Information Test (RT-CIT) aims to
  reveal whether a person is concealing knowledge regarding a certain
  detail
  (<xref alt="Seymour et al., 2000" rid="ref-seymour2000" ref-type="bibr">Seymour
  et al., 2000</xref>). To illustrate the CIT, let us consider a murder
  case scenario in which the murder weapon is known only to the
  perpetrator and the investigators. In this case, the CIT could include
  the actual murder weapon (the probe; e.g. “rifle”) and several other
  weapons (irrelevants; e.g. “knife,” and “rope”) as the items that
  would be sequentially presented to a suspect in a random order. When
  each item has to be responded to with a keypress, the recognition of
  the probe (in this case, “rifle”) by a guilty person (who is aware of
  the relevance of that item) will typically result in a slower response
  to that item than to the irrelevant items. Thereby, based on the
  probe-irrelevant RT differences, a guilty person can be distinguished
  from innocent ones.</p>
  <p>The standard RT-CIT includes a single (randomly chosen) target
  irrelevant item that requires pressing a response key different from
  the response key for probe and other, nontarget irrelevant items. For
  example, the key “I” has to be pressed whenever the target item
  appears, while the key “E” has to be pressed whenever any of the other
  items (probe and nontarget irrelevants) appear. This target item,
  which appears at random times, ensures that the examinees keep paying
  attention to the changing items. However, a recent study improved this
  method by including additional filler items that, similarly as the
  target, appear randomly throughout the task and have to be categorized
  with one of the two response keys. These were hypothesized to induce
  even closer attention to the items, and hence also to the probe
  (<xref alt="Lukács et al., 2017" rid="ref-lukacs2017" ref-type="bibr">Lukács
  et al., 2017</xref>). This method robustly increased the CIT accuracy
  in distinguishing guilty examinees from innocent ones. This enhanced
  version, however, is much more difficult to implement, especially due
  to the complex randomization rules in respect of the filler items.
  Therefore, the primary aim of this application is to provide a readily
  available tool for the independent testing and replication of this
  method.</p>
  <p>This application requires no technical knowledge; it can simply be
  opened and used in a Google Chrome browser. Furthermore, by uploading
  it on any server, it can also be made available online, where it can
  then be easily accessed anytime, from anywhere. Once loaded into the
  browser, it may again be used offline as well. One such online version
  is always available directly via the site of the repository itself:
  https://gasparl.github.io/citapp_pc/CITapp.html.</p>
  <p>The details and settings of the test can be entered and selected,
  including the specification of the probe, irrelevant, and target
  items, on the start page; see Figure 1. After these basic information
  details are given, the test may be initiated. The examinee then simply
  has to follow the instructions on the screen. The full results data
  (and also a preliminary evaluation) are automatically provided and
  downloadable after the completion of the test.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Start page screenshot.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="startpage.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>This is, at the same time, the very first publicly available
  application for a valid, scientifically proven lie detection method.
  While for now it is only intended for research purposes, this may
  provide the basis of a freely available test that in the future may be
  used by appropriate investigative and other authorities all over the
  world.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="note">
  <title>Note</title>
  <p>The basic framework of this application was first used in a recent
  online study; the resulting manuscript is currently under review
  (<xref alt="Lukács &amp; Ansorge, 2019" rid="ref-lukacs2019" ref-type="bibr">Lukács
  &amp; Ansorge, 2019</xref>). An even more similar offline version is
  being used in a currently ongoing experiment. Still, even compared to
  the latter, the vital difference in the present application is the
  user interface that allows the task to be easily administered without
  any technical expertise.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgments">
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>
  <p>Gáspár Lukács is a recipient of a DOC Fellowship of the Austrian
  Academy of Sciences at the Institute for Basic Psychological Research
  at the University of Vienna. Thanks to Bennett Kleinberg for
  inspiration.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-lukacs2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Lukács</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kleinberg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Verschuere</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Familiarity-related fillers improve the validity of reaction time-based memory detection</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Applied Research in Memory and Cognition</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jarmac.2017.01.013</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-lukacs2019">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Lukács</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ansorge</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Information leakage in the response time-based concealed information test. Manuscript submitted</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-seymour2000">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shafto</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mosmann</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Using response time measures to assess &quot;guilty knowledge&quot;</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year>
        <volume>85</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037//0021-9010.85.1.30</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-hartwig2011">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hartwig</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Why do lie-catchers fail? A lens model meta-analysis of human lie judgments</article-title>
        <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
        <volume>137</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0023589</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
