<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2523</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02523</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>causal-curve: A Python Causal Inference Package to
Estimate Causal Dose-Response Curves</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0363-9662</contrib-id>
<string-name>Roni W. Kobrosly</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Environmental Medicine and Public Health,
Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, NY, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Flowcast, 44 Tehama St, San Francisco, CA,
USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-07-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>52</issue>
<fpage>2523</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>causal inference</kwd>
<kwd>causality</kwd>
<kwd>machine learning</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>In academia and industry, randomized controlled experiments
  (colloquially “A/B tests”) are considered the gold standard approach
  for assessing the impact of a treatment or intervention. However, for
  ethical or financial reasons, these experiments may not always be
  feasible to carry out. “Causal inference” methods are a set of
  approaches that attempt to estimate causal effects from observational
  rather than experimental data, correcting for the biases that are
  inherent to analyzing observational data (e.g. confounding and
  selection bias)
  (<xref alt="Hernán &amp; Robins, 2020" rid="ref-HernánU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Hernán
  &amp; Robins, 2020</xref>).</p>
  <p>Although significant research and implementation effort has gone
  towards methods in causal inference to estimate the effects of binary
  treatments (e.g. what was the effect of treatment “A” or “B”?), much
  less has gone towards estimating the effects of continuous treatments.
  This is unfortunate because there are a great number of inquiries in
  research and industry that could benefit from tools to estimate the
  effect of continuous treatments, such as estimating how:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>the number of minutes per week of aerobic exercise causes
      positive health outcomes, after controlling for confounding
      effects.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>increasing or decreasing the price of a product would impact
      demand (price elasticity).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>changing neighborhood income inequality (as measured by the
      continuous Gini index) might or might not be causally related to
      the neighborhood crime rate.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>blood lead levels are causally related to neurodevelopment
      delays in children.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p><monospace>causal-curve</monospace> is a Python package created to
  address this gap; it is designed to perform causal inference when the
  treatment of interest is continuous in nature. From the observational
  data that is provided by the user, it estimates the “causal
  dose-response curve” (or simply the “causal curve”).</p>
  <p>In the current release of the package there are two unique model
  classes for constructing the causal dose-response curve: the
  Generalized Propensity Score (GPS) and the Targetted Maximum
  Likelihood Estimation (TMLE) tools. There is also tool to assess
  causal mediation effects in the presence of a continuous mediator and
  treatment.</p>
  <p><monospace>causal-curve</monospace> attempts to make the
  user-experience as painless as possible:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>This package’s API was designed to resemble that of
      <monospace>scikit-learn</monospace>, as this is a commonly used
      Python predictive modeling framework familiar to most machine
      learning practitioners.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>All of the major classes contained in
      <monospace>causal-curve</monospace> readily use Pandas DataFrames
      and Series as inputs, to make this package more easily integrate
      with the standard Python data analysis tools.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>A full, end-to-end example of applying the package to a causal
      inference problem (the analysis of health data) is provided. In
      addition to this, there are shorter tutorials for each of the
      three major classes are available online in the documentation,
      along with full documentation of all of their parameters, methods,
      and attributes.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>This package includes a suite of unit and integration tests made
  using the pytest framework. The repo containing the latest project
  code is integrated with TravisCI for continuous integration. Code
  coverage is monitored via codecov and is presently above 90%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="methods">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>The <monospace>GPS</monospace> method was originally described by
  Hirano
  (<xref alt="Hirano &amp; Imbens, 2004" rid="ref-HiranoU003A2004" ref-type="bibr">Hirano
  &amp; Imbens, 2004</xref>), and expanded by Moodie
  (<xref alt="Moodie &amp; Stephen, 2010" rid="ref-MoodieU003A2010" ref-type="bibr">Moodie
  &amp; Stephen, 2010</xref>) and more recently by Galagate
  (<xref alt="Galagate, 2016" rid="ref-GalagateU003A2016" ref-type="bibr">Galagate,
  2016</xref>). GPS is an extension of the standard propensity tool
  method and is essentially the treatment assignment density calculated
  at a particular treatment (and covariate) value. Similar to the
  standard propensity score approach, the GPS random variable is used to
  balance covariates. At the core of this tool, generalized linear
  models are used to estimate the GPS, and generalized additive models
  are used to estimate the smoothed final causal curve. Compared with
  this package’s TMLE method, this GPS method is more computationally
  efficient, better suited for large datasets, but produces
  significantly wider confidence intervals.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Example of a causal curve generated by the GPS
    tool.<styled-content id="figU003Aexample"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="welcome_plot.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>The <monospace>TMLE</monospace> method is based on van der Laan’s
  work on an approach to causal inference that would employ powerful
  machine learning approaches to estimate a causal effect
  (<xref alt="van der Laan &amp; Gruber, 2010" rid="ref-van_der_LaanU003A2010" ref-type="bibr">van
  der Laan &amp; Gruber, 2010</xref>). TMLE involves predicting the
  outcome from the treatment and covariates using a machine learning
  model, then predicting treatment assignment from the covariates. TMLE
  also employs a substitution “targeting” step to correct for covariate
  imbalance and to estimate an unbiased causal effect. Currently, there
  is no implementation of TMLE that is suitable for continuous
  treatments. The implemention in <monospace>causal-curve</monospace>
  constructs the final curve through a series of binary treatment
  comparisons across the user-specified range of treatment values and
  then by connecting them. Compared with the package’s GPS method, this
  TMLE method is double robust against model misspecification,
  incorporates more powerful machine learning techniques internally,
  produces significantly smaller confidence intervals, however it is
  less computationally efficient.</p>
  <p><monospace>causal-curve</monospace> allows for continuous mediation
  assessment with the <monospace>Mediation</monospace> tool. As
  described by Imai this approach provides a general approach to
  mediation analysis that invokes the potential outcomes /
  counterfactual framework
  (<xref alt="Imai &amp; Tingley, 2010" rid="ref-ImaiU003A2010" ref-type="bibr">Imai
  &amp; Tingley, 2010</xref>). While this approach can handle a
  continuous mediator and outcome, as put forward by Imai it only allows
  for a binary treatment. As mentioned above with the
  <monospace>TMLE</monospace> approach, the tool creates a series of
  binary treatment comparisons and connects them to show the user how
  mediation varies as a function of the treatment. An interpretable,
  overall mediation proportion is provided as well.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of Need</title>
  <p>While there are a few established Python packages related to causal
  inference, to the best of the author’s knowledge, there is no Python
  package available that can provide support for continuous treatments
  as <monospace>causal-curve</monospace> does. Similarly, the author
  isn’t aware of any Python implementation of a causal mediation
  analysis for continuous treatments and mediators. Finally, the
  tutorials available in the documentation introduce the concept of
  continuous treatments and are instructive as to how the results of
  their analysis should be interpretted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We acknowledge the valuable feedback from Miguel-Angel Luque, Erica
  Moodie, and Mark van der Laan during the creation of this project.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-GalagateU003A2016">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Galagate</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Causal inference with a continuous treatment and outcome: Alternative estimators for parametric dose-response function with applications.</source>
        <publisher-name>Digital Repository at the University of Maryland</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-MoodieU003A2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Moodie</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Estimation of dose–response functions for longitudinal data using the generalised propensity score.</article-title>
        <source>Statistical Methods in Medical Research</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>21</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0962280209340213</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-HiranoU003A2004">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Imbens</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>The propensity score with continuous treatments</source>
        <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-van_der_LaanU003A2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>van der Laan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Collaborative double robust penalized targeted maximum likelihood estimation.</article-title>
        <source>The International Journal of Biostatistics</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>6</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2202/1557-4679.1181</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ImaiU003A2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>Keele</given-names><suffix>K.</suffix></name>
          <name><surname>Tingley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A General Approach to Causal Mediation Analysis.</article-title>
        <source>Psychological Methods</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0020761</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-HernánU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hernán</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Causal Inference: What If.</source>
        <publisher-name>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
