<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3525</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03525</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>SIMSOPT: A flexible framework for stellarator
optimization</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-7233-577X</contrib-id>
<string-name>Matt Landreman</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-2073-4162</contrib-id>
<string-name>Bharat Medasani</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2195-6522</contrib-id>
<string-name>Florian Wechsung</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4388-2782</contrib-id>
<string-name>Andrew Giuliani</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2941-6571</contrib-id>
<string-name>Rogerio Jorge</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2337-3232</contrib-id>
<string-name>Caoxiang Zhu</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Institute for Research in Electronics and Applied Physics,
University of Maryland, College Park</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-3">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences, New York
University</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-06-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>65</issue>
<fpage>3525</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Python</kwd>
<kwd>plasma</kwd>
<kwd>plasma physics</kwd>
<kwd>magnetohydrodynamics</kwd>
<kwd>optimization</kwd>
<kwd>stellarator</kwd>
<kwd>fusion energy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>A stellarator is a magnetic field configuration used to confine
  plasma, and it is a candidate configuration for fusion energy, as well
  as a general charged particle trap. A stellarator’s magnetic field is
  typically produced using electromagnetic coils, and the shaping of the
  field and coils must be optimized to achieve good confinement. SIMSOPT
  is a collection of software components for carrying out these
  optimizations. These components include</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Interfaces to physics codes, e.g. for magnetohydrodynamic (MHD)
      equilibrium.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Tools for defining objective functions and parameter spaces for
      optimization.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Geometric objects that are important for stellarators –
      surfaces and curves – with several available
      parameterizations.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Implementations of the Biot-Savart law and other magnetic
      fields, including derivatives.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Tools for parallelized finite-difference gradient
      calculations.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>To effectively confine plasmas for the goal of fusion energy, the
  three-dimensional magnetic field of a stellarator has to be carefully
  designed. The design effort is essentially to vary the
  magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) equilibrium to meet multiple metrics, for
  example, MHD stability, neoclassical transport, fast-ion confinement,
  turbulent transport, and buildable coils. This process involves
  calling several physics codes and cannot be done manually. A software
  framework is needed to connect these physics calculations with
  numerical optimization algorithms.</p>
  <p>Although the idea of stellarator optimization is several decades
  old, there are limited codes available to use. The two most commonly
  used codes are STELLOPT
  (<xref alt="Hirshman et al., 1998" rid="ref-STELLOPT_Hirshman" ref-type="bibr">Hirshman
  et al., 1998</xref>;
  <xref alt="Lazerson et al., 2021" rid="ref-STELLOPT_repo" ref-type="bibr">Lazerson
  et al., 2021</xref>;
  <xref alt="Spong et al., 1998" rid="ref-STELLOPT_Spong" ref-type="bibr">Spong
  et al., 1998</xref>) and ROSE
  (<xref alt="Drevlak et al., 2018" rid="ref-ROSE" ref-type="bibr">Drevlak
  et al., 2018</xref>). ROSE is closed-sourced, and STELLOPT has the
  disadvantage that it is written in Fortran and couples all the codes
  explicitly, meaning that it requires modification of multiple core
  STELLOPT source files to write an interface for a new module. The goal
  of SIMSOPT is to flatten the learning curve, improve the flexibility
  for prototyping new problems, and enhance the extendibility and
  maintainability. To achieve these goals, SIMSOPT is written in
  object-oriented Python and incorporates software engineering best
  practices like continuous integration. Modern tools are used in
  SIMSOPT to manage the documentation and unit tests.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="structure">
  <title>Structure</title>
  <p>The components of SIMSOPT that are not performance bottlenecks are
  written in python, for flexibility and ease of use and development. In
  components where performance is critical, compiled C++ code is
  interfaced to python using the <monospace>pybind11</monospace> package
  (<xref alt="Jakob, 2021" rid="ref-pybind" ref-type="bibr">Jakob,
  2021</xref>). As examples, the infrastructure for defining objective
  functions and optimization problems is written in python, whereas the
  Biot-Savart law is implemented in C++.</p>
  <p>Some of the physics modules with compiled code reside in separate
  repositories. Two such modules are the VMEC
  (<xref alt="Hirshman &amp; Whitson, 1983" rid="ref-VMEC1983" ref-type="bibr">Hirshman
  &amp; Whitson, 1983</xref>) and
  SPEC<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>
  (<xref alt="Hudson et al., 2012" rid="ref-SPEC" ref-type="bibr">Hudson
  et al., 2012</xref>;
  <xref alt="Qu et al., 2020" rid="ref-SPEC2" ref-type="bibr">Qu et al.,
  2020</xref>) codes, for MHD equilibrium. These Fortran codes are
  interfaced using the <monospace>f90wrap</monospace> package
  (<xref alt="Kermode, 2020" rid="ref-f90wrap" ref-type="bibr">Kermode,
  2020</xref>), so data can be passed directly in memory to and from
  python. This is particularly useful for passing MPI communicators for
  parallelized evaluation of finite-difference gradients. Another module
  in a separate repository is BOOZ_XFORM
  (<xref alt="Landreman, 2021" rid="ref-booz_xform" ref-type="bibr">Landreman,
  2021</xref>), for calculation of Boozer coordinates. This latter
  repository is a new C++ re-implementation of an algorithm in an older
  fortran 77 code of the same name.</p>
  <p>A variety of geometric objects and magnetic field types are
  included in SIMSOPT. Several discretizations of curves and toroidal
  surfaces are included, since curves are important both in the context
  of electromagnetic coils and the magnetic axis, and flux surfaces are
  a key concept for stellarators. One magnetic field type represents the
  Biot-Savart law, defined by a set of curves and the electric current
  they carry. Other available magnetic field types include Dommaschk
  potentials
  (<xref alt="Dommaschk, 1986" rid="ref-Dommaschk" ref-type="bibr">Dommaschk,
  1986</xref>) and the analytic formula for the field of a circular
  coil, and magnetic field instances can be scaled and summed. All the
  geometric and magnetic field classes provide one or two derivatives,
  either by explicit formulae, or by automatic differentiation with the
  <monospace>jax</monospace> package
  (<xref alt="Bradbury et al., 2018" rid="ref-jax" ref-type="bibr">Bradbury
  et al., 2018</xref>). Caching is done automatically to avoid repeated
  calculations.</p>
  <p>To date, SIMSOPT calculations have primarily used optimization
  algorithms from <monospace>scipy</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Virtanen et al., 2020" rid="ref-scipy" ref-type="bibr">Virtanen
  et al., 2020</xref>). However, since SIMSOPT provides the objective
  function (and, for least-squares problems, the inidividual residual
  terms) as a standard python function handle, it requires minimal
  effort to connect the SIMSOPT objective to outside optimization
  libraries.</p>
  <p>Presently, MPI and OpenMP parallelism are used in different code
  components. The parallelized finite-difference gradient capability
  uses MPI, to support use of multiple compute nodes, and to support
  concurrent calculations with physics codes like VMEC and SPEC that
  employ MPI. Biot-Savart calculations are accelerated using SIMD
  intrinsics (via the xsimd library
  <xref alt="xtensor-stack, 2021" rid="ref-xsimd" ref-type="bibr">xtensor-stack,
  2021</xref>) and OpenMP parallelization.</p>
  <p>SIMSOPT does not presently use input data files to define
  optimization problems, in contrast to STELLOPT. Rather, problems are
  specified using a python driver script, in which objects are defined
  and configured. An advantage of this approach is that any other
  desired scripting elements can be included. One way this capability
  can be used (which is done in the first example below) is to define a
  series of optimization steps, in which the size of the parameter space
  is increased at each step, along with the numerical resolution
  parameters of the codes. The former is valuable to avoid getting stuck
  in a local minimum, and the latter improves computational
  efficiency.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="capabilities">
  <title>Capabilities</title>
  <p>Presently, SIMSOPT provides tools for each of the two optimization
  stages used for the design of stellarators such as W7-X
  (<xref alt="Klinger et al., 2017" rid="ref-Klinger2017" ref-type="bibr">Klinger
  et al., 2017</xref>) and HSX
  (<xref alt="Anderson et al., 1995" rid="ref-Anderson" ref-type="bibr">Anderson
  et al., 1995</xref>). In the first stage, the boundary of a toroidal
  magnetic surface is varied to optimize the physics properties inside
  it. In the second stage, coil shapes are optimized to approximately
  produce the boundary magnetic surface that resulted from the first
  stage.</p>
  <p>For the first stage, MHD equilibria or vacuum fields can be
  represented using the VMEC or SPEC code, or both at the same time.
  VMEC, which makes the assumption that good nested magnetic surfaces
  exist, is extremely robust and many other physics codes are able to
  postprocess its output. In VMEC-based optimizations, a typical
  objective to minimize is the departure from quasisymmetry, a symmetry
  in the field strength that provides good confinement
  (<xref alt="Nührenberg &amp; Zille, 1988" rid="ref-Nuhrenberg" ref-type="bibr">Nührenberg
  &amp; Zille, 1988</xref>). SPEC can provide added value because of its
  ability to represent magnetic islands, which are undesirable since a
  large temperature gradient cannot be supported across them. Islands
  can be eliminated using SIMSOPT by minimizing the magnitude of the
  residues
  (<xref alt="Greene, 1979" rid="ref-Greene" ref-type="bibr">Greene,
  1979</xref>), similar to the method in
  (<xref alt="Hanson &amp; Cary, 1984" rid="ref-Hanson" ref-type="bibr">Hanson
  &amp; Cary, 1984</xref>). An example of stage-1 optimization including
  both VMEC and SPEC simultaneously is shown in
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="figU003Axsections">Figure 1</xref>-<xref alt="Figure 2" rid="figU003Apoincare">Figure 2</xref>.
  Here, the shape is optimized to both eliminate an internal island
  chain, as computed from SPEC, and to achieve quasisymmetry, as
  computed from VMEC and BOOZ_XFORM. More details of this calculation
  can be found in Landreman et al.
  (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-combined_vmec_spec" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>An example of stage-1 optimization using SIMSOPT, in
    which the shape of a toroidal boundary is optimized to eliminate
    magnetic islands and improve quasisymmetry. Shown on the left are
    slices through the surface at different angles
    <inline-formula><alternatives>
    <tex-math><![CDATA[\phi]]></tex-math>
    <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    of the initial and the optimized configuratios.
    <styled-content id="figU003Axsections"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="20210530-01-014-combinedVmecSpecOpt_xsections.pdf" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>VMEC flux surfaces (black lines) and Poincare plot
    computed from the SPEC solution (colored points) for the initial and
    optimized configurations in
    <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="figU003Axsections">Figure 1</xref>. The
    initial configuration contains an island chain, whereas the
    optimized configuration has nested flux
    surfaces.<styled-content id="figU003Apoincare"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="20210530-01-014-combinedVmecSpecOpt_poincare.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>The curve and magnetic field classes in SIMSOPT can then be used
  for the second optimization stage, in which coil shapes are designed.
  Varying the shapes of the coils, derivative-based optimization can be
  used to minimize the normal component of the magnetic field on the
  target surface, similar to the FOCUS code
  (<xref alt="Zhu et al., 2018" rid="ref-focus" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et
  al., 2018</xref>).</p>
  <p>One can also use SIMSOPT for other optimization problems that
  differ from the above two-stage approach. For instance, SIMSOPT is
  presently being used for a single-stage derivative-based method in
  which coil shapes are varied to optimize directly for quasisymmetry
  near the magnetic axis
  (<xref alt="Giuliani et al., 2020" rid="ref-Giuliani" ref-type="bibr">Giuliani
  et al., 2020</xref>).
  <xref alt="Figure 3" rid="figU003Acoils">Figure 3</xref> shows an
  example in which stochastic optimization is applied to find a
  configuration in which the quasisymmetry is relatively insensitive to
  errors in the coil shapes. This example is described in more detail in
  Wechsung et al.
  (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-Wechsung" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>A stellarator obtained using stochasic optimization with
    <monospace>Curve</monospace> and <monospace>BiotSavart</monospace>
    classes from SIMSOPT, with magnetic surfaces computed using
    <monospace>Surface</monospace>
    classes.<styled-content id="figU003Acoils"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="rt_angle.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We gratefully acknowledge discussions with and assistance from
  Aaron Bader, Antoine Baillod, David Bindel, Benjamin Faber, Stuart
  Hudson, Thomas Kruger, Jonathan Schilling, Georg Stadler, and Zhisong
  Qu. This work was supported by a grant from the Simons Foundation
  (560651, ML). BM and CZ are supported by the U.S. Department of Energy
  under Contract No. DE-AC02-09CH11466 through the Princeton Plasma
  Physics Laboratory.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-VMEC1983">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hirshman</surname><given-names>S P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Whitson</surname><given-names>J C</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Steepest-descent moment method for three-dimensional magnetohydrodynamic equilibria</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Fluids</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1983">1983</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.864116</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SPEC">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>S R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dewar</surname><given-names>R L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hole</surname><given-names>M J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>McGann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>von Nessi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lazerson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Computation of multi-region relaxed magnetohydrodynamic equilibria</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Plasmas</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>19</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4765691</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SPEC2">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Z S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pfefferlé</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>S R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Baillod</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dewar</surname><given-names>R L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hole</surname><given-names>M J</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Coordinate parameterisation and spectral method optimisation for Beltrami field solver in stellarator geometry</article-title>
        <source>Plasma Phys. Controlled Fusion</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>62</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1361-6587/abc08e</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Klinger2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Klinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bozhenkov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Burhenn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Dinklage</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Fuchert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Grulke</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Langenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kocsis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Knauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Kramer-Flecken</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Laqua</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lazerson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Landreman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Maassberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Marsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pablant</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pasch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rahbarnia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stange</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Szepesi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Traverso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>J L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wauters</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Windisch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
          <string-name>the Wendelstein 7-X Team</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Performance and properties of the first plasmas of Wendelstein 7-X</article-title>
        <source>Plasma Phys. Controlled Fusion</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0741-3335/59/1/014018</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Anderson">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>F S B</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Almagri</surname><given-names>A F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>D T</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>P G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Talmadge</surname><given-names>J N</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Shohet</surname><given-names>J L</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The helically symmetric experiment, (HSX) goals, design and status</article-title>
        <source>Fusion Tech.</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13182/fst95-a11947086</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Dommaschk">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Dommaschk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Representations for vacuum potentials in stellarators</article-title>
        <source>Comp. Phys. Comm.</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1986">1986</year>
        <volume>40</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0010-4655(86)90109-8</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Greene">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>J M</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A method for determining a stochastic transition</article-title>
        <source>J. Math. Phys.</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1979">1979</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.524170</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Hanson">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>J D</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cary</surname><given-names>J R</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Elimination of stochasticity in stellarators</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Fluids</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1984">1984</year>
        <volume>27</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.864692</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-focus">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>New method to design stellarator coils without the winding surface</article-title>
        <source>Nucl. Fusion</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>58</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1741-4326/aa8e0a</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Giuliani">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Giuliani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wechsung</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cerfon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Landreman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-stage gradient-based stellarator coil design: Optimization for near-axis quasi-symmetry</article-title>
        <source>arXiv:2010.02033</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Nuhrenberg">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Nührenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zille</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Quasi-helically symmetric toroidal stellarators</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Lett. A</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1988">1988</year>
        <volume>129</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0375-9601(88)90080-1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-scipy">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Virtanen</surname><given-names>Pauli</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gommers</surname><given-names>Ralf</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Oliphant</surname><given-names>Travis E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Haberland</surname><given-names>Matt</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>Tyler</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cournapeau</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Burovski</surname><given-names>Evgeni</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>Pearu</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Weckesser</surname><given-names>Warren</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
          <string-name>others</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>SciPy 1.0: Fundamental algorithms for scientific computing in python</article-title>
        <source>Nature methods</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>17</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-019-0686-2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ROSE">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Drevlak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Beidler</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Helander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Turkin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Optimisation of stellarator equilibria with ROSE</article-title>
        <source>Nucl. Fusion</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>59</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1741-4326/aaed50</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-STELLOPT_Hirshman">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Hirshman</surname><given-names>S P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Spong</surname><given-names>D A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Whitson</surname><given-names>J C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>V E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Batchelor</surname><given-names>D B</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Carreras</surname><given-names>B A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rome</surname><given-names>J A</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Transport optimization and MHD stability of a small aspect ratio toroidal hybrid stellarator</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
        <volume>80</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/physrevlett.80.528</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-STELLOPT_Spong">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Spong</surname><given-names>D A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hirshman</surname><given-names>S P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Whitson</surname><given-names>J C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Batchelor</surname><given-names>D B</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Carreras</surname><given-names>B A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>V E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rome</surname><given-names>J A</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>J^* optimization of small aspect ratio stellarator/tokamak hybrid devices</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Plasmas</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
        <volume>5</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.872844</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-STELLOPT_repo">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Lazerson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
          <string-name>et al</string-name>
        </person-group>
        <source>STELLOPT</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <uri>https://github.com/PrincetonUniversity/STELLOPT</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-f90wrap">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kermode</surname><given-names>J R</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>f90wrap: An automated tool for constructing deep python interfaces to modern fortran codes</article-title>
        <source>J. Phys. Condens. Matter</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume>32</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1361-648x/ab82d2</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-pybind">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Jakob</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>pybind11 — Seamless operability between C++11 and Python</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <uri>https://github.com/pybind/pybind11</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-booz_xform">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Landreman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Booz_xform</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <uri>https://github.com/hiddenSymmetries/booz_xform</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-jax">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Frostig</surname><given-names>Roy</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Matthew James</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Maclaurin</surname><given-names>Dougal</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Necula</surname><given-names>George</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Paszke</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>VanderPlas</surname><given-names>Jake</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Wanderman-Milne</surname><given-names>Skye</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Qiao</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>JAX: Composable transformations of Python+NumPy programs</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <uri>http://github.com/google/jax</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-xsimd">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>xtensor-stack</surname></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>xsimd: C++ wrappers for SIMD intrinsics and parallelized, optimized mathematical functions (SSE, AVX, NEON, AVX512)</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <uri>https://github.com/xtensor-stack/xsimd</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-combined_vmec_spec">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Landreman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Medasani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Stellarator optimization for good magnetic surfaces at the same time as quasisymmetry</article-title>
        <source>Phys. Plasmas</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
        <volume>28</volume>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/5.0061665</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-Wechsung">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wechsung</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Giuliani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Landreman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Cerfon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Single-stage gradient-based stellarator coil design: Stochastic optimization</article-title>
        <source>arXiv:2106.12137</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
<fn-group>
  <fn id="fn1">
    <label>1</label><p>It is expected that the SPEC repository will be
    open-source soon, but as of this writing it remains private.</p>
  </fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>
