<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1856</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01856</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>workloopR: Analysis of work loops and other data from
muscle physiology experiments in R</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-9367-8974</contrib-id>
<string-name>Vikram B. Baliga</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-7118-9547</contrib-id>
<string-name>Shreeram Senthivasan</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Department of Zoology, University of British Columbia,
Vancouver, British Colombia, Canada V6T 1Z4</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2019-10-30">
<day>30</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>43</issue>
<fpage>1856</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>muscle physiology</kwd>
<kwd>work loop</kwd>
<kwd>twitch</kwd>
<kwd>tetanus</kwd>
<kwd>ddf</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>The work loop technique
  (<xref alt="Josephson, 1985" rid="ref-JosephsonU003A1985" ref-type="bibr">Josephson,
  1985</xref>) is used in studies of muscle physiology to determine the
  mechanical work and power output of a muscle. After isolating and
  attaching the muscle of interest to a servo motor, the motor induces
  cyclical oscillations of length change to the muscle. An example
  length change trace is shown in Figure
  <xref alt="1" rid="example-workloop">1</xref> (blue; one cycle out of
  several). As this occurs, the muscle is stimulated (grey shading)
  either directly or via its supplying nerve and the force that is
  generated is recorded (red trace). Because mechanical work is the
  product of force and distance, plotting force against length change
  for a particular cycle yields a “work loop”. Work generated during the
  muscle’s shortening phase is considered positive work, whereas work
  during lengthening is negative. Accordingly, the area enclosed within
  a work loop is the net work produced during that cycle.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>An example work loop analysis pipeline. (Left) Raw
    traces are shown for one length change cycle in blue. Stimulation is
    shown in grey shading and muscle force generation is shown in red.
    (Right) Net work is calculated as the difference between work in the
    (Middle) shortening and lengthening
    phases.<styled-content id="example-workloop"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/fig1_workloop.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>Work loop procedures have powerful experimental value and have been
  used to understand the characteristics of whole muscles, fiber
  bundles, and/or single muscle fibers from a wide variety of organisms.
  Using experimental parameters (e.g., length change amplitude,
  frequency of stimulation) that correspond to those shown by an
  organism <italic>in vivo</italic> can help explain muscle performance
  in the context of natural behavior. But since these experimental
  parameters do not need to be constrained to those shown during
  <italic>in vivo</italic> behaviors, the work loop technique affords
  the ability to explore a muscle’s properties beyond (some) natural
  physiological constraints. Ahn
  (<xref alt="2012" rid="ref-AhnU003A2012" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>)
  provides a review of the work loop technique’s importance to the field
  of muscle physiology.</p>
  <p>The ability to import and analyze data from work loop (or other
  muscle physiology ) experiments has been conspicuously absent from
  open-source environments. <monospace>workloopR</monospace> (pronounced
  “work looper”) provides functions for the import, transformation, and
  analysis of muscle physiology experiments in R. As the package’s title
  suggests, our initial motivation was to provide functions to analyze
  work loops to determine net work and power output from the time-course
  of length and force change. Over the course of developing the package,
  we expanded this goal to cover additional types of experiments that
  are often complementary to the work loop technique. Accordingly, there
  are three currently supported experiment types: work loop, simple
  twitch, and tetanus.</p>
  <p>Importing data via functions within the package creates objects of
  class <monospace>muscle_stim</monospace>, which we designed to
  essentially behave as <monospace>data.frame</monospace>s but with
  unique properties that work nicely with
  <monospace>workloopR</monospace>’s core functions. Several of our
  functions are designed to parse information stored in .ddf format
  (e.g., generated by Aurora Scientific’s Dynamic Muscle Control and
  Analysis Software). Time-course data on muscle length change, force
  development, and stimulation pattern are then imported as a
  <monospace>muscle_stim</monospace> object and important metadata and
  protocol information (e.g., specifics of the stimulus train) are
  stored in the object’s attributes. File formats other than .ddf are
  welcome, but need to be coerced into
  <monospace>muscle_stim</monospace> objects by the user using the
  <monospace>as_muscle_stim()</monospace> function.</p>
  <p>Prior to analysis, data can be transformed or corrected. Should
  metadata have been recorded incorrectly, the gear ratio of the motor
  arm and/or the direction of the muscle’s length change can be
  adjusted. Before analyzing work loop data, cycles within the work loop
  can be labeled (according to various definitions of what constitutes a
  “cycle”), which allows calculation of metrics on a per-cycle
  basis.</p>
  <p>Core data analytical functions include
  <monospace>analyze_workloop()</monospace> for work loop files and
  <monospace>isometric_timing()</monospace> for twitch and tetanus
  trials. <monospace>analyze_workloop()</monospace> computes
  instantaneous velocity, net work, instantaneous power, and net power
  for work loop trials on a per-cycle basis.
  <monospace>isometric_timing()</monospace> provides summarization of
  kinetics, i.e. the timing and magnitude of force production at various
  points within the tetanus or twitch trial.</p>
  <p>We also include functions for batch processing files (e.g.,
  multiple files from a common experiment). These functions allow for
  the import, cycle selection, gear ratio correction, and ultimately
  work &amp; power computation for all work loop trial files within a
  specified directory. Our batch analytical pipeline also allows users
  to correct for potential degradation of the muscle (according to power
  &amp; work output) over the course of the experiment.</p>
  <p>Although we do not provide plotting functions, all
  <monospace>muscle_stim</monospace> or
  <monospace>data.frame</monospace> objects produced by our analytical
  functions are designed to be friendly to visualization via either
  base-R plotting or <monospace>tidyverse</monospace> functions.</p>
  <p>Please see Figure <xref alt="2" rid="flowchart">2</xref> below for
  an overview of the <monospace>workloopR</monospace> package with
  recommended functions and vignettes.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Flow chart of suggested analysis pipeline for various
    work loop and isometric
    studies.<styled-content id="flowchart"></styled-content></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/fig2_flowchart.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We thank Doug Altshuler, Jasmin Wong, and Jolan Theriault for help
  they provided throughout the course of this project.</p>
  <p>This work was funded by the U.S. Air Force Office of Scientific
  Research (under grant no. FA9550-16-1-0182, titled “Avian-inspired
  multifunctional morphing vehicles” monitored by B. L. Lee) and also by
  the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada
  (NSERC, RGPIN-2016-05381).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-JosephsonU003A1985">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Josephson</surname><given-names>Robert K</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Mechanical power output from striated muscle during cyclic contraction</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>The Company of Biologists Ltd</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year>
        <volume>114</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>0022-0949</issn>
        <uri>https://jeb.biologists.org/content/114/1/493</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-AhnU003A2012">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>How muscles function - the work loop technique</article-title>
        <source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source>
        <publisher-name>The Company of Biologists Ltd</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>215</volume>
        <issue>7</issue>
        <issn>0022-0949</issn>
        <uri>https://jeb.biologists.org/content/215/7/1051</uri>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.062752</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
