<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">815</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00815</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>NeuNorm: Neutron Imaging Normalization
Library</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-2172-6487</contrib-id>
<string-name>Jean Bilheux</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-05-22">
<day>22</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>29</issue>
<fpage>815</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>normalization</kwd>
<kwd>neutron imaging</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>NeuNorm is an open-source Python library that normalized neutron
  imaging measurements.</p>
  <p>In order to cancel detector electronic noises, source beam
  fluctuations and other pollution signals from close by beam lines,
  every data acquired need to be normalized. In order to perform the
  normalization, one must take, in addition to his data set, either 1 or
  2 extra data set. A set of open beam (OB) when sample has been removed
  but beam is on. An optional set of dark field (DF) is taken when beam
  is off and sample off. The dark field allows to clean the electronic
  noises from the images. The principle of normalization can be
  summarized by the following figure.</p>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="../documentation/source/_static/normalization_principle.png" />
  <p>which is defined by the following equation</p>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="../documentation/source/_static/normalization_equation.png" />
  <p>where In is the image normalized, I the raw image, DF the dark
  field, OB the open beam and i and j the x and y-pixels along the
  images.</p>
  <p>To improve the normalization, the program also allows the user to
  select a region of interest (ROI) in the sample images in order to
  match the background of the raw data with the background of the open
  beam. This is necessary for some beam lines where the fluctuations of
  the beam are too important to be neglected. The program calculates
  then, for each raw data, the average counts of this ROI divided by the
  average counts of the same ROI of the open beams, then apply this
  ratio to the normalized data.</p>
  <p>Input data often contains very hight counts coming from gamma rays.
  Those are also corrected by the program by doing a median filter
  around those “gamma” pixels. How those gamma pixels are determined.
  They are always the highest counts for the input file format.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>This work is sponsored by the Laboratory Directed Research and
  Development Program of Oak Ridge National Laboratory, managed by
  UT-Battelle LLC, under Contract No. DE-AC05-00OR22725 with the U.S.
  Department of Energy. The United States Government retains and the
  publisher, by accepting the article for publication, acknowledges that
  the United States Government retains a non-exclusive, paid-up,
  irrevocable, worldwide license to publish or reproduce the published
  form of this manuscript, or allow others to do so, for United States
  Government purposes. The Department of Energy will provide public
  access to these results of federally sponsored research in accordance
  with the DOE Public Access
  Plan(http://energy.gov/downloads/doe-public-access-plan).</p>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <p>NumPy python library. Stéfan van der Walt and S. Chris Colbert
      and Gaël Varoquaux, The NumPy Array: A Structure for Efficient
      Numerical Computation, Computing in Science &amp; Engineering.
      Volume 13, Number 2, (22-30) 2011</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>SciPy python library. Travis E. Oliphant, SciPy: Open source
      scientific tools for Python, Computing in Science and Engineering,
      Volume 9, (10-20) 2007</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
