<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">739</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.00739</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>rsimsum: Summarise results from Monte Carlo simulation
studies</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8319-7624</contrib-id>
<string-name>Alessandro Gasparini</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Biostatistics Research Group, Department of Health
Sciences, University of Leicester</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2018-05-11">
<day>11</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>26</issue>
<fpage>739</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Monte Carlo simulation study</kwd>
<kwd>simulation</kwd>
<kwd>biostatistics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Monte Carlo simulation studies are numerical methods for conducting
  computer experiments based on generating pseudo-random observations
  from a known truth. Monte Carlo simulation studies - referred from now
  on as <italic>simulation studies</italic> for conciseness - represent
  a powerful tool and have several practical applications in statistical
  and biostatistical research: among others, evaluating new or existing
  statistical methods, comparing them, assessing the impact of modelling
  assumption violations, and helping with the understanding of
  statistical concepts. Establishing properties of current methods is
  necessary to allow using them with confidence; however, sometimes
  properties are very hard (if not impossible) to derive analytically:
  large sample approximation is possible, but evaluating the goodness of
  the approximation to finite samples is required. Approximations often
  require assumptions as well: what are the consequences of violating
  such assumptions? Simulation studies can help answer these questions.
  They can also help answer additional questions such as: is an
  estimator biased in a finite sample? Do confidence intervals for a
  given parameter achieve the desired nominal level of coverage? How
  does a newly developed method compare to an established one? What is
  the power to detect a desired effect size under complex experimental
  settings and analysis methods?</p>
  <p>The increased availability of powerful computational tools (both
  personal and high-performance cluster computers), the perceived
  efficacy, and the emergence of specialist courses and tutorial papers
  on simulation studies
  (<xref alt="Morris et al., 2017" rid="ref-morris_2017" ref-type="bibr">Morris
  et al., 2017</xref>) contributed to the rise of simulation studies in
  the current literature. Despite that, simulation studies are often
  poorly designed, analysed, and reported
  (<xref alt="Morris et al., 2017" rid="ref-morris_2017" ref-type="bibr">Morris
  et al., 2017</xref>): information on data-generating mechanisms
  (DGMs), number of repetitions, software, estimands are often lacking
  or poorly reported, making critical appraisal and replication of
  published studies a difficult task. Another aspect of simulation
  studies that is often poorly reported or not reported at all is the
  Monte Carlo error of summary statistics, defined as the standard
  deviation of the estimated quantity over repeated simulation studies.
  Monte Carlo errors play an important role in understanding the role of
  chance in results of simulation studies and have been showed to be
  severely underreported
  (<xref alt="Koehler et al., 2009" rid="ref-koehler_2009" ref-type="bibr">Koehler
  et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
  <p><monospace>rsimsum</monospace> is an R package that can compute
  summary statistics from simulation studies.
  <monospace>rsimsum</monospace> is modelled upon a similar package
  available in Stata, the user-written command
  <monospace>simsum</monospace>
  (<xref alt="White, 2010" rid="ref-white_2010" ref-type="bibr">White,
  2010</xref>), but - to the best of our knowledge - there is no similar
  package in R. The aim of <monospace>rsimsum</monospace> is to help to
  report simulation studies, including understanding the role of chance
  in results of simulation studies: Monte Carlo standard errors and
  confidence intervals based on them are computed and presented to the
  user by default. <monospace>rsimsum</monospace> can compute a wide
  variety of summary statistics: bias, empirical and model-based
  standard errors, relative precision, relative error in model standard
  error, mean squared error, coverage, bias. Further details on each
  summary statistic are presented elsewhere
  (<xref alt="Morris et al., 2017" rid="ref-morris_2017" ref-type="bibr">Morris
  et al., 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="White, 2010" rid="ref-white_2010" ref-type="bibr">White,
  2010</xref>).</p>
  <p>The main function of <monospace>rsimsum</monospace> is called
  <monospace>simsum</monospace> and can handle simulation studies with a
  single estimand of interest at a time. Missing values are excluded by
  default, and it is possible to define boundary values to drop
  estimated values or standard errors exceeding such limits
  (e.g. standardised values larger than 10). It is possible to define a
  variable representing methods compared with the simulation study, and
  it is possible to define factors that vary between the different
  simulated scenarios (data-generating mechanisms, DGMs). However,
  methods and DGMs are not strictly required: in that case, a simulation
  study with a single scenario and a single method is assumed. Finally,
  <monospace>rsimsum</monospace> provides a function named
  <monospace>multisimsum</monospace> that allows summarising simulation
  studies with multiple estimands as well.</p>
  <p>An important step of reporting a simulation study consists in
  visualising the results; therefore, <monospace>rsimsum</monospace>
  exploits the R package <monospace>ggplot2</monospace>
  (<xref alt="Wickham, 2009" rid="ref-ggplot2" ref-type="bibr">Wickham,
  2009</xref>) to produce a portfolio of opinionated data visualisations
  for quick exploration of results, inferring colours and facetting by
  data-generating mechanisms. <monospace>rsimsum</monospace> includes
  methods to produce (1) plots of summary statistics with confidence
  intervals based on Monte Carlo standard errors (forest plots, bar
  plots, and lolly plots), (2) zip plots to graphically visualise
  coverage by directly plotting confidence intervals
  (<xref alt="Morris et al., 2017" rid="ref-morris_2017" ref-type="bibr">Morris
  et al., 2017</xref>), and (3) heat plots. The latter is a
  visualisation type that has not been traditionally used to present
  results of simulation studies, and consists in a mosaic plot where the
  factor on the x-axis is the methods compared with the current
  simulation study and the factor on the y-axis is one of the
  data-generating factors, as selected by the user: see for instance
  Figure 1, which can be obtained via a single function call with
  <monospace>rsimsum</monospace>. Each tile of the mosaic plot is
  coloured according to the value of the summary statistic of interest,
  with a red colour representing values above the target value and a
  blue colour representing values below the target.</p>
  <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="plot.png" />
  <bold>Figure 1:</bold> example of heat plot that can be obtained with
  <monospace>rsimsum</monospace> via a single function call. The example
  data comes from a simulation study on model misspecification in
  survival models, and it is bundled with <monospace>rsimsum</monospace>
  (see
  <monospace>help(&quot;relhaz&quot;, package = &quot;rsimsum&quot;)</monospace>).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-morris_2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>Tim P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>Ian R</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Crowther</surname><given-names>Michael J</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Using simulation studies to evaluate statistical methods</article-title>
        <source>arXiv preprint arXiv:1712.03198</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-koehler_2009">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Haneuse</surname><given-names>Sebastien JPA</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>On the assessment of Monte Carlo error in simulation-based statistical analyses</article-title>
        <source>The American Statistician</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
        <volume>63</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1198/tast.2009.0030</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-white_2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>Ian R</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Simsum: Analyses of simulation studies including monte carlo error</article-title>
        <source>The Stata Journal</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <volume>10</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-ggplot2">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>Hadley</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>ggplot2: Elegant graphics for data analysis</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag New York</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
        <isbn>978-0-387-98140-6</isbn>
        <uri>http://ggplot2.org</uri>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
