<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2871</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.02871</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>UQit: A Python package for uncertainty quantification
(UQ) in computational fluid dynamics (CFD)</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-9610-9910</contrib-id>
<string-name>Saleh Rezaeiravesh</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1"><sup>*</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Ricardo Vinuesa</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Philipp Schlatter</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>SimEx/FLOW, Engineering Mechanics, KTH Royal Institute of
Technology,</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Swedish e-Science Research Centre (SeRC), Stockholm,
Sweden</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">* E-mail: <email></email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2020-11-09">
<day>9</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>60</issue>
<fpage>2871</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>uncertainty quantification (UQ)</kwd>
<kwd>computational fluid dynamics (CFD)</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>In computational physics, mathematical models are numerically
  solved and as a result, realizations for the quantities of interest
  (QoIs) are obtained. Even when adopting the most accurate numerical
  methods for deterministic mathematical models, the QoIs can still be
  up to some extent uncertain. Uncertainty is defined as the lack of
  certainty and it originates from the lack, impropriety or
  insufficiency of knowledge and information
  (<xref alt="Ghanem et al., 2017" rid="ref-GhanemU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Ghanem
  et al., 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Smith, 2013" rid="ref-SmithU003A2013" ref-type="bibr">Smith,
  2013</xref>). It is important to note that for a QoI, uncertainty is
  different from error which is defined as the deviation of a
  realization from a reference (true) value. In computational models,
  various sources of uncertainties may exist. These include, but not
  limited to, the fidelity of the mathematical model (i.e., the extent
  by which the model can reflect the truth), the parameters in the
  models, initial data and boundary conditions, finite sampling time
  when computing the time-averaged QoIs, the way numerical errors
  interact and evolve, computer arithmetic, coding bugs, geometrical
  uncertainties, etc. Various mathematical and statistical techniques
  gathered under the umbrella of uncertainty quantification (UQ) can be
  exploited to assess the uncertainty in different models and their QoIs
  (<xref alt="Ghanem et al., 2017" rid="ref-GhanemU003A2017" ref-type="bibr">Ghanem
  et al., 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Smith, 2013" rid="ref-SmithU003A2013" ref-type="bibr">Smith,
  2013</xref>). The UQ techniques not only facilitate systematic
  evaluation of validation and verification metrics, but also play a
  vital role in evaluation of the confidence and reliability of the data
  acquired in computations and experiments. Note that accurate
  accounting for such confidence intervals is crucial in data-driven
  engineering designs.</p>
  <p>In general, uncertainties can be divided into two main categories:
  aleatoric and epistemic
  (<xref alt="Smith, 2013" rid="ref-SmithU003A2013" ref-type="bibr">Smith,
  2013</xref>). The aleatoric uncertainties are random, inherent in the
  models, and hence, cannot be removed. In contrast, epistemic
  uncertainties originate from using simplified models, insufficient
  data, etc. Therefore, they can be reduced, for instance, through
  improving the models. As a general strategy in UQ, we try to
  reformulate the epistemic uncertainties in terms of aleatoric
  uncertainties so that probabilistic approaches can be applied. To
  implement the resulting framework, we can adopt a non-intrusive point
  of view which does not require the computational codes, hereafter
  simulators, to be modified. As a result, the UQ techniques can be
  combined with different features of computer experiments
  (<xref alt="Santner et al., 2003" rid="ref-SantnerU003A2003" ref-type="bibr">Santner
  et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
  <p>These strategies constitute the foundations of developing
  <monospace>UQit</monospace>, a Python package for uncertainty
  quantification in computational physics, in general, and computational
  fluid dynamics (CFD), in particular. In CFD, the Navier-Stokes
  equations are numerically integrated as a model of fluid flows. The
  flows are, in general, three-dimensional and time-dependent (unsteady)
  and at most of the Reynolds numbers relevant to practical
  applications, turbulent. A wide range of approaches has been used for
  numerical modeling of turbulence
  (<xref alt="Sagaut et al., 2013" rid="ref-SagautU003A2013" ref-type="bibr">Sagaut
  et al., 2013</xref>). Moving from low- toward high-fidelity
  approaches, the nature of the uncertainties inherent in the
  simulations change from model-based to numerical-driven. Regardless of
  the approach, we may need to study the influence of different factors
  on the simulations QoIs, where UQ techniques are beneficial.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need-design">
  <title>Statement of need &amp; Design</title>
  <p>Performing different types of UQ analyses in CFD is so important
  that it has been considered as one of the required technologies in the
  NASA CFD vision 2030
  (<xref alt="Slotnick et al., 2014" rid="ref-SlotnickU003A2014" ref-type="bibr">Slotnick
  et al., 2014</xref>). In this regard, <monospace>UQit</monospace> can
  be seen as a good match noting that it can be (one of) the first
  Python-based open-source packages for UQ in CFD. In fact, there are
  many similarities as well as connections between UQ and the techniques
  in the fields of machine learning and data sciences in which Python
  libraries are rich. These besides the flexible design of
  <monospace>UQit</monospace> provide a good potential for further
  development of <monospace>UQit</monospace> in response to different
  needs coming up in particular applications. Due to the non-intrusive
  nature of the implemented UQ techniques, <monospace>UQit</monospace>
  treats the CFD simulator as a blackbox, therefore it can be linked to
  any CFD simulator conditioned on having an appropriate interface. As a
  possible future development, a Python VTK interface can be considered
  for the purpose of in-situ UQ analyses which will be suitable for
  large-scale simulations of fluid flows on supercomputers without the
  need of storing large data sets.</p>
  <p>The documentation for each UQ technique in
  <monospace>UQit</monospace> starts from providing an overview of the
  theoretical background and introducing the main relevant references.
  These are followed by the details of implementation, instructions on
  how to use the method, and notebooks. The examples in each notebook
  are exploited not only as a user guide, but also as a way to verify
  and validate the implementations in <monospace>UQit</monospace>
  through comparison of the results with reference data. Considering
  these aspects, <monospace>UQit</monospace> provides an appropriate
  environment for pedagogical purposes when it comes to practical guides
  to UQ approaches.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="features">
  <title>Features</title>
  <p>Here, a short summary of the main UQ techniques implemented in
  <monospace>UQit</monospace> is given. In general, the methods are
  implemented at the highest required flexibility and they can be
  applied to any number of uncertain parameters. For the theoretical
  background, further details, and different applications in CFD, see
  our recent paper
  (<xref alt="Rezaeiravesh et al., 2020" rid="ref-RezaeiraveshU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Rezaeiravesh
  et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
  <p><bold>Surrogates</bold> play a key role in conducting non-intrusive
  UQ analyses and computer experiments. They establish a functional
  relation between the simulator outputs (or QoIs) and the model inputs
  and parameters. The surrogates are constructed based on a limited
  number of training data and once constructed, they are much less
  expensive to run than the simulators. <monospace>UQit</monospace> uses
  different approaches to construct surrogates, including Lagrange
  interpolation, polynomial chaos expansion
  (<xref alt="Xiu, 2010" rid="ref-XiuU003A2010" ref-type="bibr">Xiu,
  2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="Xiu &amp; Karniadakis, 2002" rid="ref-XiuU003A2002" ref-type="bibr">Xiu
  &amp; Karniadakis, 2002</xref>), and Gaussian process regression
  (<xref alt="Gramacy, 2020" rid="ref-GramacyU003A2020" ref-type="bibr">Gramacy,
  2020</xref>;
  <xref alt="Rasmussen &amp; Williams, 2005" rid="ref-RasmussenU003A2005" ref-type="bibr">Rasmussen
  &amp; Williams, 2005</xref>). In developing
  <monospace>UQit</monospace>, a high level of flexibility in
  constructing GPR surrogates has been considered especially when it
  comes to incorporating the observational uncertainties.</p>
  <p>The goal of <bold>uncertainty propagation</bold> or <bold>UQ
  forward problem</bold> is to estimate how the known uncertainties in
  the inputs and parameters propagate into the QoIs. In
  <monospace>UQit</monospace>, these problems are efficiently handled
  using non-intrusive generalized polynomial chaos expansion (PCE)
  (<xref alt="Xiu, 2010" rid="ref-XiuU003A2010" ref-type="bibr">Xiu,
  2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="Xiu &amp; Karniadakis, 2002" rid="ref-XiuU003A2002" ref-type="bibr">Xiu
  &amp; Karniadakis, 2002</xref>). For constructing a PCE,
  <monospace>UQit</monospace> offers a diverse set of options for the
  schemes of truncating the expansion, types of parameter samples, and
  methods to compute the coefficients in the expansion. For the latter,
  regression and projection methods can be adopted. As a useful feature
  for computationally expensive CFD simulations, the compressed sensing
  method can be utilized when the number of training samples is less
  than the number of terms in the expansion. By combining standard PCE
  and GPR, <monospace>UQit</monospace> provides the novel probabilistic
  PCE which is applicable to many CFD applications.</p>
  <p><bold>Global sensitivity analysis</bold> is performed to quantify
  the sensitivity of the QoIs with respect to the uncertain inputs and
  parameters. Contrary to the local sensitivity analysis, in GSA all
  parameters are allowed to vary simultaneously and no linearization is
  involved in computing sensitivities. In <monospace>UQit</monospace>,
  Sobol Sensitivity Indices (main, interaction, and total)
  (<xref alt="Sobol, 2001" rid="ref-SobolU003A2001" ref-type="bibr">Sobol,
  2001</xref>) are computed as indicators of GSA.</p>
  <p>Driven by the needs, different features will be developed and added
  to <monospace>UQit</monospace> in future.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgments">
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>
  <p>This work has been supported by the EXCELLERAT project which has
  received funding from the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and
  innovation programme under grant agreement No 823691. The financial
  support by the Linné FLOW Centre at KTH for SR is gratefully
  acknowledged. PS and SR acknowledge financial support by the Knut and
  Alice Wallenberg Foundation as part of the Wallenberg Academy Fellow
  programme.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-RasmussenU003A2005">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>Carl Edward</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Christopher K. I.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Gaussian processes for machine learning (adaptive computation and machine learning)</source>
        <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
        <isbn>026218253X</isbn>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SantnerU003A2003">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Santner</surname><given-names>Thomas J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Brian J.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Notz</surname><given-names>William I.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>The design and analysis of computer experiments</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4757-3799-8</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-GhanemU003A2017">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <source>Handbook of uncertainty quantification</source>
        <person-group person-group-type="editor">
          <name><surname>Ghanem</surname><given-names>Roger</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Higdon</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Owhadi</surname><given-names>Houman</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-12385-1</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-GramacyU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Gramacy</surname><given-names>Robert B.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Surrogates: Gaussian process modeling, design and optimization for the applied sciences</source>
        <publisher-name>Chapman Hall/CRC</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, Florida</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <isbn>9781000766523</isbn>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-XiuU003A2002">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Xiu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Karniadakis</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>The Wiener–Askey polynomial chaos for stochastic differential equations</article-title>
        <source>SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
        <volume>24</volume>
        <issue>2</issue>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/S1064827501387826</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-XiuU003A2010">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Xiu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Numerical methods for stochastic computations: A spectral method approach</source>
        <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ, USA</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
        <isbn>9781400835348</isbn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctv7h0skv</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SobolU003A2001">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Sobol</surname><given-names>I. M</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Global sensitivity indices for nonlinear mathematical models and their Monte Carlo estimates</article-title>
        <source>Mathematics and Computers in Simulation</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year>
        <volume>55</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
        <issn>0378-4754</issn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-4754(00)00270-6</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-RezaeiraveshU003A2020">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Rezaeiravesh</surname><given-names>Saleh</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Vinuesa</surname><given-names>Ricardo</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Schlatter</surname><given-names>Philipp</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An uncertainty-quantification framework for assessing accuracy, sensitivity, and robustness in computational fluid dynamics</article-title>
        <source>arXiv:2007.07071</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
        <volume></volume>
        <issue></issue>
        <issn></issn>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SlotnickU003A2014">
      <element-citation publication-type="pamphlet">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Slotnick</surname><given-names>J P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Khodadoust</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J J</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Darmofal</surname><given-names>D L</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Gropp</surname><given-names>W D</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>E A</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Mavriplis</surname><given-names>D J</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>CFD vision 2030 study: A path to revolutionary computational aerosciences</article-title>
        <source>NASA Technical Report</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SmithU003A2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Uncertainty quantification: Theory, implementation, and applications</source>
        <publisher-name>Society for Industrial; Applied Mathematics</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA, USA</publisher-loc>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <isbn>9781611973211</isbn>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-SagautU003A2013">
      <element-citation publication-type="book">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Sagaut</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Deck</surname><given-names>Sebastian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Terracol</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <source>Multiscale and multiresolution approaches in turbulence: LES, DES and hybrid RANS/LES methods: Applications and guidelines</source>
        <publisher-name>Imperial College Press</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
        <isbn>9781848169876</isbn>
        <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/p878</pub-id>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
